<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<tractatus>
  <proposition id="1*" depth="0">
    <german>Die Welt ist alles, was der Fall ist.</german>
    <ogden>The world is everything that is the case.</ogden>
    <pears_mcguinness>The world is all that is the case.</pears_mcguinness>
  </proposition>
  <proposition id="1.1" depth="1">
    <german>Die Welt ist die Gesamtheit der Tatsachen, nicht der Dinge.</german>
    <ogden>The world is the totality of facts, not of things.</ogden>
    <pears_mcguinness>The world is the totality of facts, not of things.</pears_mcguinness>
  </proposition>
  <proposition id="1.11" depth="2">
    <german>Die Welt ist durch die Tatsachen bestimmt und dadurch, dass es alle Tatsachen sind.</german>
    <ogden>The world is determined by the facts, and by these being all the facts.</ogden>
    <pears_mcguinness>The world is determined by the facts, and by their being all the facts.</pears_mcguinness>
  </proposition>
  <proposition id="1.12" depth="2">
    <german>Denn, die Gesamtheit der Tatsachen bestimmt, was der Fall ist und auch, was alles nicht der Fall ist.</german>
    <ogden>For the totality of facts determines both what is the case, and also all that is not the case.</ogden>
    <pears_mcguinness>For the totality of facts determines what is the case, and also whatever is not the case.</pears_mcguinness>
  </proposition>
  <proposition id="1.13" depth="2">
    <german>Die Tatsachen im logischen Raum sind die Welt.</german>
    <ogden>The facts in logical space are the world.</ogden>
    <pears_mcguinness>The facts in logical space are the world.</pears_mcguinness>
  </proposition>
  <proposition id="1.2" depth="1">
    <german>Die Welt zerfällt in Tatsachen.</german>
    <ogden>The world divides into facts.</ogden>
    <pears_mcguinness>The world divides into facts.</pears_mcguinness>
  </proposition>
  <proposition id="1.21" depth="2">
    <german>Eines kann der Fall sein oder nicht der Fall sein und alles übrige gleich bleiben.</german>
    <ogden>Any one can either be the case or not be the case, and everything else remain the same.</ogden>
    <pears_mcguinness>Each item can be the case or not the case while everything else remains the same.</pears_mcguinness>
  </proposition>
  <proposition id="2" depth="0">
    <german>Was der Fall ist, die Tatsache, ist das Bestehen von Sachverhalten.</german>
    <ogden>What is the case, the fact, is the existence of atomic facts.</ogden>
    <pears_mcguinness>What is the case—a fact—is the existence of states of affairs.</pears_mcguinness>
    <proposition id="2.01" depth="2">
      <german>Der Sachverhalt ist eine Verbindung von Gegenständen. (Sachen, Dingen.)</german>
      <ogden>An atomic fact is a combination of objects (entities, things).</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>A state of affairs (a state of things) is a combination of objects (things).</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.011" depth="3">
      <german>Es ist dem Ding wesentlich, der Bestandteil eines Sachverhaltes sein zu können.</german>
      <ogden>It is essential to a thing that it can be a constituent part of an atomic fact.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>It is essential to things that they should be possible constituents of states of affairs.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.012" depth="3">
      <german>In der Logik ist nichts zufällig: Wenn das Ding im Sachverhalt vorkommen kann , so muss die Möglichkeit des Sachverhaltes im Ding bereits präjudiziert sein.</german>
      <ogden>In logic nothing is accidental: if a thing can occur in an atomic fact the possibility of that atomic fact must already be prejudged in the thing.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>In logic nothing is accidental: if a thing can occur in a state of affairs, the possibility of the state of affairs must be written into the thing itself.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.0121" depth="4">
      <german>Es erschiene gleichsam als Zufall, wenn dem Ding, das allein für sich bestehen könnte, nachträglich eine Sachlage passen würde.</german>
      <ogden>It would, so to speak, appear as an accident, when to a thing that could exist alone on its own account, subsequently a state of affairs could be made to fit.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>It would seem to be a sort of accident, if it turned out that a situation would fit a thing that could already exist entirely on its own.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.0122" depth="4">
      <german>Das Ding ist selbständig, insofern es in allen möglichen Sachlagen vorkommen kann, aber diese Form der Selbständigkeit ist eine Form des Zusammenhangs mit dem Sachverhalt, eine Form der Unselbständigkeit. (Es ist unmöglich, dass Worte in zwei verschiedenen Weisen auftreten, allein und im Satz.)</german>
      <ogden>The thing is independent, in so far as it can occur in all possible circumstances, but this form of independence is a form of connexion with the atomic fact, a form of dependence. (It is impossible for words to occur in two different ways, alone and in the proposition.)</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Things are independent in so far as they can occur in all possible situations, but this form of independence is a form of connexion with states of affairs, a form of dependence. (It is impossible for words to appear in two different roles: by themselves, and in propositions.)</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.0123" depth="4">
      <german>Wenn ich den Gegenstand kenne, so kenne ich auch sämtliche Möglichkeiten seines Vorkommens in Sachverhalten.</german>
      <ogden>If I know an object, then I also know all the possibilities of its occurrence in atomic facts.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>If I know an object I also know all its possible occurrences in states of affairs.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.01231" depth="5">
      <german>Um einen Gegenstand zu kennen, muss ich zwar nicht seine externen – aber ich muss alle seine internen Eigenschaften kennen.</german>
      <ogden>In order to know an object, I must know not its external but all its internal qualities.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>If I am to know an object, though I need not know its external properties, I must know all its internal properties.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.0124" depth="4">
      <german>Sind alle Gegenstände gegeben, so sind damit auch alle möglichen Sachverhalte gegeben.</german>
      <ogden>If all objects are given, then thereby are all possible atomic facts also given.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>If all objects are given, then at the same time all possible states of affairs are also given.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.013" depth="3">
      <german>Jedes Ding ist, gleichsam, in einem Raume möglicher Sachverhalte. Diesen Raum kann ich mir leer denken, nicht aber das Ding ohne den Raum.</german>
      <ogden>Every thing is, as it were, in a space of possible atomic facts. I can think of this space as empty, but not of the thing without the space.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Each thing is, as it were, in a space of possible states of affairs. This space I can imagine empty, but I cannot imagine the thing without the space.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.0131" depth="4">
      <german>Der räumliche Gegenstand muss im unendlichen Raume liegen. (Der Raumpunkt ist eine Argumentstelle.)</german>
      <ogden>A spatial object must lie in infinite space. (A point in space is an argument place.)</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>A spatial object must be situated in infinite space. (A spatial point is an argument-place.)</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.014" depth="3">
      <german>Die Gegenstände enthalten die Möglichkeit aller Sachlagen.</german>
      <ogden>Objects contain the possibility of all states of affairs.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Objects contain the possibility of all situations.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.0141" depth="4">
      <german>Die Möglichkeit seines Vorkommens in Sachverhalten, ist die Form des Gegenstandes.</german>
      <ogden>The possibility of its occurrence in atomic facts is the form of the object.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The possibility of its occurring in states of affairs is the form of an object.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.02" depth="2">
      <german>Der Gegenstand ist einfach.</german>
      <ogden>The object is simple.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Objects are simple.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.0201" depth="4">
      <german>Jede Aussage über Komplexe lässt sich in eine Aussage über deren Bestandteile und in diejenigen Sätze zerlegen, welche die Komplexe vollständig beschreiben.</german>
      <ogden>Every statement about complexes can be analysed into a statement about their constituent parts, and into those propositions which completely describe the complexes.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Every statement about complexes can be resolved into a statement about their constituents and into the propositions that describe the complexes completely.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.021" depth="3">
      <german>Die Gegenstände bilden die Substanz der Welt. Darum können sie nicht zusammengesetzt sein.</german>
      <ogden>Objects form the substance of the world. Therefore they cannot be compound.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Objects make up the substance of the world. That is why they cannot be composite.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.0211" depth="4">
      <german>Hätte die Welt keine Substanz, so würde, ob ein Satz Sinn hat, davon abhängen, ob ein anderer Satz wahr ist.</german>
      <ogden>If the world had no substance, then whether a proposition had sense would depend on whether another proposition was true.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>If the world had no substance, then whether a proposition had sense would depend on whether another proposition was true.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.0212" depth="4">
      <german>Es wäre dann unmöglich, ein Bild der Welt (wahr oder falsch) zu entwerfen.</german>
      <ogden>It would then be impossible to form a picture of the world (true or false).</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>In that case we could not sketch any picture of the world (true or false).</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.022" depth="3">
      <german>Es ist offenbar, dass auch eine von der wirklichen noch so verschieden gedachte Welt Etwas – eine Form – mit der wirklichen gemein haben muss.</german>
      <ogden>It is clear that however different from the real one an imagined world may be, it must have something—a form—in common with the real world.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>It is obvious that an imagined world, however different it may be from the real one, must have something —a form—in common with it.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.023" depth="3">
      <german>Diese feste Form besteht eben aus den Gegenständen.</german>
      <ogden>This fixed form consists of the objects.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Objects are just what constitute this unalterable form.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.0231" depth="4">
      <german>Die Substanz der Welt kann nur eine Form und keine materiellen Eigenschaften bestimmen. Denn diese werden erst durch die Sätze dargestellt – erst durch die Konfiguration der Gegenstände gebildet.</german>
      <ogden>The substance of the world can only determine a form and not any material properties. For these are first presented by the propositions—first formed by the configuration of the objects.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The substance of the world can only determine a form, and not any material properties. For it is only by means of propositions that material properties are represented—only by the configuration of objects that they are produced.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.0232" depth="4">
      <german>Beiläufig gesprochen: Die Gegenstände sind farblos.</german>
      <ogden>Roughly speaking: objects are colourless.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>In a manner of speaking, objects are colourless.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.0233" depth="4">
      <german>Zwei Gegenstände von der gleichen logischen Form sind – abgesehen von ihren externen Eigenschaften – von einander nur dadurch unterschieden, dass sie verschieden sind.</german>
      <ogden>Two objects of the same logical form are—apart from their external properties—only differentiated from one another in that they are different.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>If two objects have the same logical form, the only distinction between them, apart from their external properties, is that they are different.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.02331" depth="5">
      <german>Entweder ein Ding hat Eigenschaften, die kein anderes hat, dann kann man es ohneweiteres durch eine Beschreibung aus den anderen herausheben, und darauf hinweisen; oder aber, es gibt mehrere Dinge, die ihre sämtlichen Eigenschaften gemeinsam haben, dann ist es überhaupt unmöglich auf eines von ihnen zu zeigen.</german>
      <ogden>Either a thing has properties which no other has, and then one can distinguish it straight away from  the others by a description and refer to it; or, on the other hand, there are several things which have the totality of their properties in common, and then it is quite impossible to point to any one of them.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Either a thing has properties that nothing else has, in which case we can immediately use a description to distinguish it from the others and refer to it; or, on the other hand, there are several things that have the whole set of their properties in common, in which case it is quite impossible to indicate one of them.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.024" depth="3">
      <german>Die Substanz ist das, was unabhängig von dem was der Fall ist, besteht.</german>
      <ogden>Substance is what exists independently of what is the case.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The substance is what subsists independently of what is the case.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.025" depth="3">
      <german>Sie ist Form und Inhalt.</german>
      <ogden>It is form and content.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>It is form and content.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.0251" depth="4">
      <german>Raum, Zeit und Farbe (Färbigkeit) sind Formen der Gegenstände.</german>
      <ogden>Space, time and colour (colouredness) are forms of objects.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Space, time, colour (being coloured) are forms of objects.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.026" depth="3">
      <german>Nur wenn es Gegenstände gibt, kann es eine feste Form der Welt geben.</german>
      <ogden>Only if there are objects can there be a fixed form of the world.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>There must be objects, if the world is to have unalterable form.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.027" depth="3">
      <german>Das Feste, das Bestehende und der Gegenstand sind Eins.</german>
      <ogden>The fixed, the existent and the object are one.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Objects, the unalterable, and the subsistent are one and the same.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.0271" depth="4">
      <german>Der Gegenstand ist das Feste, Bestehende; die Konfiguration ist das Wechselnde, Unbeständige.</german>
      <ogden>The object is the fixed, the existent; the configuration is the changing, the variable.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Objects are what is unalterable and subsistent; their configuration is what is changing and unstable.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.0272" depth="4">
      <german>Die Konfiguration der Gegenstände bildet den Sachverhalt.</german>
      <ogden>The configuration of the objects forms the atomic fact.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The configuration of objects produces states of affairs.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.03" depth="2">
      <german>Im Sachverhalt hängen die Gegenstände ineinander, wie die Glieder einer Kette.</german>
      <ogden>In the atomic fact objects hang one in another, like the links of a chain.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>In a state of affairs objects fit into one another like the links of a chain.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.031" depth="3">
      <german>Im Sachverhalt verhalten sich die Gegenstände in bestimmter Art und Weise zueinander.</german>
      <ogden>In the atomic fact the objects are combined in a definite way.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>In a state of affairs objects stand in a determinate relation to one another.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.032" depth="3">
      <german>Die Art und Weise, wie die Gegenstände im Sachverhalt zusammenhängen, ist die Struktur des Sachverhaltes.</german>
      <ogden>The way in which objects hang together in the atomic fact is the structure of the atomic fact.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The determinate way in which objects are connected in a state of affairs is the structure of the state of affairs.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.033" depth="3">
      <german>Die Form ist die Möglichkeit der Struktur.</german>
      <ogden>The form is the possibility of the structure.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Form is the possibility of structure.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.034" depth="3">
      <german>Die Struktur der Tatsache besteht aus den Strukturen der Sachverhalte.</german>
      <ogden>The structure of the fact consists of the structures of the atomic facts.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The structure of a fact consists of the structures of states of affairs.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.04" depth="2">
      <german>Die Gesamtheit der bestehenden Sachverhalte ist die Welt.</german>
      <ogden>The totality of existent atomic facts is the world.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The totality of existing states of affairs is the world.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.05" depth="2">
      <german>Die Gesamtheit der bestehenden Sachverhalte bestimmt auch, welche Sachverhalte nicht bestehen.</german>
      <ogden>The totality of existent atomic facts also determines which atomic facts do not exist.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The totality of existing states of affairs also determines which states of affairs do not exist.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.06" depth="2">
      <german>Das Bestehen und Nichtbestehen von Sachverhalten ist die Wirklichkeit.</german>
      <ogden>The existence and non-existence of atomic facts is the reality.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The existence and non-existence of states of affairs is reality.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.061" depth="3">
      <german>Die Sachverhalte sind von einander unabhängig.</german>
      <ogden>Atomic facts are independent of one another.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>States of affairs are independent of one another.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.062" depth="3">
      <german>Aus dem Bestehen oder Nichtbestehen eines Sachverhaltes kann nicht auf das Bestehen oder Nichtbestehen eines anderen geschlossen werden.</german>
      <ogden>From the existence or non-existence of an atomic fact we cannot infer the existence or non-existence of another.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>From the existence or non-existence of one state of affairs it is impossible to infer the existence or non-existence of another.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.063" depth="3">
      <german>Die gesamte Wirklichkeit ist die Welt.</german>
      <ogden>The total reality is the world.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The sum-total of reality is the world.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.1" depth="1">
      <german>Wir machen uns Bilder der Tatsachen.</german>
      <ogden>We make to ourselves pictures of facts.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>We picture facts to ourselves.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.11" depth="2">
      <german>Das Bild stellt die Sachlage im logischen Raume, das Bestehen und Nichtbestehen von Sachverhalten vor.</german>
      <ogden>The picture presents the facts in logical space, the existence and non-existence of atomic facts.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>A picture presents a situation in logical space, the existence and non-existence of states of affairs.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.12" depth="2">
      <german>Das Bild ist ein Modell der Wirklichkeit.</german>
      <ogden>The picture is a model of reality.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>A picture is a model of reality.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.13" depth="2">
      <german>Den Gegenständen entsprechen im Bilde die Elemente des Bildes.</german>
      <ogden>To the objects correspond in the picture the elements of the picture.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>In a picture objects have the elements of the picture corresponding to them.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.131" depth="3">
      <german>Die Elemente des Bildes vertreten im Bild die Gegenstände.</german>
      <ogden>The elements of the picture stand, in the picture, for the objects.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>In a picture the elements of the picture are the representatives of objects.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.14" depth="2">
      <german>Das Bild besteht darin, dass sich seine Elemente in bestimmter Art und Weise zu einander verhalten.</german>
      <ogden>The picture consists in the fact that its elements are combined with one another in a definite way.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>What constitutes a picture is that its elements are related to one another in a determinate way.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.141" depth="3">
      <german>Das Bild ist eine Tatsache.</german>
      <ogden>The picture is a fact.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>A picture is a fact.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.15" depth="2">
      <german>Dass sich die Elemente des Bildes in bestimmter Art und Weise zu einander verhalten, stellt vor, dass sich die Sachen so zu einander verhalten.</german>
      <ogden>That the elements of the picture are combined with one another in a definite way, represents that the things are so combined with one another.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The fact that the elements of a picture are related to one another in a determinate way represents that things are related to one another in the same way.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.151" depth="3">
      <german>Die Form der Abbildung ist die Möglichkeit, dass sich die Dinge so zu einander verhalten, wie die Elemente des Bildes.</german>
      <ogden>The form of representation is the possibility that the things are combined with one another as are the elements of the picture.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Pictorial form is the possibility that things are related to one another in the same way as the elements of the picture.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.1511" depth="4">
      <german>Das Bild ist so mit der Wirklichkeit verknüpft – es reicht bis zu ihr.</german>
      <ogden>Thus the picture is linked with reality; it reaches up to it.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>That is how a picture is attached to reality; it reaches right out to it.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.1512" depth="4">
      <german>Es ist wie ein Maßstab an die Wirklichkeit angelegt.</german>
      <ogden>It is like a scale applied to reality.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>It is laid against reality like a measure.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.15121" depth="5">
      <german>Nur die äußersten Punkte der Teilstriche berühren den zu messenden Gegenstand.</german>
      <ogden>Only the outermost points of the dividing lines touch the object to be measured.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Only the end-points of the graduating lines actually touch the object that is to be measured.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.1513" depth="4">
      <german>Nach dieser Auffassung gehört also zum Bilde auch noch die abbildende Beziehung, die es zum Bild macht.</german>
      <ogden>According to this view the representing relation which makes it a picture, also belongs to the picture.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>So a picture, conceived in this way, also includes the pictorial relationship, which makes it into a picture.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.1514" depth="4">
      <german>Die abbildende Beziehung besteht aus den Zuordnungen der Elemente des Bildes und der Sachen.</german>
      <ogden>The representing relation consists of the co-ordinations of the elements of the picture and the things.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The pictorial relationship consists of the correlations of the picture’s elements with things.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.1515" depth="4">
      <german>Diese Zuordnungen sind gleichsam die Fühler der Bildelemente, mit denen das Bild die Wirklichkeit berührt.</german>
      <ogden>These co-ordinations are as it were the feelers of its elements with which the picture touches reality.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>These correlations are, as it were, the feelers of the picture’s elements, with which the picture touches reality.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.16" depth="2">
      <german>Die Tatsache muss, um Bild zu sein, etwas mit dem Abgebildeten gemeinsam haben.</german>
      <ogden>In order to be a picture a fact must have something in common with what it pictures.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>If a fact is to be a picture, it must have something in common with what it depicts.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.161" depth="3">
      <german>In Bild und Abgebildetem muss etwas identisch sein, damit das eine überhaupt ein Bild des anderen sein kann.</german>
      <ogden>In the picture and the pictured there must be something identical in order that the one can be a picture of the other at all.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>There must be something identical in a picture and what it depicts, to enable the one to be a picture of the other at all.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.17" depth="2">
      <german>Was das Bild mit der Wirklichkeit gemein haben muss, um sie auf seine Art und Weise – richtig oder falsch – abbilden zu können, ist seine Form der Abbildung.</german>
      <ogden>What the picture must have in common with reality in order to be able to represent it after its manner—rightly or falsely—is its form of representation.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>What a picture must have in common with reality, in order to be able to depict it—correctly or incorrectly—in the way that it does, is its pictorial form.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.171" depth="3">
      <german>Das Bild kann jede Wirklichkeit abbilden, deren Form es hat.</german>
      <ogden>The picture can represent every reality whose form it has.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>A picture can depict any reality whose form it has.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.172" depth="3">
      <german>Seine Form der Abbildung aber, kann das Bild nicht abbilden; es weist sie auf.</german>
      <ogden>The picture, however, cannot represent its form of representation; it shows it forth.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>A picture cannot, however, depict its pictorial form: it displays it.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.173" depth="3">
      <german>Das Bild stellt sein Objekt von außerhalb dar (sein Standpunkt ist seine Form der Darstellung), darum stellt das Bild sein Objekt richtig oder falsch dar.</german>
      <ogden>The picture represents its object from without (its standpoint is its form of representation), therefore the picture represents its object rightly or falsely.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>A picture represents its subject from a position outside it. (Its standpoint is its representational form.) That is why a picture represents its subject correctly or incorrectly.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.174" depth="3">
      <german>Das Bild kann sich aber nicht außerhalb seiner Form der Darstellung stellen.</german>
      <ogden>But the picture cannot place itself outside of its form of representation.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>A picture cannot, however, place itself outside its representational form.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.18" depth="2">
      <german>Was jedes Bild, welcher Form immer, mit der Wirklichkeit gemein haben muss, um sie überhaupt – richtig oder falsch – abbilden zu können, ist die logische Form, das ist, die Form der Wirklichkeit.</german>
      <ogden>What every picture, of whatever form, must have in common with reality in order to be able to represent it at all—rightly or falsely—is the logical form, that is, the form of reality.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>What any picture, of whatever form, must have in common with reality, in order to be able to depict it—correctly or incorrectly—in any way at all, is logical form, i.e. the form of reality.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.181" depth="3">
      <german>Ist die Form der Abbildung die logische Form, so heißt das Bild das logische Bild.</german>
      <ogden>If the form of representation is the logical form, then the picture is called a logical picture.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>A picture whose pictorial form is logical form is called a logical picture.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.182" depth="3">
      <german>Jedes Bild ist auch ein logisches. (Dagegen ist z. B. nicht jedes Bild ein räumliches.)</german>
      <ogden>Every picture is also a logical picture. (On the other hand, for example, not every picture is spatial.)</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Every picture is at the same time a logical one. (On the other hand, not every picture is, for example, a spatial one.)</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.19" depth="2">
      <german>Das logische Bild kann die Welt abbilden.</german>
      <ogden>The logical picture can depict the world.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Logical pictures can depict the world.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.2" depth="1">
      <german>Das Bild hat mit dem Abgebildeten die logische Form der Abbildung gemein.</german>
      <ogden>The picture has the logical form of representation in common with what it pictures.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>A picture has logico-pictorial form in common with what it depicts.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.201" depth="3">
      <german>Das Bild bildet die Wirklichkeit ab, indem es eine Möglichkeit des Bestehens und Nichtbestehens von Sachverhalten darstellt.</german>
      <ogden>The picture depicts reality by representing a possibility of the existence and non-existence of atomic facts.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>A picture depicts reality by representing a possibility of existence and non-existence of states of affairs.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.202" depth="3">
      <german>Das Bild stellt eine mögliche Sachlage im logischen Raume dar.</german>
      <ogden>The picture represents a possible state of affairs in logical space.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>A picture represents a possible situation in logical space.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.203" depth="3">
      <german>Das Bild enthält die Möglichkeit der Sachlage, die es darstellt.</german>
      <ogden>The picture contains the possibility of the state of affairs which it represents.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>A picture contains the possibility of the situation that it represents.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.21" depth="2">
      <german>Das Bild stimmt mit der Wirklichkeit überein oder nicht; es ist richtig oder unrichtig, wahr oder falsch.</german>
      <ogden>The picture agrees with reality or not; it is right or wrong, true or false.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>A picture agrees with reality or fails to agree; it is correct or incorrect, true or false.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.22" depth="2">
      <german>Das Bild stellt dar, was es darstellt, unabhängig von seiner Wahr- oder Falschheit, durch die Form der Abbildung.</german>
      <ogden>The picture represents what it represents, independently of its truth or falsehood, through the form of representation.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>What a picture represents it represents independently of its truth or falsity, by means of its pictorial form.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.221" depth="3">
      <german>Was das Bild darstellt, ist sein Sinn.</german>
      <ogden>What the picture represents is its sense.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>What a picture represents is its sense.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.222" depth="3">
      <german>In der Übereinstimmung oder Nichtübereinstimmung seines Sinnes mit der Wirklichkeit, besteht seine Wahrheit oder Falschheit.</german>
      <ogden>In the agreement or disagreement of its sense with reality, its truth or falsity consists.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The agreement or disagreement of its sense with reality constitutes its truth or falsity.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.223" depth="3">
      <german>Um zu erkennen, ob das Bild wahr oder falsch ist, müssen wir es mit der Wirklichkeit vergleichen.</german>
      <ogden>In order to discover whether the picture is true or false we must compare it with reality.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>In order to tell whether a picture is true or false we must compare it with reality.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.224" depth="3">
      <german>Aus dem Bild allein ist nicht zu erkennen, ob es wahr oder falsch ist.</german>
      <ogden>It cannot be discovered from the picture alone whether it is true or false.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>It is impossible to tell from the picture alone whether it is true or false.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="2.225" depth="3">
      <german>Ein a priori wahres Bild gibt es nicht.</german>
      <ogden>There is no picture which is a priori true.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>There are no pictures that are true a priori .</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
  </proposition>
  <proposition id="3" depth="0">
    <german>Das logische Bild der Tatsachen ist der Gedanke.</german>
    <ogden>The logical picture of the facts is the thought.</ogden>
    <pears_mcguinness>A logical picture of facts is a thought.</pears_mcguinness>
    <proposition id="3.001" depth="3">
      <german>„Ein Sachverhalt ist denkbar“ heißt: Wir können uns ein Bild von ihm machen.</german>
      <ogden>“An atomic fact is thinkable”—means: we can imagine it.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>‘A state of affairs is thinkable’: what this means is that we can picture it to ourselves.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.01" depth="2">
      <german>Die Gesamtheit der wahren Gedanken sind ein Bild der Welt.</german>
      <ogden>The totality of true thoughts is a picture of the world.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The totality of true thoughts is a picture of the world.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.02" depth="2">
      <german>Der Gedanke enthält die Möglichkeit der Sachlage, die er denkt. Was denkbar ist, ist auch möglich.</german>
      <ogden>The thought contains the possibility of the state of affairs which it thinks. What is thinkable is also possible.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>A thought contains the possibility of the situation of which it is the thought. What is thinkable is possible too.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.03" depth="2">
      <german>Wir können nichts Unlogisches denken, weil wir sonst unlogisch denken müssten.</german>
      <ogden>We cannot think anything unlogical, for otherwise we should have to think unlogically.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Thought can never be of anything illogical, since, if it were, we should have to think illogically.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.031" depth="3">
      <german>Man sagte einmal, dass Gott alles schaffen könne, nur nichts, was den logischen Gesetzen zuwider wäre. – Wir können nämlich von einer „unlogischen“ Welt nicht sagen , wie sie aussähe.</german>
      <ogden>It used to be said that God could create everything, except what was contrary to the laws of logic. The truth is, we could not say of an “unlogical” world how it would look.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>It used to be said that God could create anything except what would be contrary to the laws of logic. The truth is that we could not say what an ‘illogical’ world would look like.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.032" depth="3">
      <german>Etwas „der Logik widersprechendes“ in der Sprache darstellen, kann man ebensowenig, wie in der Geometrie eine den Gesetzen des Raumes widersprechende Figur durch ihre Koordinaten darstellen; oder die Koordinaten eines Punktes angeben, welcher nicht existiert.</german>
      <ogden>To present in language anything which “contradicts logic” is as impossible as in geometry to present by its co-ordinates a figure which contradicts the laws of space; or to give the co-ordinates of a point which does not exist.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>It is as impossible to represent in language anything that ‘contradicts logic’ as it is in geometry to represent by its co-ordinates a figure that contradicts the laws of space, or to give the co-ordinates of a point that does not exist.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.0321" depth="4">
      <german>Wohl können wir einen Sachverhalt räumlich darstellen, welcher den Gesetzen der Physik, aber keinen, der den Gesetzen der Geometrie zuwiderliefe.</german>
      <ogden>We could present spatially an atomic fact which contradicted the laws of physics, but not one which contradicted the laws of geometry.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Though a state of affairs that would contravene the laws of physics can be represented by us spatially, one that would contravene the laws of geometry cannot.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.04" depth="2">
      <german>Ein a priori richtiger Gedanke wäre ein solcher, dessen Möglichkeit seine Wahrheit bedingte.</german>
      <ogden>An a priori true thought would be one whose possibility guaranteed its truth.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>If a thought were correct a priori , it would be a thought whose possibility ensured its truth.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.05" depth="2">
      <german>Nur so könnten wir a priori wissen, dass ein Gedanke wahr ist, wenn aus dem Gedanken selbst (ohne Vergleichsobjekt) seine Wahrheit zu erkennen wäre.</german>
      <ogden>Only if we could know a priori that a thought is true if its truth was to be recognized from the thought itself (without an object of comparison).</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>A priori knowledge that a thought was true would be possible only if its truth were recognizable from the thought itself (without anything to compare it with).</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.1" depth="1">
      <german>Im Satz drückt sich der Gedanke sinnlich wahrnehmbar aus.</german>
      <ogden>In the proposition the thought is expressed perceptibly through the senses.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>In a proposition a thought finds an expression that can be perceived by the senses.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.11" depth="2">
      <german>Wir benützen das sinnlich wahrnehmbare Zeichen (Laut- oder Schriftzeichen etc.) des Satzes als Projektion der möglichen Sachlage.</german>
      <ogden>We use the sensibly perceptible sign (sound or written sign, etc.) of the proposition as a projection of the possible state of affairs.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>We use the perceptible sign of a proposition (spoken or written, etc.) as a projection of a possible situation.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.12" depth="2">
      <german>Das Zeichen, durch welches wir den Gedanken ausdrücken, nenne ich das Satzzeichen. Und der Satz ist das Satzzeichen in seiner projektiven Beziehung zur Welt.</german>
      <ogden>The sign through which we express the thought I call the propositional sign. And the proposition is the propositional sign in its projective relation to the world.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>I call the sign with which we express a thought a propositional sign.—And a proposition is a propositional sign in its projective relation to the world.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.13" depth="2">
      <german>Zum Satz gehört alles, was zur Projektion gehört; aber nicht das Projizierte.</german>
      <ogden>To the proposition belongs everything which belongs to the projection; but not what is projected.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>A proposition includes all that the projection includes, but not what is projected.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.14" depth="2">
      <german>Das Satzzeichen besteht darin, dass sich seine Elemente, die Wörter, in ihm auf bestimmte Art und Weise zu einander verhalten.</german>
      <ogden>The propositional sign consists in the fact that its elements, the words, are combined in it in a definite way.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>What constitutes a propositional sign is that in it its elements (the words) stand in a determinate relation to one another.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.141" depth="3">
      <german>Der Satz ist kein Wörtergemisch. – (Wie das musikalische Thema kein Gemisch von Tönen.)</german>
      <ogden>The proposition is not a mixture of words (just as the musical theme is not a mixture of tones).</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>A proposition is not a blend of words.—(Just as a theme in music is not a blend of notes.)</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.142" depth="3">
      <german>Nur Tatsachen können einen Sinn ausdrücken, eine Klasse von Namen kann es nicht.</german>
      <ogden>Only facts can express a sense, a class of names cannot.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Only facts can express a sense, a set of names cannot.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.143" depth="3">
      <german>Dass das Satzzeichen eine Tatsache ist, wird durch die gewöhnliche Ausdrucksform der Schrift oder des Druckes verschleiert.</german>
      <ogden>That the propositional sign is a fact is concealed by the ordinary form of expression, written or printed.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Although a propositional sign is a fact, this is obscured by the usual form of expression in writing or print.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.1431" depth="4">
      <german>Sehr klar wird das Wesen des Satzzeichens, wenn wir es uns, statt aus Schriftzeichen, aus räumlichen Gegenständen (etwa Tischen, Stühlen, Büchern) zusammengesetzt denken.</german>
      <ogden>The essential nature of the propositional sign becomes very clear when we imagine it made up of spatial objects (such as tables, chairs, books) instead of written signs.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The essence of a propositional sign is very clearly seen if we imagine one composed of spatial objects (such as tables, chairs, and books) instead of written signs.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.1432" depth="4">
      <german>Nicht: „Das komplexe Zeichen ‚ aRb ‘ sagt, dass a in der Beziehung R zu b steht“, sondern: Dass „ a “ in einer gewissen Beziehung zu „ b “ steht, sagt, dass aRb .</german>
      <ogden>We must not say, “The complex sign ‘ aRb ’ says ‘ a stands in relation R to b ’”; but we must say, “ That ‘ a ’ stands in a certain relation to ‘ b ’ says that aRb ”.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Instead of, ‘The complex sign “ aRb ” says that a stands to b in
the relation R ’, we ought to put, ‘ That “ a ” stands to “ b ” in a certain
relation says that aRb .’</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.144" depth="3">
      <german>Sachlagen kann man beschreiben, nicht benennen .</german>
      <ogden>States of affairs can be described but not named .</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Situations can be described but not given names .</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.2" depth="1">
      <german>Im Satze kann der Gedanke so ausgedrückt sein, dass den Gegenständen des Gedankens Elemente des Satzzeichens entsprechen.</german>
      <ogden>In propositions thoughts can be so expressed that to the objects of the thoughts correspond the elements of the propositional sign.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>In a proposition a thought can be expressed in such a way that elements of the propositional sign correspond to the objects of the thought.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.201" depth="3">
      <german>Diese Elemente nenne ich „einfache Zeichen“ und den Satz „vollständig analysiert“.</german>
      <ogden>These elements I call “simple signs” and the proposition “completely analysed”.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>I call such elements ‘simple signs’, and such a proposition ‘complete analysed’.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.202" depth="3">
      <german>Die im Satze angewandten einfachen Zeichen heißen Namen.</german>
      <ogden>The simple signs employed in propositions are called names.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The simple signs employed in propositions are called names.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.203" depth="3">
      <german>Der Name bedeutet den Gegenstand. Der Gegenstand ist seine Bedeutung. („ A “ ist dasselbe Zeichen wie „ A “.)</german>
      <ogden>The name means the object. The object is its meaning. (“ A ” is the same sign as “ A ”.)</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>A name means an object. The object is its meaning. (‘ A ’ is the same sign as ‘ A ’.)</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.21" depth="2">
      <german>Der Konfiguration der einfachen Zeichen im Satzzeichen entspricht die Konfiguration der Gegenstände in der Sachlage.</german>
      <ogden>To the configuration of the simple signs in the propositional sign corresponds the configuration of the objects in the state of affairs.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The configuration of objects in a situation corresponds to the configuration of simple signs in the propositional sign.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.22" depth="2">
      <german>Der Name vertritt im Satz den Gegenstand.</german>
      <ogden>In the proposition the name represents the object.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>In a proposition a name is the representative of an object.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.221" depth="3">
      <german>Die Gegenstände kann ich nur nennen . Zeichen vertreten sie. Ich kann nur von ihnen sprechen, sie aussprechen kann ich nicht. Ein Satz kann nur sagen, wie ein Ding ist, nicht was es ist.</german>
      <ogden>Objects I can only name . Signs represent them. I can only speak of them. I cannot assert them . A proposition can only say how a thing is, not what it is.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Objects can only be named . Signs are their representatives. I can only speak about them: I cannot put them into words . Propositions can only say how things are, not what they are.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.23" depth="2">
      <german>Die Forderung der Möglichkeit der einfachen Zeichen ist die Forderung der Bestimmtheit des Sinnes.</german>
      <ogden>The postulate of the possibility of the simple signs is the postulate of the determinateness of the sense.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The requirement that simple signs be possible is the requirement that sense be determinate.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.24" depth="2">
      <german>Der Satz, welcher vom Komplex handelt, steht in interner Beziehung zum Satze, der von dessen Bestandteil handelt.</german>
      <ogden>A proposition about a complex stands in internal relation to the proposition about its constituent part.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>A proposition about a complex stands in an internal relation to a proposition about a constituent of the complex.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.25" depth="2">
      <german>Es gibt eine und nur eine vollständige Analyse des Satzes.</german>
      <ogden>There is one and only one complete analysis of the proposition.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>A proposition has one and only one complete analysis.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.251" depth="3">
      <german>Der Satz drückt auf bestimmte, klar angebbare Weise aus, was er ausdrückt: Der Satz ist artikuliert.</german>
      <ogden>The proposition expresses what it expresses in a definite and clearly specifiable way: the proposition is articulate.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>What a proposition expresses it expresses in a determinate manner, which can be set out clearly: a proposition is articulate.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.26" depth="2">
      <german>Der Name ist durch keine Definition weiter zu zergliedern: er ist ein Urzeichen.</german>
      <ogden>The name cannot be analysed further by any definition. It is a primitive sign.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>A name cannot be dissected any further by means of a definition: it is a primitive sign.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.261" depth="3">
      <german>Jedes definierte Zeichen bezeichnet über jene Zeichen, durch welche es definiert wurde; und die Definitionen weisen den Weg.</german>
      <ogden>Every defined sign signifies via those signs by which it is defined, and the definitions show the way.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Every sign that has a definition signifies via the signs that serve to define it; and the definitions point the way.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.262" depth="3">
      <german>Was in den Zeichen nicht zum Ausdruck kommt, das zeigt ihre Anwendung. Was die Zeichen verschlucken, das spricht ihre Anwendung aus.</german>
      <ogden>What does not get expressed in the sign is shown by its application. What the signs conceal, their application declares.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>What signs fail to express, their application shows. What signs slur over, their application says clearly.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.263" depth="3">
      <german>Die Bedeutungen von Urzeichen können durch Erläuterungen erklärt werden. Erläuterungen sind Sätze, welche die Urzeichen enthalten. Sie können also nur verstanden werden, wenn die Bedeutungen dieser Zeichen bereits bekannt sind.</german>
      <ogden>The meanings of primitive signs can be explained by elucidations. Elucidations are propositions which contain the primitive signs. They can, therefore, only be understood when the meanings of these signs are already known.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The meanings of primitive signs can be explained by means of elucidations. Elucidations are propositions that contain the primitive signs. So they can only be understood if the meanings of those signs are already known.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.3" depth="1">
      <german>Nur der Satz hat Sinn; nur im Zusammenhang des Satzes hat ein Name Bedeutung.</german>
      <ogden>Only the proposition has sense; only in the context of a proposition has a name meaning.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Only propositions have sense; only in the nexus of a proposition does a name have meaning.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.31" depth="2">
      <german>Jeden Teil des Satzes, der seinen Sinn charakterisiert, nenne ich einen Ausdruck (ein Symbol).</german>
      <ogden>Every part of a proposition which characterizes its sense I call an expression (a symbol).</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>I call any part of a proposition that characterizes its sense an expression (or a symbol).</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.311" depth="3">
      <german>Der Ausdruck setzt die Formen aller Sätze voraus, in welchen er vorkommen kann. Er ist das gemeinsame charakteristische Merkmal einer Klasse von Sätzen.</german>
      <ogden>An expression presupposes the forms of all propositions in which it can occur. It is the common characteristic mark of a class of propositions.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>An expression presupposes the forms of all the propositions in which it can occur. It is the common characteristic mark of a class of propositions.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.312" depth="3">
      <german>Er wird also dargestellt durch die allgemeine Form der Sätze, die er charakterisiert.</german>
      <ogden>It is therefore represented by the general form of the propositions which it characterizes.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>It is therefore presented by means of the general form of the propositions that it characterizes.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.313" depth="3">
      <german>Der Ausdruck wird also durch eine Variable dargestellt, deren Werte die Sätze sind, die den Ausdruck enthalten.</german>
      <ogden>An expression is thus presented by a variable, whose values are the propositions which contain the expression.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Thus an expression is presented by means of a variable whose values are the propositions that contain the expression.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.314" depth="3">
      <german>Der Ausdruck hat nur im Satz Bedeutung. Jede Variable lässt sich als Satzvariable auffassen.</german>
      <ogden>An expression has meaning only in a proposition. Every variable can be conceived as a propositional variable.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>An expression has meaning only in a proposition. All variables can be construed as propositional variables.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.315" depth="3">
      <german>Verwandeln wir einen Bestandteil eines Satzes in eine Variable, so gibt es eine Klasse von Sätzen, welche sämtlich Werte des so entstandenen variablen Satzes sind. Diese Klasse hängt im allgemeinen noch davon ab, was wir, nach willkürlicher Übereinkunft, mit Teilen jenes Satzes meinen. Verwandeln wir aber alle jene Zeichen, deren Bedeutung willkürlich bestimmt wurde, in Variable, so gibt es nun noch immer eine solche Klasse. Diese aber ist nun von keiner Übereinkunft abhängig, sondern nur noch von der Natur des Satzes. Sie entspricht einer logischen Form – einem logischen Urbild.</german>
      <ogden>If we change a constituent part of a proposition into a variable, there is a class of propositions which are all the values of the resulting variable proposition. This class in general still depends on what, by arbitrary agreement, we mean by parts of that proposition. But if we change all those signs, whose meaning was arbitrarily determined, into variables, there always remains such a class. But this is now no longer dependent on any agreement; it depends only on the nature of the proposition. It corresponds to a logical form, to a logical prototype.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>If we turn a constituent of a proposition into a variable, there is a class of propositions all of which are values of the resulting variable proposition. In general, this class too will be dependent on the meaning that our arbitrary conventions have given to parts of the original proposition. But if all the signs in it that have arbitrarily determined meanings are turned into variables, we shall still get a class of this kind. This one, however, is not dependent on any convention, but solely on the nature of the proposition. It corresponds to a logical form—a logical prototype.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.316" depth="3">
      <german>Welche Werte die Satzvariable annehmen darf, wird festgesetzt.</german>
      <ogden>What values the propositional variable can assume is determined.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>What values a propositional variable may take is something that is stipulated.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.317" depth="3">
      <german>Die Festsetzung der Werte der Satzvariablen ist die Angabe der Sätze , deren gemeinsames Merkmal die Variable ist.</german>
      <ogden>The determination of the values of the propositional variable is done by indicating the propositions whose common mark the variable is.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>To stipulate values for a propositional variable is to give the propositions whose common characteristic the variable is.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.318" depth="3">
      <german>Den Satz fasse ich – wie Frege und Russell – als Funktion der in ihm enthaltenen Ausdrücke auf.</german>
      <ogden>I conceive the proposition—like Frege and Russell—as a function of the expressions contained in it.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Like Frege and Russell I construe a proposition as a function of the expressions contained in it.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.32" depth="2">
      <german>Das Zeichen ist das sinnlich Wahrnehmbare am Symbol.</german>
      <ogden>The sign is the part of the symbol perceptible by the senses.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>A sign is what can be perceived of a symbol.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.321" depth="3">
      <german>Zwei verschiedene Symbole können also das Zeichen (Schriftzeichen oder Lautzeichen etc.) miteinander gemein haben – sie bezeichnen dann auf verschiedene Art und Weise.</german>
      <ogden>Two different symbols can therefore have the sign (the written sign or the sound sign) in common—they then signify in different ways.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>So one and the same sign (written or spoken, etc.) can be common to two different symbols—in which case they will signify in different ways.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.322" depth="3">
      <german>Es kann nie das gemeinsame Merkmal zweier Gegenstände anzeigen, dass wir sie mit demselben Zeichen, aber durch zwei verschiedene Bezeichnungsweisen bezeichnen. Denn das Zeichen ist ja willkürlich. Man könnte also auch zwei verschiedene Zeichen wählen, und wo bliebe dann das Gemeinsame in der Bezeichnung?</german>
      <ogden>It can never indicate the common characteristic of two objects that we symbolize them with the same signs but by different methods of symbolizing . For the sign is arbitrary. We could therefore equally well choose two different signs and where then would be what was common in the symbolization?</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Our use of the same sign to signify two different objects can never indicate a common characteristic of the two, if we use it with two different modes of signification . For the sign, of course, is arbitrary. So we could choose two different signs instead, and then what would be left in common on the signifying side?</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.323" depth="3">
      <german>In der Umgangssprache kommt es ungemein häufig vor, dass dasselbe Wort auf verschiedene Art und Weise bezeichnet – also verschiedenen Symbolen angehört –, oder, dass zwei Wörter, die auf verschiedene Art und Weise bezeichnen, äußerlich in der gleichen Weise im Satz angewandt werden.</german>
      <ogden>In the language of everyday life it very often happens that the same word signifies in two different ways—and therefore belongs to two different symbols—or that two words, which signify in different ways, are apparently applied in the same way in the proposition.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>In everyday language it very frequently happens that the same word has different modes of signification—and so belongs to different symbols—or that two words that have different modes of signification are employed in propositions in what is superficially the same way.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.324" depth="3">
      <german>So entstehen leicht die fundamentalsten Verwechslungen (deren die ganze Philosophie voll ist).</german>
      <ogden>Thus there easily arise the most fundamental confusions (of which the whole of philosophy is full).</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>In this way the most fundamental confusions are easily produced (the whole of philosophy is full of them).</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.325" depth="3">
      <german>Um diesen Irrtümern zu entgehen, müssen wir eine Zeichensprache verwenden, welche sie ausschließt, indem sie nicht das gleiche Zeichen in verschiedenen Symbolen, und Zeichen, welche auf verschiedene Art bezeichnen, nicht äußerlich auf die gleiche Art verwendet. Eine Zeichensprache also, die der logischen Grammatik – der logischen Syntax – gehorcht.</german>
      <ogden>In order to avoid these errors, we must employ a symbolism which excludes them, by not applying the same sign in different symbols and by not applying signs in the same way which signify in different ways. A symbolism, that is to say, which obeys the rules of logical grammar—of logical syntax.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>In order to avoid such errors we must make use of a sign-language that excludes them by not using the same sign for different symbols and by not using in a superficially similar way signs that have different modes of signification: that is to say, a sign-language that is governed by logical grammar—by logical syntax.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.326" depth="3">
      <german>Um das Symbol am Zeichen zu erkennen, muss man auf den sinnvollen Gebrauch achten.</german>
      <ogden>In order to recognize the symbol in the sign we must consider the significant use.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>In order to recognize a symbol by its sign we must observe how it is used with a sense.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.327" depth="3">
      <german>Das Zeichen bestimmt erst mit seiner logisch-syntaktischen Verwendung zusammen eine logische Form.</german>
      <ogden>The sign determines a logical form only together with its logical syntactic application.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>A sign does not determine a logical form unless it is taken together with its logico-syntactical employment.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.328" depth="3">
      <german>Wird ein Zeichen nicht gebraucht , so ist es bedeutungslos. Das ist der Sinn der Devise Occams.</german>
      <ogden>If a sign is not necessary then it is meaningless. That is the meaning of Occam’s razor.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>If a sign is useless , it is meaningless. That is the point of Occam’s maxim.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.33" depth="2">
      <german>In der logischen Syntax darf nie die Bedeutung eines Zeichens eine Rolle spielen; sie muss sich aufstellen lassen, ohne dass dabei von der Bedeutung eines Zeichens die Rede wäre, sie darf nur die Beschreibung der Ausdrücke voraussetzen.</german>
      <ogden>In logical syntax the meaning of a sign ought never to play a rôle; it must admit of being established without mention being thereby made of the meaning of a sign; it ought to presuppose only the description of the expressions.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>In logical syntax the meaning of a sign should never play a role. It must be possible to establish logical syntax without mentioning the meaning of a sign: only the description of expressions may be presupposed.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.331" depth="3">
      <german>Von dieser Bemerkung sehen wir in Russells „Theory of types“ hinüber: Der Irrtum Russells zeigt sich darin, dass er bei der Aufstellung der Zeichenregeln von der Bedeutung der Zeichen reden musste.</german>
      <ogden>From this observation we get a further view—into Russell’s Theory of Types . Russell’s error is shown by the fact that in drawing up his symbolic rules he has to speak about the things his signs mean.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>From this observation we turn to Russell’s ‘theory of types’. It can be seen that Russell must be wrong, because he had to mention the meaning of signs when establishing the rules for them.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.332" depth="3">
      <german>Kein Satz kann etwas über sich selbst aussagen, weil das Satzzeichen nicht in sich selbst enthalten sein kann (das ist die ganze „Theory of types“).</german>
      <ogden>No proposition can say anything about itself, because the propositional sign cannot be contained in itself (that is the “whole theory of types”).</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>No proposition can make a statement about itself, because a propositional sign cannot be contained in itself (that is the whole of the ‘theory of types’).</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.333" depth="3">
      <german>Eine Funktion kann darum nicht ihr eigenes Argument sein, weil das Funktionszeichen bereits das Urbild seines Arguments enthält und es sich nicht selbst enthalten kann.</german>
      <ogden>A function cannot be its own argument, because the functional sign already contains the prototype of its own argument and it cannot contain itself.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The reason why a function cannot be its own argument is that the sign for a function already contains the prototype of its argument, and it cannot contain itself.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.334" depth="3">
      <german>Die Regeln der logischen Syntax müssen sich von selbst verstehen, wenn man nur weiß, wie ein jedes Zeichen bezeichnet.</german>
      <ogden>The rules of logical syntax must follow of themselves, if we only know how every single sign signifies.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The rules of logical syntax must go without saying, once we know how each individual sign signifies.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.34" depth="2">
      <german>Der Satz besitzt wesentliche und zufällige Züge.</german>
      <ogden>A proposition possesses essential and accidental features.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>A proposition possesses essential and accidental features.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.341" depth="3">
      <german>Das Wesentliche am Satz ist also das, was allen Sätzen, welche den gleichen Sinn ausdrücken können, gemeinsam ist.</german>
      <ogden>The essential in a proposition is therefore that which is common to all propositions which can express the same sense.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>So what is essential in a proposition is what all propositions that can express the same sense have in common.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.3411" depth="4">
      <german>Man könnte also sagen: Der eigentliche Name ist das, was alle Symbole, die den Gegenstand bezeichnen, gemeinsam haben. Es würde sich so successive ergeben, dass keinerlei Zusammensetzung für den Namen wesentlich ist.</german>
      <ogden>One could therefore say the real name is that which all symbols, which signify an object, have in common. It would then follow, step by step, that no sort of composition was essential for a name.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>So one could say that the real name of an object was what all symbols that signified it had in common. Thus, one by one, all kinds of composition would prove to be unessential to a name.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.342" depth="3">
      <german>An unseren Notationen ist zwar etwas willkürlich, aber das ist nicht willkürlich: Dass, wenn wir etwas willkürlich bestimmt haben, dann etwas anderes der Fall sein muss. (Dies hängt von dem Wesen der Notation ab.)</german>
      <ogden>In our notations there is indeed something arbitrary, but this is not arbitrary, namely that if we have determined anything arbitrarily, then something else must be the case. (This results from the essence of the notation.)</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Although there is something arbitrary in our notations, this much is not arbitrary—that when we have determined one thing arbitrarily, something else is necessarily the case. (This derives from the essence of notation.)</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.3421" depth="4">
      <german>Eine besondere Bezeichnungsweise mag unwichtig sein, aber wichtig ist es immer, dass diese eine mögliche Bezeichnungsweise ist. Und so verhält es sich in der Philosophie überhaupt: Das Einzelne erweist sich immer wieder als unwichtig, aber die Möglichkeit jedes Einzelnen gibt uns einen Aufschluss über das Wesen der Welt.</german>
      <ogden>A particular method of symbolizing may be unimportant, but it is always important that this is a possible method of symbolizing. And this happens as a rule in philosophy: The single thing proves over and over again to be unimportant, but the possibility of every single thing reveals something about the nature of the world.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>A particular mode of signifying may be unimportant but it is always important that it is a possible mode of signifying. And that is generally so in philosophy: again and again the individual case turns out to be unimportant, but the possibility of each individual case discloses something about the essence of the world.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.343" depth="3">
      <german>Definitionen sind Regeln der Übersetzung von einer Sprache in eine andere. Jede richtige Zeichensprache muss sich in jede andere nach solchen Regeln übersetzen lassen: Dies ist, was sie alle gemeinsam haben.</german>
      <ogden>Definitions are rules for the translation of one language into another. Every correct symbolism must be translatable into every other according to such rules. It is this which all have in common.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Definitions are rules for translating from one language into another. Any correct sign-language must be translatable into any other in accordance with such rules: it is this that they all have in common.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.344" depth="3">
      <german>Das, was am Symbol bezeichnet, ist das Gemeinsame aller jener Symbole, durch die das erste den Regeln der logischen Syntax zufolge ersetzt werden kann.</german>
      <ogden>What signifies in the symbol is what is common to all those symbols by which it can be replaced according to the rules of logical syntax.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>What signifies in a symbol is what is common to all the symbols that the rules of logical syntax allow us to substitute for it.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.3441" depth="4">
      <german>Man kann z. B. das Gemeinsame aller Notationen für die Wahrheitsfunktionen so ausdrücken: Es ist ihnen gemeinsam, dass sich alle – z. B. – durch die Notation von „ ~ p “ („nicht p “) und „ p ∨ q “ („ p oder q “) ersetzen lassen .</german>
      <ogden>We can, for example, express what is common to all notations for the truth-functions as follows: It is common to them that they all, for example, can be replaced by the notations of “ ~ p ” (“not p ”) and “ p ∨ q ” (“ p or q ”).</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>For instance, we can express what is common to all notations for truth-functions in the following way: they have in common that, for example, the notation that uses ‘ ~ p ’ (‘not p ’) and ‘ p ∨ q ’ (‘ p or q ’) can be substituted for any of them.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.3442" depth="4">
      <german>Das Zeichen des Komplexes löst sich auch bei der Analyse nicht willkürlich auf, so dass etwa seine Auflösung in jedem Satzgefüge eine andere wäre.</german>
      <ogden>The sign of the complex is not arbitrarily resolved in the analysis, in such a way that its resolution would be different in every propositional structure.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Nor does analysis resolve the sign for a complex in an arbitrary way, so that it would have a different resolution every time that it was incorporated in a different proposition.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.4" depth="1">
      <german>Der Satz bestimmt einen Ort im logischen Raum. Die Existenz dieses logischen Ortes ist durch die Existenz der Bestandteile allein verbürgt, durch die Existenz des sinnvollen Satzes.</german>
      <ogden>The proposition determines a place in logical space: the existence of this logical place is guaranteed by the existence of the constituent parts alone, by the existence of the significant proposition.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>A proposition determines a place in logical space. The existence of this logical place is guaranteed by the mere existence of the constituents—by the existence of the proposition with a sense.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.41" depth="2">
      <german>Das Satzzeichen und die logischen Koordinaten: Das ist der logische Ort.</german>
      <ogden>The propositional sign and the logical co-ordinates: that is the logical place.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The propositional sign with logical co-ordinates—that is the logical place.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.411" depth="3">
      <german>Der geometrische und der logische Ort stimmen darin überein, dass beide die Möglichkeit einer Existenz sind.</german>
      <ogden>The geometrical and the logical place agree in that each is the possibility of an existence.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>In geometry and logic alike a place is a possibility: something can exist in it.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.42" depth="2">
      <german>Obwohl der Satz nur einen Ort des logischen Raumes bestimmen darf, so muss doch durch ihn schon der ganze logische Raum gegeben sein.</german>
      <ogden>Although a proposition may only determine one place in logical space, the whole logical space must already be given by it.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>A proposition can determine only one place in logical space: nevertheless the whole of logical space must already be given by it.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="3.5" depth="1">
      <german>Das angewandte, gedachte, Satzzeichen ist der Gedanke.</german>
      <ogden>The applied, thought, propositional sign, is the thought.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>A propositional sign, applied and thought out, is a thought.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
  </proposition>
  <proposition id="4" depth="0">
    <german>Der Gedanke ist der sinnvolle Satz.</german>
    <ogden>The thought is the significant proposition.</ogden>
    <pears_mcguinness>A thought is a proposition with a sense.</pears_mcguinness>
    <proposition id="4.001" depth="3">
      <german>Die Gesamtheit der Sätze ist die Sprache.</german>
      <ogden>The totality of propositions is the language.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The totality of propositions is language.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.002" depth="3">
      <german>Der Mensch besitzt die Fähigkeit Sprachen zu bauen, womit sich jeder Sinn ausdrücken lässt, ohne eine Ahnung davon zu haben, wie und was jedes Wort bedeutet. – Wie man auch spricht, ohne zu wissen, wie die einzelnen Laute hervorgebracht werden.</german>
      <ogden>Man possesses the capacity of constructing languages, in which every sense can be expressed, without having an idea how and what each word means—just as one speaks without knowing how the single sounds are produced.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Man possesses the ability to construct languages capable of expressing every sense, without having any idea how each word has meaning or what its meaning is—just as people speak without knowing how the individual sounds are produced.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.003" depth="3">
      <german>Die meisten Sätze und Fragen, welche über philosophische Dinge geschrieben worden sind, sind nicht falsch, sondern unsinnig. Wir können daher Fragen dieser Art überhaupt nicht beantworten, sondern nur ihre Unsinnigkeit feststellen. Die meisten Fragen und Sätze der Philosophen beruhen darauf, dass wir unsere Sprachlogik nicht verstehen.</german>
      <ogden>Most propositions and questions, that have been written about philosophical matters, are not false, but senseless. We cannot, therefore, answer questions of this kind at all, but only state their senselessness. Most questions and propositions of the philosophers result from the fact that we do not understand the logic of our language.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Most of the propositions and questions to be found in philosophical works are not false but nonsensical. Consequently we cannot give any answer to questions of this kind, but can only point out that they are nonsensical. Most of the propositions and questions of philosophers arise from our failure to understand the logic of our language.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.0031" depth="4">
      <german>Alle Philosophie ist „Sprachkritik“. (Allerdings nicht im Sinne Mauthners.) Russells Verdienst ist es, gezeigt zu haben, dass die scheinbare logische Form des Satzes nicht seine wirkliche sein muss.</german>
      <ogden>All philosophy is “Critique of language” (but not at all in Mauthner’s sense). Russell’s merit is to have shown that the apparent logical form of the proposition need not be its real form.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>All philosophy is a ‘critique of language’ (though not in Mauthner’s sense). It was Russell who performed the service of showing that the apparent logical form of a proposition need not be its real one.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.01" depth="2">
      <german>Der Satz ist ein Bild der Wirklichkeit.</german>
      <ogden>The proposition is a picture of reality.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>A proposition is a picture of reality.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.011" depth="3">
      <german>Auf den ersten Blick scheint der Satz – wie er etwa auf dem Papier gedruckt steht – kein Bild der Wirklichkeit zu sein, von der er handelt. Aber auch die Notenschrift scheint auf den ersten Blick kein Bild der Musik zu sein, und unsere Lautzeichen-(Buchstaben-)Schrift kein Bild unserer Lautsprache.</german>
      <ogden>At the first glance the proposition—say as it stands printed on paper—does not seem to be a picture of the reality of which it treats. But nor does the musical score appear at first sight to be a picture of a musical piece; nor does our phonetic spelling (letters) seem to be a picture of our spoken language.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>At first sight a proposition—one set out on the printed page, for example—does not seem to be a picture of the reality with which it is concerned. But neither do written notes seem at first sight to be a picture of a piece of music, nor our phonetic notation (the alphabet) to be a picture of our speech.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.012" depth="3">
      <german>Offenbar ist, dass wir einen Satz von der Form „ aRb “ als Bild empfinden. Hier ist das Zeichen offenbar ein Gleichnis des Bezeichneten.</german>
      <ogden>It is obvious that we perceive a proposition of the form aRb as a picture. Here the sign is obviously a likeness of the signified.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>It is obvious that a proposition of the form ‘ aRb ’ strikes us as a picture. In this case the sign is obviously a likeness of what is signified.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.013" depth="3">
      <german>Und wenn wir in das Wesentliche dieser Bildhaftigkeit eindringen, so sehen wir, dass dieselbe durch scheinbare Unregelmäßigkeiten (wie die Verwendung der ♯ und ♭ in der Notenschrift) nicht gestört wird.</german>
      <ogden>And if we penetrate to the essence of this pictorial nature we see that this is not disturbed by apparent irregularities (like the use of ♯ and ♭ in the score).</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>And if we penetrate to the essence of this pictorial character, we see that it is not impaired by apparent irregularities (such as the use of ♯ and ♭ in musical notation).</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.014" depth="3">
      <german>Die Grammophonplatte, der musikalische Gedanke, die Notenschrift, die Schallwellen, stehen alle in jener abbildenden internen Beziehung zu einander, die zwischen Sprache und Welt besteht.</german>
      <ogden>The gramophone record, the musical thought, the score, the waves of sound, all stand to one another in that pictorial internal relation, which holds between language and the world.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>A gramophone record, the musical idea, the written notes, and the sound-waves, all stand to one another in the same internal relation of depicting that holds between language and the world.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.0141" depth="4">
      <german>Dass es eine allgemeine Regel gibt, durch die der Musiker aus der Partitur die Symphonie entnehmen kann, durch welche man aus der Linie auf der Grammophonplatte die Symphonie und nach der ersten Regel wieder die Partitur ableiten kann, darin besteht eben die innere Ähnlichkeit dieser scheinbar so ganz verschiedenen Gebilde. Und jene Regel ist das Gesetz der Projektion, welches die Symphonie in die Notensprache projiziert. Sie ist die Regel der Übersetzung der Notensprache in die Sprache der Grammophonplatte.</german>
      <ogden>In the fact that there is a general rule by which the musician is able to read the symphony out of the score, and that there is a rule by which one could reconstruct the symphony from the line on a gramophone record and from this again—by means of the first rule—construct the score, herein lies the internal similarity between these things which at first sight seem to be entirely different. And the rule is the law of projection which projects the symphony into the language of the musical score. It is the rule of translation of this language into the language of the gramophone record.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>There is a general rule by means of which the musician can obtain the symphony from the score, and which makes it possible to derive the symphony from the groove on the gramophone record, and, using the first rule, to derive the score again. That is what constitutes the inner similarity between these things which seem to be constructed in such entirely different ways. And that rule is the law of projection which projects the symphony into the language of musical notation. It is the rule for translating this language into the language of gramophone records.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.015" depth="3">
      <german>Die Möglichkeit aller Gleichnisse, der ganzen Bildhaftigkeit unserer Ausdrucksweise, ruht in der Logik der Abbildung.</german>
      <ogden>The possibility of all similes, of all the images of our language, rests on the logic of representation.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The possibility of all imagery, of all our pictorial modes of expression, is contained in the logic of depiction.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.016" depth="3">
      <german>Um das Wesen des Satzes zu verstehen, denken wir an die Hieroglyphenschrift, welche die Tatsachen die sie beschreibt abbildet.</german>
      <ogden>In order to understand the essence of the proposition, consider hieroglyphic writing, which pictures the facts it describes.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>In order to understand the essential nature of a proposition, we should consider hieroglyphic script, which depicts the facts that it describes.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.02" depth="2">
      <german>Dies sehen wir daraus, dass wir den Sinn des Satzzeichens verstehen, ohne dass er uns erklärt wurde.</german>
      <ogden>This we see from the fact that we understand the sense of the propositional sign, without having had it explained to us.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>We can see this from the fact that we understand the sense of a propositional sign without its having been explained to us.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.021" depth="3">
      <german>Der Satz ist ein Bild der Wirklichkeit: Denn ich kenne die von ihm dargestellte Sachlage, wenn ich den Satz verstehe. Und den Satz verstehe ich, ohne dass mir sein Sinn erklärt wurde.</german>
      <ogden>The proposition is a picture of reality, for I know the state of affairs presented by it, if I understand the proposition. And I understand the proposition, without its sense having been explained to me.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>A proposition is a picture of reality: for if I understand a proposition, I know the situation that it represents. And I understand the proposition without having had its sense explained to me.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.022" depth="3">
      <german>Der Satz zeigt seinen Sinn.</german>
      <ogden>The proposition shows its sense.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>A proposition shows its sense.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.023" depth="3">
      <german>Die Wirklichkeit muss durch den Satz auf ja oder nein fixiert sein.</german>
      <ogden>The proposition determines reality to this extent, that one only needs to say “Yes” or “No” to it to make it agree with reality.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>A proposition must restrict reality to two alternatives: yes or no.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.024" depth="3">
      <german>Einen Satz verstehen, heißt, wissen was der Fall ist, wenn er wahr ist.</german>
      <ogden>To understand a proposition means to know what is the case, if it is true.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>To understand a proposition means to know what is the case if it is true.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.025" depth="3">
      <german>Die Übersetzung einer Sprache in eine andere geht nicht so vor sich, dass man jeden Satz der einen in einen Satz der anderen übersetzt, sondern nur die Satzbestandteile werden übersetzt.</german>
      <ogden>The translation of one language into another is not a process of translating each proposition of the one into a proposition of the other, but only the constituent parts of propositions are translated.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>When translating one language into another, we do not proceed by translating each proposition of the one into a proposition of the other, but merely by translating the constituents of propositions.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.026" depth="3">
      <german>Die Bedeutung der einfachen Zeichen (der Wörter) müssen uns erklärt werden, dass wir sie verstehen.</german>
      <ogden>The meanings of the simple signs (the words) must be explained to us, if we are to understand them.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The meanings of simple signs (words) must be explained to us if we are to understand them.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.027" depth="3">
      <german>Es liegt im Wesen des Satzes, dass er uns einen neuen Sinn mitteilen kann.</german>
      <ogden>It is essential to propositions, that they can communicate a new sense to us.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>It belongs to the essence of a proposition that it should be able to communicate a new sense to us.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.03" depth="2">
      <german>Ein Satz muss mit alten Ausdrücken einen neuen Sinn mitteilen.</german>
      <ogden>A proposition must communicate a new sense with old words.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>A proposition must use old expressions to communicate a new sense.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.031" depth="3">
      <german>Im Satz wird gleichsam eine Sachlage probeweise zusammengestellt.</german>
      <ogden>In the proposition a state of affairs is, as it were, put together for the sake of experiment.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>In a proposition a situation is, as it were, constructed by way of experiment.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.0311" depth="4">
      <german>Ein Name steht für ein Ding, ein anderer für ein anderes Ding und untereinander sind sie verbunden, so stellt das Ganze – wie ein lebendes Bild – den Sachverhalt vor.</german>
      <ogden>One name stands for one thing, and another for another thing, and they are connected together. And so the whole, like a living picture, presents the atomic fact.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>One name stands for one thing, another for another thing, and they are combined with one another. In this way the whole group—like a tableau vivant —presents a state of affairs.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.0312" depth="4">
      <german>Die Möglichkeit des Satzes beruht auf dem Prinzip der Vertretung von Gegenständen durch Zeichen.</german>
      <ogden>The possibility of propositions is based upon the principle of the representation of objects by signs.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The possibility of propositions is based on the principle that objects have signs as their representatives.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.032" depth="3">
      <german>Nur insoweit ist der Satz ein Bild der Sachlage, als er logisch gegliedert ist.</german>
      <ogden>The proposition is a picture of its state of affairs, only in so far as it is logically articulated.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>It is only in so far as a proposition is logically articulated that it is a picture of a situation.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.04" depth="2">
      <german>Am Satz muss gerade soviel zu unterscheiden sein, als an der Sachlage, die er darstellt.</german>
      <ogden>In the proposition there must be exactly as many things distinguishable as there are in the state of affairs, which it represents.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>In a proposition there must be exactly as many distinguishable parts as in the situation that it represents.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.041" depth="3">
      <german>Diese mathematische Mannigfaltigkeit kann man natürlich nicht selbst wieder abbilden. Aus ihr kann man beim Abbilden nicht heraus.</german>
      <ogden>This mathematical multiplicity naturally cannot in its turn be represented. One cannot get outside it in the representation.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>This mathematical multiplicity, of course, cannot itself be the subject of depiction. One cannot get away from it when depicting.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.0411" depth="4">
      <german>Wollten wir z. B. das, was wir durch „ ( x ). fx “ ausdrücken, durch Vorsetzen eines Indexes vor „ fx “ ausdrücken – etwa so: „ Alg. fx “ – es würde nicht genügen – wir wüssten nicht, was verallgemeinert wurde. Wollten wir es durch einen Index „ a “ anzeigen – etwa so: „ f ( x a ) “ – es würde auch nicht genügen – wir wüssten nicht den Bereich der Allgemeinheitsbezeichnung.</german>
      <ogden>If we tried, for example, to express what is expressed by “ ( x ). fx ” by putting an index before fx , like: “ Gen. fx ”, it would not do, we should not know what was generalized. If we tried to show it by an index g , like: “ f ( x g ) ” it would not do—we should not know the scope of the generalization.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>If, for example, we wanted to express what we now write as ‘ ( x ). fx ’ by putting an affix in front of ‘ fx ’—for instance by writing ‘ Gen. fx ’—it would not be adequate: we should not know what was being generalized. If we wanted to signalize it with an affix ‘ g ’—for instance by writing ‘ f ( x g ) ’—that would not be adequate either: we should not know the scope of the generality-sign.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.0412" depth="4">
      <german>Aus demselben Grunde genügt die idealistische Erklärung des Sehens der räumlichen Beziehungen durch die „Raumbrille“ nicht, weil sie nicht die Mannigfaltigkeit dieser Beziehungen erklären kann.</german>
      <ogden>For the same reason the idealist explanation of the seeing of spatial relations through “spatial spectacles” does not do, because it cannot explain the multiplicity of these relations.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>For the same reason the idealist’s appeal to ‘spatial spectacles’ is inadequate to explain the seeing of spatial relations, because it cannot explain the multiplicity of these relations.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.05" depth="2">
      <german>Die Wirklichkeit wird mit dem Satz verglichen.</german>
      <ogden>Reality is compared with the proposition.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Reality is compared with propositions.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.06" depth="2">
      <german>Nur dadurch kann der Satz wahr oder falsch sein, indem er ein Bild der Wirklichkeit ist.</german>
      <ogden>Propositions can be true or false only by being pictures of the reality.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>A proposition can be true or false only in virtue of being a picture of reality.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.061" depth="3">
      <german>Beachtet man nicht, dass der Satz einen von den Tatsachen unabhängigen Sinn hat, so kann man leicht glauben, dass wahr und falsch gleichberechtigte Beziehungen von Zeichen und Bezeichnetem sind.</german>
      <ogden>If one does not observe that propositions have a sense independent of the facts, one can easily believe that true and false are two relations between signs and things signified with equal rights.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>It must not be overlooked that a proposition has a sense that is independent of the facts: otherwise one can easily suppose that true and false are relations of equal status between signs and what they signify.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.062" depth="3">
      <german>Kann man sich nicht mit falschen Sätzen, wie bisher mit wahren, verständigen? Solange man nur weiß, dass sie falsch gemeint sind. Nein! Denn, wahr ist ein Satz, wenn es sich so verhält, wie wir es durch ihn sagen; und wenn wir mit „ p “ ~ p meinen, und es sich so verhält wie wir es meinen, so ist „ p “ in der neuen Auffassung wahr und nicht falsch.</german>
      <ogden>Can we not make ourselves understood by means of false propositions as hitherto with true ones, so long as we know that they are meant to be false? No! For a proposition is true, if what we assert by means of it is the case; and if by “ p ” we mean ~ p , and what we mean is the case, then “ p ” in the new conception is true and not false.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Can we not make ourselves understood with false propositions just as we have done up till now with true ones?—So long as it is known that they are meant to be false.—No! For a proposition is true if we use it to say that things stand in a certain way, and they do; and if by ‘ p ’ we mean ~ p and things stand as we mean that they do, then, construed in the new way, ‘ p ’ is true and not false.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.0621" depth="4">
      <german>Dass aber die Zeichen „ p “ und „ ~ p “ das gleiche sagen können , ist wichtig. Denn es zeigt, dass dem Zeichen „~“ in der Wirklichkeit nichts entspricht.</german>
      <ogden>That, however, the signs “ p ” and “ ~ p ” can say the same thing is important, for it shows that the sign “~” corresponds to nothing in reality.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>But it is important that the signs ‘ p ’ and ‘ ~ p ’ can say the same thing. For it shows that nothing in reality corresponds to the sign ‘~’.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.063" depth="3">
      <german>Ein Bild zur Erklärung des Wahrheitsbegriffes: Schwarzer Fleck auf weißem Papier; die Form des Fleckes kann man beschreiben, indem man für jeden Punkt der Fläche angibt, ob er weiß oder schwarz ist. Der Tatsache, dass ein Punkt schwarz ist, entspricht eine positive – der, dass ein Punkt weiß (nicht schwarz) ist, eine negative Tatsache. Bezeichne ich einen Punkt der Fläche (einen Fregeschen Wahrheitswert), so entspricht dies der Annahme, die zur Beurteilung aufgestellt wird, etc. etc.</german>
      <ogden>An illustration to explain the concept of truth. A black spot on white paper; the form of the spot can be described by saying of each point of the plane whether it is white or black. To the fact that a point is black corresponds a positive fact; to the fact that a point is white (not black), a negative fact. If I indicate a point of the plane (a truth-value in Frege’s terminology), this corresponds to the assumption proposed for judgment, etc. etc.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>An analogy to illustrate the concept of truth: imagine a black spot on white paper: you can describe the shape of the spot by saying, for each point on the sheet, whether it is black or white. To the fact that a point is black there corresponds a positive fact, and to the fact that a point is white (not black), a negative fact. If I designate a point on the sheet (a truth-value according to Frege), then this corresponds to the supposition that is put forward for judgement, etc. etc.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.064" depth="3">
      <german>Jeder Satz muss schon einen Sinn haben; die Bejahung kann ihn ihm nicht geben, denn sie bejaht ja gerade den Sinn. Und dasselbe gilt von der Verneinung, etc.</german>
      <ogden>Every proposition must already have a sense; assertion cannot give it a sense, for what it asserts is the sense itself. And the same holds of denial, etc.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Every proposition must already have a sense: it cannot be given a sense by affirmation. Indeed its sense is just what is affirmed. And the same applies to negation, etc.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.0641" depth="4">
      <german>Man könnte sagen: Die Verneinung bezieht sich schon auf den logischen Ort, den der verneinte Satz bestimmt.</german>
      <ogden>One could say, the denial is already related to the logical place determined by the proposition that is denied.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>One could say that negation must be related to the logical place determined by the negated proposition.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.1" depth="1">
      <german>Der Satz stellt das Bestehen und Nichtbestehen der Sachverhalte dar.</german>
      <ogden>A proposition presents the existence and non-existence of atomic facts.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Propositions represent the existence and non-existence of states of affairs.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.11" depth="2">
      <german>Die Gesamtheit der wahren Sätze ist die gesamte Naturwissenschaft (oder die Gesamtheit der Naturwissenschaften).</german>
      <ogden>The totality of true propositions is the total natural science (or the totality of the natural sciences).</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The totality of true propositions is the whole of natural science (or the whole corpus of the natural sciences).</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.111" depth="3">
      <german>Die Philosophie ist keine der Naturwissenschaften.</german>
      <ogden>Philosophy is not one of the natural sciences.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Philosophy is not one of the natural sciences.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.112" depth="3">
      <german>Der Zweck der Philosophie ist die logische Klärung der Gedanken.</german>
      <ogden>The object of philosophy is the logical clarification of thoughts.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Philosophy aims at the logical clarification of thoughts.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.1121" depth="4">
      <german>Die Psychologie ist der Philosophie nicht verwandter als irgend eine andere Naturwissenschaft.</german>
      <ogden>Psychology is no nearer related to philosophy, than is any other natural science.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Psychology is no more closely related to philosophy than any other natural science.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.1122" depth="4">
      <german>Die Darwinsche Theorie hat mit der Philosophie nicht mehr zu schaffen als irgendeine andere Hypothese der Naturwissenschaft.</german>
      <ogden>The Darwinian theory has no more to do with philosophy than has any other hypothesis of natural science.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Darwin’s theory has no more to do with philosophy than any other hypothesis in natural science.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.113" depth="3">
      <german>Die Philosophie begrenzt das bestreitbare Gebiet der Naturwissenschaft.</german>
      <ogden>Philosophy limits the disputable sphere of natural science.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Philosophy sets limits to the much disputed sphere of natural science.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.114" depth="3">
      <german>Sie soll das Denkbare abgrenzen und damit das Undenkbare.</german>
      <ogden>It should limit the thinkable and thereby the unthinkable.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>It must set limits to what can be thought; and, in doing so, to what cannot be thought.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.115" depth="3">
      <german>Sie wird das Unsagbare bedeuten, indem sie das Sagbare klar darstellt.</german>
      <ogden>It will mean the unspeakable by clearly displaying the speakable.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>It will signify what cannot be said, by presenting clearly what can be said.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.116" depth="3">
      <german>Alles was überhaupt gedacht werden kann, kann klar gedacht werden. Alles, was sich aussprechen lässt, lässt sich klar aussprechen.</german>
      <ogden>Everything that can be thought at all can be thought clearly. Everything that can be said can be said clearly.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Everything that can be thought at all can be thought clearly. Everything that can be put into words can be put clearly.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.12" depth="2">
      <german>Der Satz kann die gesamte Wirklichkeit darstellen, aber er kann nicht das darstellen, was er mit der Wirklichkeit gemein haben muss, um sie darstellen zu können – die logische Form.</german>
      <ogden>Propositions can represent the whole reality, but they cannot represent what they must have in common with reality in order to be able to represent it—the logical form.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Propositions can represent the whole of reality, but they cannot represent what they must have in common with reality in order to be able to represent it—logical form.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.121" depth="3">
      <german>Der Satz kann die logische Form nicht darstellen, sie spiegelt sich in ihm.</german>
      <ogden>Propositions cannot represent the logical form: this mirrors itself in the propositions.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Propositions cannot represent logical form: it is mirrored in them.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.1211" depth="4">
      <german>So zeigt ein Satz „ fa “, dass in seinem Sinn der Gegenstand a vorkommt, zwei Sätze „ fa “ und „ ga “, dass in ihnen beiden von demselben Gegenstand die Rede ist.</german>
      <ogden>Thus a proposition “ fa ” shows that in its sense the object a occurs, two propositions “ fa ” and “ ga ” that they are both about the same object.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Thus one proposition ‘ fa ’ shows that the object a occurs in its sense, two propositions ‘ fa ’ and ‘ ga ’ show that the same object is mentioned in both of them.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.1212" depth="4">
      <german>Was gezeigt werden kann , kann nicht gesagt werden.</german>
      <ogden>What can be shown cannot be said.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>What can be shown, cannot be said.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.1213" depth="4">
      <german>Jetzt verstehen wir auch unser Gefühl: dass wir im Besitze einer richtigen logischen Auffassung seien, wenn nur einmal alles in unserer Zeichensprache stimmt.</german>
      <ogden>Now we understand our feeling that we are in possession of the right logical conception, if only all is right in our symbolism.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Now, too, we understand our feeling that once we have a sign-language in which everything is all right, we already have a correct logical point of view.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.122" depth="3">
      <german>Wir können in gewissem Sinne von formalen Eigenschaften der Gegenstände und Sachverhalte bezw. von Eigenschaften der Struktur der Tatsachen reden, und in demselben Sinne von formalen Relationen und Relationen von Strukturen.</german>
      <ogden>We can speak in a certain sense of formal properties of objects and atomic facts, or of properties of the structure of facts, and in the same sense of formal relations and relations of structures.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>In a certain sense we can talk about formal properties of objects and states of affairs, or, in the case of facts, about structural properties: and in the same sense about formal relations and structural relations.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.1221" depth="4">
      <german>Eine interne Eigenschaft einer Tatsache können wir auch einen Zug dieser Tatsache nennen. (In dem Sinn, in welchem wir etwa von Gesichtszügen sprechen.)</german>
      <ogden>An internal property of a fact we also call a feature of this fact. (In the sense in which we speak of facial features.)</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>An internal property of a fact can also be called a feature of that fact (in the sense in which we speak of facial features, for example).</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.123" depth="3">
      <german>Eine Eigenschaft ist intern, wenn es undenkbar ist, dass ihr Gegenstand sie nicht besitzt.</german>
      <ogden>A property is internal if it is unthinkable that its object does not possess it.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>A property is internal if it is unthinkable that its object should not possess it.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.124" depth="3">
      <german>Das Bestehen einer internen Eigenschaft einer möglichen Sachlage wird nicht durch einen Satz ausgedrückt, sondern es drückt sich in dem sie darstellenden Satz durch eine interne Eigenschaft dieses Satzes aus.</german>
      <ogden>The existence of an internal property of a possible state of affairs is not expressed by a proposition, but it expresses itself in the proposition which presents that state of affairs, by an internal property of this proposition.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The existence of an internal property of a possible situation is not expressed by means of a proposition: rather, it expresses itself in the proposition representing the situation, by means of an internal property of that proposition.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.1241" depth="4">
      <german>Formen kann man nicht dadurch voneinander unterscheiden, dass man sagt, die eine habe diese, die andere aber jene Eigenschaft; denn dies setzt voraus, dass es einen Sinn habe, beide Eigenschaften von beiden Formen auszusagen.</german>
      <ogden>One cannot distinguish forms from one another by saying that one has this property, the other that: for this assumes that there is a sense in asserting either property of either form.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>It is impossible to distinguish forms from one another by saying that one has this property and another that property: for this presupposes that it makes sense to ascribe either property to either form.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.125" depth="3">
      <german>Das Bestehen einer internen Relation zwischen möglichen Sachlagen drückt sich sprachlich durch eine interne Relation zwischen den sie darstellenden Sätzen aus.</german>
      <ogden>The existence of an internal relation between possible states of affairs expresses itself in language by an internal relation between the propositions presenting them.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The existence of an internal relation between possible situations expresses itself in language by means of an internal relation between the propositions representing them.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.1251" depth="4">
      <german>Hier erledigt sich nun die Streitfrage, „ob alle Relationen intern oder extern seien“.</german>
      <ogden>Now this settles the disputed question “whether all relations are internal or external”.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Here we have the answer to the vexed question ‘whether all relations are internal or external’.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.1252" depth="4">
      <german>Reihen, welche durch interne Relationen geordnet sind, nenne ich Formenreihen.</german>
      <ogden>Series which are ordered by internal relations I call formal series.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>I call a series that is ordered by an internal relation a series of forms.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.126" depth="3">
      <german>In dem Sinne, in welchem wir von formalen Eigenschaften sprechen, können wir nun auch von formalen Begriffen reden.</german>
      <ogden>In the sense in which we speak of formal properties we can now speak also of formal concepts.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>We can now talk about formal concepts, in the same sense that we speak of formal properties.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.127" depth="3">
      <german>Die Satzvariable bezeichnet den formalen Begriff und ihre Werte die Gegenstände, welche unter diesen Begriff fallen.</german>
      <ogden>The propositional variable signifies the formal concept, and its values signify the objects which fall under this concept.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The propositional variable signifies the formal concept, and its values signify the objects that fall under the concept.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.1271" depth="4">
      <german>Jede Variable ist das Zeichen eines formalen Begriffes.</german>
      <ogden>Every variable is the sign of a formal concept.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Every variable is the sign for a formal concept.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.1272" depth="4">
      <german>So ist der variable Name „ x “ das eigentliche Zeichen des Scheinbegriffes Gegenstand .</german>
      <ogden>So the variable name “ x ” is the proper sign of the pseudo-concept object .</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Thus the variable name ‘ x ’ is the proper sign for the pseudo-concept object .</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.12721" depth="5">
      <german>Der formale Begriff ist mit einem Gegenstand, der unter ihn fällt, bereits gegeben. Man kann also nicht Gegenstände eines formalen Begriffes und den formalen Begriff selbst als Grundbegriffe einführen. Man kann also z. B. nicht den Begriff der Funktion, und auch spezielle Funktionen (wie Russell) als Grundbegriffe einführen; oder den Begriff der Zahl und bestimmte Zahlen.</german>
      <ogden>The formal concept is already given with an object, which falls under it. One cannot, therefore, introduce both, the objects which fall under a formal concept and the formal concept itself, as primitive ideas. One cannot, therefore, e.g. introduce (as Russell does) the concept of function and also special functions as primitive ideas; or the concept of number and definite numbers.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>A formal concept is given immediately any object falling under it is given. It is not possible, therefore, to introduce as primitive ideas objects belonging to a formal concept and the formal concept itself. So it is impossible, for example, to introduce as primitive ideas both the concept of a function and specific functions, as Russell does; or the concept of a number and particular numbers.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.1273" depth="4">
      <german>Wollen wir den allgemeinen Satz: „ b ist ein Nachfolger von a “ in der Begriffsschrift ausdrücken, so brauchen wir hierzu einen Ausdruck für das allgemeine Glied der Formenreihe:</german>
      <ogden>If we want to express in logical symbolism the general proposition “ b is a successor of a ” we need for this an expression for the general term of the formal series:</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>If we want to express in conceptual notation the general proposition, ‘ b is a successor of a ’, then we require an expression for the general term of the series of forms</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.1274" depth="4">
      <german>Die Frage nach der Existenz eines formalen Begriffes ist unsinnig. Denn kein Satz kann eine solche Frage beantworten.</german>
      <ogden>The question about the existence of a formal concept is senseless. For no proposition can answer such a question.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>To ask whether a formal concept exists is nonsensical. For no proposition can be the answer to such a question.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.128" depth="3">
      <german>Die logischen Formen sind zah llos .</german>
      <ogden>The logical forms are anumerical .</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Logical forms are without number.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.2" depth="1">
      <german>Der Sinn des Satzes ist seine Übereinstimmung und Nichtübereinstimmung mit den Möglichkeiten des Bestehens und Nichtbestehens der Sachverhalte.</german>
      <ogden>The sense of a proposition is its agreement and disagreement with the possibilities of the existence and non-existence of the atomic facts.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The sense of a proposition is its agreement and disagreement with possibilities of existence and non-existence of states of affairs.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.21" depth="2">
      <german>Der einfachste Satz, der Elementarsatz, behauptet das Bestehen eines Sachverhaltes.</german>
      <ogden>The simplest proposition, the elementary proposition, asserts the existence of an atomic fact.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The simplest kind of proposition, an elementary proposition, asserts the existence of a state of affairs.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.211" depth="3">
      <german>Ein Zeichen des Elementarsatzes ist es, dass kein Elementarsatz mit ihm in Widerspruch stehen kann.</german>
      <ogden>It is a sign of an elementary proposition, that no elementary proposition can contradict it.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>It is a sign of a proposition’s being elementary that there can be no elementary proposition contradicting it.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.22" depth="2">
      <german>Der Elementarsatz besteht aus Namen. Er ist ein Zusammenhang, eine Verkettung, von Namen.</german>
      <ogden>The elementary proposition consists of names. It is a connexion, a concatenation, of names.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>An elementary proposition consists of names. It is a nexus, a concatenation, of names.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.221" depth="3">
      <german>Es ist offenbar, dass wir bei der Analyse der Sätze auf Elementarsätze kommen müssen, die aus Namen in unmittelbarer Verbindung bestehen.</german>
      <ogden>It is obvious that in the analysis of propositions we must come to elementary propositions, which consist of names in immediate combination.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>It is obvious that the analysis of propositions must bring us to elementary propositions which consist of names in immediate combination.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.2211" depth="4">
      <german>Auch wenn die Welt unendlich komplex ist, so dass jede Tatsache aus unendlich vielen Sachverhalten besteht und jeder Sachverhalt aus unendlich vielen Gegenständen zusammengesetzt ist, auch dann müsste es Gegenstände und Sachverhalte geben.</german>
      <ogden>Even if the world is infinitely complex, so that every fact consists of an infinite number of atomic facts and every atomic fact is composed of an infinite number of objects, even then there must be objects and atomic facts.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Even if the world is infinitely complex, so that every fact consists of infinitely many states of affairs and every state of affairs is composed of infinitely many objects, there would still have to be objects and states of affairs.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.23" depth="2">
      <german>Der Name kommt im Satz nur im Zusammenhange des Elementarsatzes vor.</german>
      <ogden>The name occurs in the proposition only in the context of the elementary proposition.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>It is only in the nexus of an elementary proposition that a name occurs in a proposition.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.24" depth="2">
      <german>Die Namen sind die einfachen Symbole, ich deute sie durch einzelne Buchstaben („ x “, „ y “, „ z “) an.</german>
      <ogden>The names are the simple symbols, I indicate them by single letters ( x , y , z ).</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Names are the simple symbols: I indicate them by single letters (‘ x ’, ‘ y ’, ‘ z ’).</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.241" depth="3">
      <german>Gebrauche ich zwei Zeichen in ein und derselben Bedeutung, so drücke ich dies aus, indem ich zwischen beide das Zeichen „=“ setze.</german>
      <ogden>If I use two signs with one and the same meaning, I express this by putting between them the sign “=”.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>When I use two signs with one and the same meaning, I express this by putting the sign ‘=’ between them.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.242" depth="3">
      <german>Ausdrücke von der Form „ a = b “ sind also nur Behelfe der Darstellung; sie sagen nichts über die Bedeutung der Zeichen „ a “, „ b “ aus.</german>
      <ogden>Expressions of the form “ a = b ” are therefore only expedients in presentation: They assert nothing about the meaning of the signs “ a ” and “ b ”.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Expressions of the form ‘ a = b ’ are, therefore, mere representational devices. They state nothing about the meaning of the signs ‘ a ’ and ‘ b ’.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.243" depth="3">
      <german>Können wir zwei Namen verstehen, ohne zu wissen, ob sie dasselbe Ding oder zwei verschiedene Dinge bezeichnen? – Können wir einen Satz, worin zwei Namen vorkommen, verstehen, ohne zu wissen, ob sie Dasselbe oder Verschiedenes bedeuten?</german>
      <ogden>Can we understand two names without knowing whether they signify the same thing or two different things? Can we understand a proposition in which two names occur, without knowing if they mean the same or different things?</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Can we understand two names without knowing whether they signify the same thing or two different things?—Can we understand a proposition in which two names occur without knowing whether their meaning is the same or different?</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.25" depth="2">
      <german>Ist der Elementarsatz wahr, so besteht der Sachverhalt; ist der Elementarsatz falsch, so besteht der Sachverhalt nicht.</german>
      <ogden>If the elementary proposition is true, the atomic fact exists; if it is false the atomic fact does not exist.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>If an elementary proposition is true, the state of affairs exists: if an elementary proposition is false, the state of affairs does not exist.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.26" depth="2">
      <german>Die Angabe aller wahren Elementarsätze beschreibt die Welt vollständig. Die Welt ist vollständig beschrieben durch die Angaben aller Elementarsätze plus der Angabe, welche von ihnen wahr und welche falsch sind.</german>
      <ogden>The specification of all true elementary propositions describes the world completely. The world is completely described by the specification of all elementary propositions plus the specification, which of them are true and which false.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>If all true elementary propositions are given, the result is a complete description of the world. The world is completely described by giving all elementary propositions, and adding which of them are true and which false.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.27" depth="2">
      <german>Bezüglich des Bestehens und Nichtbestehens von n Sachverhalten gibt es K n = n ( n ν ) ∑ ν = 0 Möglichkeiten.</german>
      <ogden>With regard to the existence of n atomic facts there are K n = n ( n ν ) ∑ ν = 0 possibilities.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>For n states of affairs, there are K n = n ( n ν ) ∑ ν = 0 possibilities of existence and non-existence.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.28" depth="2">
      <german>Diesen Kombinationen entsprechen ebenso viele Möglichkeiten der Wahrheit – und Falschheit – von n Elementarsätzen.</german>
      <ogden>To these combinations correspond the same number of possibilities of the truth—and falsehood—of n elementary propositions.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>There correspond to these combinations the same number of possibilities of truth—and falsity—for n elementary propositions.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.3" depth="1">
      <german>Die Wahrheitsmöglichkeiten der Elementarsätze bedeuten die Möglichkeiten des Bestehens und Nichtbestehens der Sachverhalte.</german>
      <ogden>The truth-possibilities of the elementary propositions mean the possibilities of the existence and non-existence of the atomic facts.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Truth-possibilities of elementary propositions mean possibilities of existence and non-existence of states of affairs.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.31" depth="2">
      <german>Die Wahrheitsmöglichkeiten können wir durch Schemata folgender Art darstellen („W“ bedeutet „wahr“, „F“, „falsch“. Die Reihen der „W“ und „F“ unter der Reihe der Elementarsätze bedeuten in leichtverständlicher Symbolik deren Wahrheitsmöglichkeiten):</german>
      <ogden>The truth-possibilities can be presented by schemata of the following kind (“T” means “true”, “F” “false”. The rows of T’s and F’s under the row of the elementary propositions mean their truth-possibilities in an easily intelligible symbolism).</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>We can represent truth-possibilities by schemata of the following kind (‘T’ means ‘true’, ‘F’ means ‘false’; the rows of ‘T’s’ and ‘F’s’ under the row of elementary propositions symbolize their truth-possibilities in a way that can easily be understood):</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.4" depth="1">
      <german>Der Satz ist der Ausdruck der Übereinstimmung und Nichtübereinstimmung mit den Wahrheitsmöglichkeiten der Elementarsätze.</german>
      <ogden>A proposition is the expression of agreement and disagreement with the truth-possibilities of the elementary propositions.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>A proposition is an expression of agreement and disagreement with truth-possibilities of elementary propositions.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.41" depth="2">
      <german>Die Wahrheitsmöglichkeiten der Elementarsätze sind die Bedingungen der Wahrheit und Falschheit der Sätze.</german>
      <ogden>The truth-possibilities of the elementary propositions are the conditions of the truth and falsehood of the propositions.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Truth-possibilities of elementary propositions are the conditions of the truth and falsity of propositions.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.411" depth="3">
      <german>Es ist von vornherein wahrscheinlich, dass die Einführung der Elementarsätze für das Verständnis aller anderen Satzarten grundlegend ist. Ja, das Verständnis der allgemeinen Sätze hängt fühlbar von dem der Elementarsätze ab.</german>
      <ogden>It seems probable even at first sight that the introduction of the elementary propositions is fundamental for the comprehension of the other kinds of propositions. Indeed the comprehension of the general propositions depends palpably on that of the elementary propositions.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>It immediately strikes one as probable that the introduction of elementary propositions provides the basis for understanding all other kinds of proposition. Indeed the understanding of general propositions palpably depends on the understanding of elementary propositions.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.42" depth="2">
      <german>Bezüglich der Übereinstimmung und Nichtübereinstimmung eines Satzes mit den Wahrheitsmöglichkeiten von n Elementarsätzen gibt es K n ( K n κ ) = L n ∑ κ = 0 Möglichkeiten.</german>
      <ogden>With regard to the agreement and disagreement of a proposition with the truth-possibilities of n elementary propositions there are K n ( K n κ ) = L n ∑ κ = 0 possibilities.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>For n elementary propositions there are K n ( K n κ ) = L n ∑ κ = 0 ways in which a proposition can agree and disagree with their truth possibilities.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.43" depth="2">
      <german>Die Übereinstimmung mit den Wahrheitsmöglichkeiten können wir dadurch ausdrücken, indem wir ihnen im Schema etwa das Abzeichen „W“ (wahr) zuordnen.</german>
      <ogden>Agreement with the truth-possibilities can be expressed by co-ordinating with them in the schema the mark “T” (true).</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>We can express agreement with truth-possibilities by correlating the mark ‘T’ (true) with them in the schema.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.431" depth="3">
      <german>Der Ausdruck der Übereinstimmung und Nichtübereinstimmung mit den Wahrheitsmöglichkeiten der Elementarsätze drückt die Wahrheitsbedingungen des Satzes aus.</german>
      <ogden>The expression of the agreement and disagreement with the truth-possibilities of the elementary propositions expresses the truth-conditions of the proposition.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The expression of agreement and disagreement with the truth possibilities of elementary propositions expresses the truth-conditions of a proposition.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.44" depth="2">
      <german>Das Zeichen, welches durch die Zuordnung jener Abzeichen „W“ und der Wahrheitsmöglichkeiten entsteht, ist ein Satzzeichen.</german>
      <ogden>The sign which arises from the co-ordination of that mark “T” with the truth-possibilities is a propositional sign.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The sign that results from correlating the mark ‘T’ with truth-possibilities is a propositional sign.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.441" depth="3">
      <german>Es ist klar, dass dem Komplex der Zeichen „F“ und „W“ kein Gegenstand (oder Komplex von Gegenständen) entspricht; so wenig, wie den horizontalen und vertikalen Strichen oder den Klammern. – „Logische Gegenstände“ gibt es nicht.</german>
      <ogden>It is clear that to the complex of the signs “F” and “T” no object (or complex of objects) corresponds; any more than to horizontal and vertical lines or to brackets. There are no “logical objects”.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>It is clear that a complex of the signs ‘F’ and ‘T’ has no object (or complex of objects) corresponding to it, just as there is none corresponding to the horizontal and vertical lines or to the brackets.—There are no ‘logical objects’.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.442" depth="3">
      <german>Es ist z. B.:</german>
      <ogden>Thus e.g.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>For example, the following is a propositional sign:</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.45" depth="2">
      <german>Für n Elementarsätze gibt es L n mögliche Gruppen von Wahrheitsbedingungen.</german>
      <ogden>For n elementary propositions there are L n possible groups of truth-conditions.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>For n elementary propositions there are L n possible groups of truth-conditions.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.46" depth="2">
      <german>Unter den möglichen Gruppen von Wahrheitsbedingungen gibt es zwei extreme Fälle.</german>
      <ogden>Among the possible groups of truth-conditions there are two extreme cases.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Among the possible groups of truth-conditions there are two extreme cases.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.461" depth="3">
      <german>Der Satz zeigt was er sagt, die Tautologie und die Kontradiktion, dass sie nichts sagen.</german>
      <ogden>The proposition shows what it says, the tautology and the contradiction that they say nothing.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Propositions show what they say: tautologies and contradictions show that they say nothing.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.4611" depth="4">
      <german>Tautologie und Kontradiktion sind aber nicht unsinnig; sie gehören zum Symbolismus, und zwar ähnlich wie die „0“ zum Symbolismus der Arithmetik.</german>
      <ogden>Tautology and contradiction are, however, not nonsensical; they are part of the symbolism, in the same way that “0” is part of the symbolism of Arithmetic.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Tautologies and contradictions are not, however, nonsensical. They are part of the symbolism, much as ‘0’ is part of the symbolism of arithmetic.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.462" depth="3">
      <german>Tautologie und Kontradiktion sind nicht Bilder der Wirklichkeit. Sie stellen keine mögliche Sachlage dar. Denn jene lässt jede mögliche Sachlage zu, diese keine .</german>
      <ogden>Tautology and contradiction are not pictures of the reality. They present no possible state of affairs. For the one allows every possible state of affairs, the other none .</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Tautologies and contradictions are not pictures of reality. They do not represent any possible situations. For the former admit all possible situations, and latter none .</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.463" depth="3">
      <german>Die Wahrheitsbedingungen bestimmen den Spielraum, der den Tatsachen durch den Satz gelassen wird.</german>
      <ogden>The truth-conditions determine the range, which is left to the facts by the proposition.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The truth-conditions of a proposition determine the range that it leaves open to the facts.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.464" depth="3">
      <german>Die Wahrheit der Tautologie ist gewiss, des Satzes möglich, der Kontradiktion unmöglich.</german>
      <ogden>The truth of tautology is certain, of propositions possible, of contradiction impossible.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>A tautology’s truth is certain, a proposition’s possible, a contradiction’s impossible.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.465" depth="3">
      <german>Das logische Produkt einer Tautologie und eines Satzes sagt dasselbe, wie der Satz. Also ist jenes Produkt identisch mit dem Satz. Denn man kann das Wesentliche des Symbols nicht ändern, ohne seinen Sinn zu ändern.</german>
      <ogden>The logical product of a tautology and a proposition says the same as the proposition. Therefore that product is identical with the proposition. For the essence of the symbol cannot be altered without altering its sense.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The logical product of a tautology and a proposition says the same thing as the proposition. This product, therefore, is identical with the proposition. For it is impossible to alter what is essential to a symbol without altering its sense.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.466" depth="3">
      <german>Einer bestimmten logischen Verbindung von Zeichen entspricht eine bestimmte logische Verbindung ihrer Bedeutungen; jede beliebige Verbindung entspricht nur den unverbundenen Zeichen.</german>
      <ogden>To a definite logical combination of signs corresponds a definite logical combination of their meanings; every arbitrary combination only corresponds to the unconnected signs.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>What corresponds to a determinate logical combination of signs is a determinate logical combination of their meanings. It is only to the uncombined signs that absolutely any combination corresponds.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.4661" depth="4">
      <german>Freilich sind auch in der Tautologie und Kontradiktion die Zeichen noch mit einander verbunden, d. h. sie stehen in Beziehungen zu einander, aber diese Beziehungen sind bedeutungslos, dem Symbol unwesentlich.</german>
      <ogden>Of course the signs are also combined with one another in the tautology and contradiction, i.e. they stand in relations to one another, but these relations are meaningless, unessential to the symbol .</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Admittedly the signs are still combined with one another even in tautologies and contradictions—i.e. they stand in certain relations to one another: but these relations have no meaning, they are not essential to the symbol .</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.5" depth="1">
      <german>Nun scheint es möglich zu sein, die allgemeinste Satzform anzugeben: das heißt, eine Beschreibung der Sätze irgend einer Zeichensprache zu geben, so dass jeder mögliche Sinn durch ein Symbol, auf welches die Beschreibung passt, ausgedrückt werden kann, und dass jedes Symbol, worauf die Beschreibung passt, einen Sinn ausdrücken kann, wenn die Bedeutungen der Namen entsprechend gewählt werden.</german>
      <ogden>Now it appears to be possible to give the most general form of proposition; i.e. to give a description of the propositions of some one sign language, so that every possible sense can be expressed by a symbol, which falls under the description, and so that every symbol which falls under the description can express a sense, if the meanings of the names are chosen accordingly.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>It now seems possible to give the most general propositional form: that is, to give a description of the propositions of any sign-language whatsoever in such a way that every possible sense can be expressed by a symbol satisfying the description, and every symbol satisfying the description can express a sense, provided that the meanings of the names are suitably chosen.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.51" depth="2">
      <german>Angenommen, mir wären alle Elementarsätze gegeben: Dann lässt sich einfach fragen: Welche Sätze kann ich aus ihnen bilden. Und das sind alle Sätze und so sind sie begrenzt.</german>
      <ogden>Suppose all elementary propositions were given me: then we can simply ask: what propositions I can build out of them. And these are all propositions and so are they limited.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Suppose that I am given all elementary propositions: then I can simply ask what propositions I can construct out of them. And there I have all propositions, and that fixes their limits.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.52" depth="2">
      <german>Die Sätze sind Alles, was aus der Gesamtheit aller Elementarsätze folgt (natürlich auch daraus, dass es die Gesamtheit aller ist). (So könnte man in gewissem Sinne sagen, dass alle Sätze Verallgemeinerungen der Elementarsätze sind.)</german>
      <ogden>The propositions are everything which follows from the totality of all elementary propositions (of course also from the fact that it is the totality of them all ). (So, in some sense, one could say, that all propositions are generalizations of the elementary propositions.)</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Propositions comprise all that follows from the totality of all elementary propositions (and, of course, from its being the totality of them all ). (Thus, in a certain sense, it could be said that all propositions were generalizations of elementary propositions.)</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="4.53" depth="2">
      <german>Die allgemeine Satzform ist eine Variable.</german>
      <ogden>The general proposition form is a variable.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The general propositional form is a variable.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
  </proposition>
  <proposition id="5" depth="0">
    <german>Der Satz ist eine Wahrheitsfunktion der Elementarsätze.</german>
    <ogden>Propositions are truth-functions of elementary propositions.</ogden>
    <pears_mcguinness>A proposition is a truth-function of elementary propositions.</pears_mcguinness>
    <proposition id="5.01" depth="2">
      <german>Die Elementarsätze sind die Wahrheitsargumente des Satzes.</german>
      <ogden>The elementary propositions are the truth-arguments of propositions.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Elementary propositions are the truth-arguments of propositions.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.02" depth="2">
      <german>Es liegt nahe, die Argumente von Funktionen mit den Indices von Namen zu verwechseln. Ich erkenne nämlich sowohl am Argument wie am Index die Bedeutung des sie enthaltenden Zeichens.</german>
      <ogden>It is natural to confuse the arguments of functions with the indices of names. For I recognize the meaning of the sign containing it from the argument just as much as from the index.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The arguments of functions are readily confused with the affixes of names. For both arguments and affixes enable me to recognize the meaning of the signs containing them.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.1" depth="1">
      <german>Die Wahrheitsfunktionen lassen sich in Reihen ordnen.</german>
      <ogden>The truth-functions can be ordered in series.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Truth-functions can be arranged in series.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.101" depth="3">
      <german>Die Wahrheitsfunktionen jeder Anzahl von Elementarsätzen lassen sich in einem Schema folgender Art hinschreiben:</german>
      <ogden>The truth-functions of every number of elementary propositions can be written in a schema of the following kind:</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The truth-functions of a given number of elementary propositions can always be set out in a schema of the following kind:</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.11" depth="2">
      <german>Sind die Wahrheitsgründe, die einer Anzahl von Sätzen gemeinsam sind, sämtlich auch Wahrheitsgründe eines bestimmten Satzes, so sagen wir, die Wahrheit dieses Satzes folge aus der Wahrheit jener Sätze.</german>
      <ogden>If the truth-grounds which are common to a number of propositions are all also truth-grounds of some one proposition, we say that the truth of this proposition follows from the truth of those propositions.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>If all the truth-grounds that are common to a number of propositions are at the same time truth-grounds of a certain proposition, then we say that the truth of that proposition follows from the truth of the others.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.12" depth="2">
      <german>Insbesondere folgt die Wahrheit eines Satzes „ p “ aus der Wahrheit eines anderen „ q “, wenn alle Wahrheitsgründe des zweiten Wahrheitsgründe des ersten sind.</german>
      <ogden>In particular the truth of a proposition p follows from that of a proposition q , if all the truth-grounds of the second are truth-grounds of the first.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>In particular, the truth of a proposition ‘ p ’ follows from the truth of another proposition ‘ q ’ if all the truth-grounds of the latter are truth-grounds of the former.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.121" depth="3">
      <german>Die Wahrheitsgründe des einen sind in denen des anderen enthalten; p folgt aus q .</german>
      <ogden>The truth-grounds of q are contained in those of p ; p follows from q .</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The truth-grounds of the one are contained in those of the other: p follows from q .</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.122" depth="3">
      <german>Folgt p aus q , so ist der Sinn von „ p “ im Sinne von „ q “ enthalten.</german>
      <ogden>If p follows from q , the sense of “ p ” is contained in that of “ q ”.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>If p follows from q , the sense of ‘ p ’ is contained in the sense of ‘ q ’.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.123" depth="3">
      <german>Wenn ein Gott eine Welt erschafft, worin gewisse Sätze wahr sind, so schafft er damit auch schon eine Welt, in welcher alle ihre Folgesätze stimmen. Und ähnlich könnte er keine Welt schaffen, worin der Satz „ p “ wahr ist, ohne seine sämtlichen Gegenstände zu schaffen.</german>
      <ogden>If a god creates a world in which certain propositions are true, he creates thereby also a world in which all propositions consequent on them are true. And similarly he could not create a world in which the proposition “ p ” is true without creating all its objects.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>If a god creates a world in which certain propositions are true, then by that very act he also creates a world in which all the propositions that follow from them come true. And similarly he could not create a world in which the proposition ‘ p ’ was true without creating all its objects.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.124" depth="3">
      <german>Der Satz bejaht jeden Satz, der aus ihm folgt.</german>
      <ogden>A proposition asserts every proposition which follows from it.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>A proposition affirms every proposition that follows from it.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.1241" depth="4">
      <german>„ p . q “ ist einer der Sätze, welche „ p “ bejahen, und zugleich einer der Sätze, welche „ q “ bejahen.</german>
      <ogden>“ p . q ” is one of the propositions which assert “ p ” and at the same time one of the propositions which assert “ q ”.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>‘ p . q ’ is one of the propositions that affirm ‘ p ’ and at the same time one of the propositions that affirm ‘ q ’.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.13" depth="2">
      <german>Dass die Wahrheit eines Satzes aus der Wahrheit anderer Sätze folgt, ersehen wir aus der Struktur der Sätze.</german>
      <ogden>That the truth of one proposition follows from the truth of other propositions, we perceive from the structure of the propositions.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>When the truth of one proposition follows from the truth of others, we can see this from the structure of the propositions.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.131" depth="3">
      <german>Folgt die Wahrheit eines Satzes aus der Wahrheit anderer, so drückt sich dies durch Beziehungen aus, in welchen die Formen jener Sätze zu einander stehen; und zwar brauchen wir sie nicht erst in jene Beziehungen zu setzen, indem wir sie in einem Satz miteinander verbinden, sondern diese Beziehungen sind intern und bestehen, sobald, und dadurch dass, jene Sätze bestehen.</german>
      <ogden>If the truth of one proposition follows from the truth of others, this expresses itself in relations in which the forms of these propositions stand to one another, and we do not need to put them in these relations first by connecting them with one another in a proposition; for these relations are internal, and exist as soon as, and by the very fact that, the propositions exist.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>If the truth of one proposition follows from the truth of others, this finds expression in relations in which the forms of the propositions stand to one another: nor is it necessary for us to set up these relations between them, by combining them with one another in a single proposition; on the contrary, the relations are internal, and their existence is an immediate result of the existence of the propositions.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.1311" depth="4">
      <german>Wenn wir von p ∨ q und ~ p auf q schließen, so ist hier durch die Bezeichnungsweise die Beziehung der Satzformen von „ p ∨ q “ und „ ~ p “ verhüllt. Schreiben wir aber z. B. statt „ p ∨ q “ „ p | q .|. p | q “ und statt „ ~ p “ „ p | p “ ( p | q = weder p , noch q ), so wird der innere Zusammenhang offenbar.</german>
      <ogden>When we conclude from p ∨ q and ~ p to q the relation between the forms of the propositions “ p ∨ q ” and “ ~ p ” is here concealed by the method of symbolizing. But if we write, e.g. instead of “ p ∨ q ” “ p | q .|. p | q ” and instead of “ ~ p ” “ p | p ” ( p | q = neither p nor q ), then the inner connexion becomes obvious.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>When we infer q from p ∨ q and ~ p , the relation between the propositional forms of ‘ p ∨ q ’ and ‘ ~ p ’ is masked, in this case, by our mode of signifying. But if instead of ‘ p ∨ q ’ we write, for example, ‘ p | q .|. p | q ’, and instead of ‘ ~ p ’, ‘ p | p ’ ( p | q = neither p nor q ), then the inner connexion becomes obvious.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.132" depth="3">
      <german>Folgt p aus q , so kann ich von q auf p schließen; p aus q folgern.</german>
      <ogden>If p follows from q , I can conclude from q to p ; infer p from q .</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>If p follows from q , I can make an inference from q to p , deduce p from q .</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.133" depth="3">
      <german>Alles Folgern geschieht a priori.</german>
      <ogden>All inference takes place a priori.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>All deductions are made a priori .</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.134" depth="3">
      <german>Aus einem Elementarsatz lässt sich kein anderer folgern.</german>
      <ogden>From an elementary proposition no other can be inferred.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>One elementary proposition cannot be deduced from another.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.135" depth="3">
      <german>Auf keine Weise kann aus dem Bestehen irgend einer Sachlage auf das Bestehen einer von ihr gänzlich verschiedenen Sachlage geschlossen werden.</german>
      <ogden>In no way can an inference be made from the existence of one state of affairs to the existence of another entirely different from it.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>There is no possible way of making an inference from the existence of one situation to the existence of another, entirely different situation.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.136" depth="3">
      <german>Einen Kausalnexus, der einen solchen Schluss rechtfertigte, gibt es nicht.</german>
      <ogden>There is no causal nexus which justifies such an inference.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>There is no causal nexus to justify such an inference.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.1361" depth="4">
      <german>Die Ereignisse der Zukunft können wir nicht aus den gegenwärtigen erschließen.</german>
      <ogden>The events of the future cannot be inferred from those of the present.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>We cannot infer the events of the future from those of the present.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.1362" depth="4">
      <german>Die Willensfreiheit besteht darin, dass zukünftige Handlungen jetzt nicht gewusst werden können. Nur dann könnten wir sie wissen, wenn die Kausalität eine innere Notwendigkeit wäre, wie die des logischen Schlusses. – Der Zusammenhang von Wissen und Gewusstem ist der der logischen Notwendigkeit.</german>
      <ogden>The freedom of the will consists in the fact that future actions cannot be known now. We could only know them if causality were an inner necessity, like that of logical deduction.—The connexion of knowledge and what is known is that of logical necessity.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The freedom of the will consists in the impossibility of knowing actions that still lie in the future. We could know them only if causality were an inner necessity like that of logical inference.—The connexion between knowledge and what is known is that of logical necessity.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.1363" depth="4">
      <german>Wenn daraus, dass ein Satz uns einleuchtet, nicht folgt , dass er wahr ist, so ist das Einleuchten auch keine Rechtfertigung für unseren Glauben an seine Wahrheit.</german>
      <ogden>If from the fact that a proposition is obvious to us it does not follow that it is true, then obviousness is no justification for our belief in its truth.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>If the truth of a proposition does not follow from the fact that it is self-evident to us, then its self-evidence in no way justifies our belief in its truth.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.14" depth="2">
      <german>Folgt ein Satz aus einem anderen, so sagt dieser mehr als jener, jener weniger als dieser.</german>
      <ogden>If a proposition follows from another, then the latter says more than the former, the former less than the latter.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>If one proposition follows from another, then the latter says more than the former, and the former less than the latter.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.141" depth="3">
      <german>Folgt p aus q und q aus p , so sind sie ein und derselbe Satz.</german>
      <ogden>If p follows from q and q from p then they are one and the same proposition.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>If p follows from q and q from p , then they are one and the same proposition.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.142" depth="3">
      <german>Die Tautologie folgt aus allen Sätzen: sie sagt nichts.</german>
      <ogden>A tautology follows from all propositions: it says nothing.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>A tautology follows from all propositions: it says nothing.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.143" depth="3">
      <german>Die Kontradiktion ist das Gemeinsame der Sätze, was kein Satz mit einem anderen gemein hat. Die Tautologie ist das Gemeinsame aller Sätze, welche nichts miteinander gemein haben.</german>
      <ogden>Contradiction is something shared by propositions, which no proposition has in common with another. Tautology is that which is shared by all propositions, which have nothing in common with one another.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Contradiction is that common factor of propositions which no proposition has in common with another. Tautology is the common factor of all propositions that have nothing in common with one another.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.15" depth="2">
      <german>Ist W r die Anzahl der Wahrheitsgründe des Satzes „ r “, W rs die Anzahl derjenigen Wahrheitsgründe des Satzes „ s “, die zugleich Wahrheitsgründe von „ r “ sind, dann nennen wir das Verhältnis: W rs : W r das Maß der Wahrscheinlichkeit , welche der Satz „ r “ dem Satz „ s “ gibt.</german>
      <ogden>If T r is the number of the truth-grounds of the proposition “ r ”, T rs the number of those truth-grounds of the proposition “ s ” which are at the same time truth-grounds of “ r ”, then we call the ratio T rs : T r the measure of the probability which the proposition “ r ” gives to the proposition “ s ”.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>If T r is the number of the truth-grounds of a proposition ‘ r ’, and if T rs is the number of the truth-grounds of a proposition ‘ s ’ that are at the same time truth-grounds of ‘ r ’, then we call the ratio T rs : T r the degree of probability that the proposition ‘ r ’ gives to the proposition ‘ s ’.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.151" depth="3">
      <german>Sei in einem Schema wie dem obigen in No. 5.101 W r die Anzahl der „W“ im Satze r ; W rs die Anzahl derjenigen „W“ im Satze s , die in gleichen Kolonnen mit „W“ des Satzes r stehen. Der Satz r gibt dann dem Satze s die Wahrscheinlichkeit: W rs : W r .</german>
      <ogden>Suppose in a schema like that above in No. 5.101 T r is the number of the “T” ’s in the proposition r , T rs the number of those “T” ’s in the proposition s , which stand in the same columns as “T” ’s of the proposition r ; then the proposition r gives to the proposition s the probability T rs : T r .</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>In a schema like the one above in 5.101, let T r be the number of ‘T’s’ in the proposition r , and let T rs , be the number of ‘T’s’ in the proposition s that stand in columns in which the proposition r has ‘T’s’. Then the proposition r gives to the proposition s the probability T rs : T r .</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.1511" depth="4">
      <german>Es gibt keinen besonderen Gegenstand, der den Wahrscheinlichkeitssätzen eigen wäre.</german>
      <ogden>There is no special object peculiar to probability propositions.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>There is no special object peculiar to probability propositions.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.152" depth="3">
      <german>Sätze, welche keine Wahrheitsargumente mit einander gemein haben, nennen wir von einander unabhängig.</german>
      <ogden>Propositions which have no truth-arguments in common with one another we call independent.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>When propositions have no truth-arguments in common with one another, we call them independent of one another.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.153" depth="3">
      <german>Ein Satz ist an sich weder wahrscheinlich noch unwahrscheinlich. Ein Ereignis trifft ein, oder es trifft nicht ein, ein Mittelding gibt es nicht.</german>
      <ogden>A proposition is in itself neither probable nor improbable. An event occurs or does not occur, there is no middle course.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>In itself, a proposition is neither probable nor improbable. Either an event occurs or it does not: there is no middle way.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.154" depth="3">
      <german>In einer Urne seien gleichviel weiße und schwarze Kugeln (und keine anderen). Ich ziehe eine Kugel nach der anderen und lege sie wieder in die Urne zurück. Dann kann ich durch den Versuch feststellen, dass sich die Zahlen der gezogenen schwarzen und weißen Kugeln bei fortgesetztem Ziehen einander nähern.</german>
      <ogden>In an urn there are equal numbers of white and black balls (and no others). I draw one ball after another and put them back in the urn. Then I can determine by the experiment that the numbers of the black and white balls which are drawn approximate as the drawing continues.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Suppose that an urn contains black and white balls in equal numbers (and none of any other kind). I draw one ball after another, putting them back into the urn. By this experiment I can establish that the number of black balls drawn and the number of white balls drawn approximate to one another as the draw continues.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.155" depth="3">
      <german>Die Einheit des Wahrscheinlichkeitssatzes ist: Die Umstände – die ich sonst nicht weiter kenne – geben dem Eintreffen eines bestimmten Ereignisses den und den Grad der Wahrscheinlichkeit.</german>
      <ogden>The unit of the probability proposition is: The circumstances—with which I am not further acquainted—give to the occurrence of a definite event such and such a degree of probability.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The minimal unit for a probability proposition is this: The circumstances—of which I have no further knowledge—give such and such a degree of probability to the occurrence of a particular event.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.156" depth="3">
      <german>So ist die Wahrscheinlichkeit eine Verallgemeinerung.</german>
      <ogden>Probability is a generalization.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>It is in this way that probability is a generalization.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.2" depth="1">
      <german>Die Strukturen der Sätze stehen in internen Beziehungen zu einander.</german>
      <ogden>The structures of propositions stand to one another in internal relations.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The structures of propositions stand in internal relations to one another.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.21" depth="2">
      <german>Wir können diese internen Beziehungen dadurch in unserer Ausdrucksweise hervorheben, dass wir einen Satz als Resultat einer Operation darstellen, die ihn aus anderen Sätzen (den Basen der Operation) hervorbringt.</german>
      <ogden>We can bring out these internal relations in our manner of expression, by presenting a proposition as the result of an operation which produces it from other propositions (the bases of the operation).</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>In order to give prominence to these internal relations we can adopt the following mode of expression: we can represent a proposition as the result of an operation that produces it out of other propositions (which are the bases of the operation).</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.22" depth="2">
      <german>Die Operation ist der Ausdruck einer Beziehung zwischen den Strukturen ihres Resultats und ihrer Basen.</german>
      <ogden>The operation is the expression of a relation between the structures of its result and its bases.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>An operation is the expression of a relation between the structures of its result and of its bases.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.23" depth="2">
      <german>Die Operation ist das, was mit dem einen Satz geschehen muss, um aus ihm den anderen zu machen.</german>
      <ogden>The operation is that which must happen to a proposition in order to make another out of it.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The operation is what has to be done to the one proposition in order to make the other out of it.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.231" depth="3">
      <german>Und das wird natürlich von ihren formalen Eigenschaften, von der internen Ähnlichkeit ihrer Formen abhängen.</german>
      <ogden>And that will naturally depend on their formal properties, on the internal similarity of their forms.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>And that will, of course, depend on their formal properties, on the internal similarity of their forms.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.232" depth="3">
      <german>Die interne Relation, die eine Reihe ordnet, ist äquivalent mit der Operation, durch welche ein Glied aus dem anderen entsteht.</german>
      <ogden>The internal relation which orders a series is equivalent to the operation by which one term arises from another.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The internal relation by which a series is ordered is equivalent to the operation that produces one term from another.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.233" depth="3">
      <german>Die Operation kann erst dort auftreten, wo ein Satz auf logisch bedeutungsvolle Weise aus einem anderen entsteht. Also dort, wo die logische Konstruktion des Satzes anfängt.</german>
      <ogden>The first place in which an operation can occur is where a proposition arises from another in a logically significant way; i.e. where the logical construction of the proposition begins.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Operations cannot make their appearance before the point at which one proposition is generated out of another in a logically meaningful way; i.e. the point at which the logical construction of propositions begins.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.234" depth="3">
      <german>Die Wahrheitsfunktionen der Elementarsätze sind Resultate von Operationen, die die Elementarsätze als Basen haben. (Ich nenne diese Operationen Wahrheitsoperationen.)</german>
      <ogden>The truth-functions of elementary proposition, are results of operations which have the elementary propositions as bases. (I call these operations, truth-operations.)</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Truth-functions of elementary propositions are results of operations with elementary propositions as bases. (These operations I call truth-operations.)</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.2341" depth="4">
      <german>Der Sinn einer Wahrheitsfunktion von p ist eine Funktion des Sinnes von p .</german>
      <ogden>The sense of a truth-function of p is a function of the sense of p .</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The sense of a truth-function of p is a function of the sense of p .</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.24" depth="2">
      <german>Die Operation zeigt sich in einer Variablen; sie zeigt, wie man von einer Form von Sätzen zu einer anderen gelangen kann.</german>
      <ogden>An operation shows itself in a variable; it shows how we can proceed from one form of proposition to another.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>An operation manifests itself in a variable; it shows how we can get from one form of proposition to another.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.241" depth="3">
      <german>Die Operation kennzeichnet keine Form, sondern nur den Unterschied der Formen.</german>
      <ogden>The operation does not characterize a form but only the difference between forms.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>An operation is not the mark of a form, but only of a difference between forms.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.242" depth="3">
      <german>Dieselbe Operation, die „ q “ aus „ p “ macht, macht aus „ q “ „ r “ u. s. f. Dies kann nur darin ausgedrückt sein, dass „ p “, „ q “, „ r “, etc. Variable sind, die gewisse formale Relationen allgemein zum Ausdruck bringen.</german>
      <ogden>The same operation which makes “ q ” from “ p ”, makes “ r ” from “ q ”, and so on. This can only be expressed by the fact that “ p ”, “ q ”, “ r ”, etc., are variables which give general expression to certain formal relations.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The operation that produces ‘ q ’ from ‘ p ’ also produces ‘ r ’ from ‘ q ’, and so on. There is only one way of expressing this: ‘ p ’, ‘ q ’, ‘ r ’, etc. have to be variables that give expression in a general way to certain formal relations.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.25" depth="2">
      <german>Das Vorkommen der Operation charakterisiert den Sinn des Satzes nicht.</german>
      <ogden>The occurrence of an operation does not characterize the sense of a proposition.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The occurrence of an operation does not characterize the sense of a proposition.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.251" depth="3">
      <german>Eine Funktion kann nicht ihr eigenes Argument sein, wohl aber kann das Resultat einer Operation ihre eigene Basis werden.</german>
      <ogden>A function cannot be its own argument, but the result of an operation can be its own basis.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>A function cannot be its own argument, whereas an operation can take one of its own results as its base.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.252" depth="3">
      <german>Nur so ist das Fortschreiten von Glied zu Glied in einer Formenreihe (von Type zu Type in den Hierarchien Russells und Whiteheads) möglich. (Russell und Whitehead haben die Möglichkeit dieses Fortschreitens nicht zugegeben, aber immer wieder von ihr Gebrauch gemacht.)</german>
      <ogden>Only in this way is the progress from term to term in a formal series possible (from type to type in the hierarchy of Russell and Whitehead). (Russell and Whitehead have not admitted the possibility of this progress but have made use of it all the same.)</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>It is only in this way that the step from one term of a series of forms to another is possible (from one type to another in the hierarchies of Russell and Whitehead). (Russell and Whitehead did not admit the possibility of such steps, but repeatedly availed themselves of it.)</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.2521" depth="4">
      <german>Die fortgesetzte Anwendung einer Operation auf ihr eigenes Resultat nenne ich ihre successive Anwendung („ O ’ O ’ O ’ a “ ist das Resultat der dreimaligen successiven Anwendung von „ O ’ ξ “ auf „ a “).</german>
      <ogden>The repeated application of an operation to its own result I call its successive application (“ O ’ O ’ O ’ a ” is the result of the threefold successive application of “ O ’ ξ ” to “ a ”).</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>If an operation is applied repeatedly to its own results, I speak of successive applications of it. (‘ O ’ O ’ O ’ a ’ is the result of three successive applications of the operation ‘ O ’ ξ ’ to ‘ a ’.)</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.2522" depth="4">
      <german>Das allgemeine Glied einer Formenreihe a , O ’ a , O ’ O ’ a , … schreibe ich daher so: „ [ a , x , O ’ x ] “. Dieser Klammerausdruck ist eine Variable. Das erste Glied des Klammerausdruckes ist der Anfang der Formenreihe, das zweite die Form eines beliebigen Gliedes x der Reihe und das dritte die Form desjenigen Gliedes der Reihe, welches auf x unmittelbar folgt.</german>
      <ogden>The general term of the formal series a , O ’ a , O ’ O ’ a , … . I write thus: “ [ a , x , O ’ x ] ”. This expression in brackets is a variable. The first term of the expression is the beginning of the formal series, the second the form of an arbitrary term x of the series, and the third the form of that term of the series which immediately follows x .</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Accordingly I use the sign ‘ [ a , x , O ’ x ] ’ for the general term of the series of forms a , O ’ a , O ’ O ’ a , … . This bracketed expression is a variable: the first term of the bracketed expression is the beginning of the series of forms, the second is the form of a term x arbitrarily selected from the series, and the third is the form of the term that immediately follows x in the series.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.2523" depth="4">
      <german>Der Begriff der successiven Anwendung der Operation ist äquivalent mit dem Begriff „und so weiter“.</german>
      <ogden>The concept of the successive application of an operation is equivalent to the concept “and so on”.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The concept of successive applications of an operation is equivalent to the concept ‘and so on’.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.253" depth="3">
      <german>Eine Operation kann die Wirkung einer anderen rückgängig machen. Operationen können einander aufheben.</german>
      <ogden>One operation can reverse the effect of another. Operations can cancel one another.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>One operation can counteract the effect of another. Operations can cancel one another.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.254" depth="3">
      <german>Die Operation kann verschwinden (z. B. die Verneinung in „ ~ ~ p “: ~ ~ p = p ).</german>
      <ogden>Operations can vanish ( e.g. denial in “ ~ ~ p ”. ~ ~ p = p ).</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>An operation can vanish (e.g. negation in ‘ ~ ~ p ’: ~ ~ p = p ).</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.3" depth="1">
      <german>Alle Sätze sind Resultate von Wahrheitsoperationen mit den Elementarsätzen.</german>
      <ogden>All propositions are results of truth-operations on the elementary propositions.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>All propositions are results of truth-operations on elementary propositions.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.31" depth="2">
      <german>Die Schemata No. 4.31 haben auch dann eine Bedeutung, wenn „ p “, „ q “, „ r “, etc. nicht Elementarsätze sind.</german>
      <ogden>The Schemata No. 4.31 are also significant, if “ p ”, “ q ”, “ r ”, etc. are not elementary propositions.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The schemata in 4.31 have a meaning even when ‘ p ’, ‘ q ’, ‘ r ’, etc. are not elementary propositions.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.32" depth="2">
      <german>Alle Wahrheitsfunktionen sind Resultate der successiven Anwendung einer endlichen Anzahl von Wahrheitsoperationen auf die Elementarsätze.</german>
      <ogden>All truth-functions are results of the successive application of a finite number of truth-operations to elementary propositions.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>All truth-functions are results of successive applications to elementary propositions of a finite number of truth-operations.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.4" depth="1">
      <german>Hier zeigt es sich, dass es „logische Gegenstände“, „logische Konstante“ (im Sinne Freges und Russells) nicht gibt.</german>
      <ogden>Here it becomes clear that there are no such things as “logical objects” or “logical constants” (in the sense of Frege and Russell).</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>At this point it becomes manifest that there are no ‘logical objects’ or ‘logical constants’ (in Frege’s and Russell’s sense).</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.41" depth="2">
      <german>Denn: Alle Resultate von Wahrheitsoperationen mit Wahrheitsfunktionen sind identisch, welche eine und dieselbe Wahrheitsfunktion von Elementarsätzen sind.</german>
      <ogden>For all those results of truth-operations on truth-functions are identical, which are one and the same truth-function of elementary propositions.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The reason is that the results of truth-operations on truth-functions are always identical whenever they are one and the same truth-function of elementary propositions.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.42" depth="2">
      <german>Dass ∨, ⊃, etc. nicht Beziehungen im Sinne von rechts und links etc. sind, leuchtet ein.</german>
      <ogden>That ∨, ⊃, etc., are not relations in the sense of right and left, etc., is obvious.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>It is self-evident that ∨, ⊃, etc. are not relations in the sense in which right and left etc. are relations.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.43" depth="2">
      <german>Dass aus einer Tatsache p unendlich viele andere folgen sollten, nämlich ~ ~ p , ~ ~ ~ ~ p , etc., ist doch von vornherein kaum zu glauben. Und nicht weniger merkwürdig ist, dass die unendliche Anzahl der Sätze der Logik (der Mathematik) aus einem halben Dutzend „Grundgesetzen“ folgen.</german>
      <ogden>That from a fact p an infinite number of others should follow, namely, ~ ~ p , ~ ~ ~ ~ p , etc., is indeed hardly to be believed, and it is no less wonderful that the infinite number of propositions of logic (of mathematics) should follow from half a dozen “primitive propositions”.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Even at first sight it seems scarcely credible that there should follow from one fact p infinitely many others , namely ~ ~ p , ~ ~ ~ ~ p , etc. And it is no less remarkable that the infinite number of propositions of logic (mathematics) follow from half a dozen ‘primitive propositions’.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.44" depth="2">
      <german>Die Wahrheitsfunktionen sind keine materiellen Funktionen.</german>
      <ogden>Truth-functions are not material functions.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Truth-functions are not material functions.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.441" depth="3">
      <german>Dieses Verschwinden der scheinbaren logischen Konstanten tritt auch ein, wenn „ ~ ( ∃ x ). ~ fx “ dasselbe sagt wie „ ( x ). fx “, oder „ ( ∃ x ). fx . x = a “ dasselbe wie „ fa “.</german>
      <ogden>This disappearance of the apparent logical constants also occurs if “ ~ ( ∃ x ). ~ fx ” says the same as “ ( x ). fx ”, or “ ( ∃ x ). fx . x = a ” the same as “ fa ”.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>This vanishing of the apparent logical constants also occurs in the case of ‘ ~ ( ∃ x ). ~ fx ’, which says the same as ‘ ( x ). fx ’, and in the case of ‘ ( ∃ x ). fx . x = a ’, which says the same as ‘ fa ’.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.442" depth="3">
      <german>Wenn uns ein Satz gegeben ist, so sind mit ihm auch schon die Resultate aller Wahrheitsoperationen, die ihn zur Basis haben, gegeben.</german>
      <ogden>If a proposition is given to us then the results of all truth-operations which have it as their basis are given with it.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>If we are given a proposition, then with it we are also given the results of all truth-operations that have it as their base.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.45" depth="2">
      <german>Gibt es logische Urzeichen, so muss eine richtige Logik ihre Stellung zueinander klar machen und ihr Dasein rechtfertigen. Der Bau der Logik aus ihren Urzeichen muss klar werden.</german>
      <ogden>If there are logical primitive signs a correct logic must make clear their position relative to one another and justify their existence. The construction of logic out of its primitive signs must become clear.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>If there are primitive logical signs, then any logic that fails to show clearly how they are placed relatively to one another and to justify their existence will be incorrect. The construction of logic out of its primitive signs must be made clear.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.451" depth="3">
      <german>Hat die Logik Grundbegriffe, so müssen sie von einander unabhängig sein. Ist ein Grundbegriff eingeführt, so muss er in allen Verbindungen eingeführt sein, worin er überhaupt vorkommt. Man kann ihn also nicht zuerst für eine Verbindung, dann noch einmal für eine andere einführen. Z. B.: Ist die Verneinung eingeführt, so müssen wir sie jetzt in Sätzen von der Form „ ~ p “ ebenso verstehen, wie in Sätzen wie „ ~ ( p ∨ q ) “, „ ( ∃ x ). ~ fx “ u. a. Wir dürfen sie nicht erst für die eine Klasse von Fällen, dann für die andere einführen, denn es bliebe dann zweifelhaft, ob ihre Bedeutung in beiden Fällen die gleiche wäre und es wäre kein Grund vorhanden, in beiden Fällen dieselbe Art der Zeichenverbindung zu benützen.</german>
      <ogden>If logic has primitive ideas these must be independent of one another. If a primitive idea is introduced it must be introduced in all contexts in which it occurs at all. One cannot therefore introduce it for one context and then again for another. For example, if denial is introduced, we must understand it in propositions of the form “ ~ p ”, just as in propositions like “ ~ ( p ∨ q ) ”, “ ( ∃ x ). ~ fx ” and others. We may not first introduce it for one class of cases and then for another, for it would then remain doubtful whether its meaning in the two cases was the same, and there would be no reason to use the same way of symbolizing in the two cases.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>If logic has primitive ideas, they must be independent of one another. If a primitive idea has been introduced, it must have been introduced in all the combinations in which it ever occurs. It cannot, therefore, be introduced first for one combination and later reintroduced for another. For example, once negation has been introduced, we must understand it both in propositions of the form ‘ ~ p ’ and in propositions like ‘ ~ ( p ∨ q ) ’, ‘ ( ∃ x ). ~ fx ’, etc. We must not introduce it first for the one class of cases and then for the other, since it would then be left in doubt whether its meaning were the same in both cases, and no reason would have been given for combining the signs in the same way in both cases.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.452" depth="3">
      <german>Die Einführung eines neuen Behelfes in den Symbolismus der Logik muss immer ein folgenschweres Ereignis sein. Kein neuer Behelf darf in die Logik – sozusagen, mit ganz unschuldiger Miene – in Klammern oder unter dem Striche eingeführt werden.</german>
      <ogden>The introduction of a new expedient in the symbolism of logic must always be an event full of consequences. No new symbol may be introduced in logic in brackets or in the margin—with, so to speak, an entirely innocent face.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The introduction of any new device into the symbolism of logic is necessarily a momentous event. In logic a new device should not be introduced in brackets or in a footnote with what one might call a completely innocent air.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.453" depth="3">
      <german>Alle Zahlen der Logik müssen sich rechtfertigen lassen.</german>
      <ogden>All numbers in logic must be capable of justification.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>All numbers in logic stand in need of justification.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.454" depth="3">
      <german>In der Logik gibt es kein Nebeneinander, kann es keine Klassifikation geben.</german>
      <ogden>In logic there is no side by side, there can be no classification.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>In logic there is no co-ordinate status, and there can be no classification.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.4541" depth="4">
      <german>Die Lösungen der logischen Probleme müssen einfach sein, denn sie setzen den Standard der Einfachheit.</german>
      <ogden>The solution of logical problems must be neat for they set the standard of neatness.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The solutions of the problems of logic must be simple, since they set the standard of simplicity.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.46" depth="2">
      <german>Wenn man die logischen Zeichen richtig einführte, so hätte man damit auch schon den Sinn aller ihrer Kombinationen eingeführt; also nicht nur „ p ∨ q “ sondern auch schon „ ~ ( p ∨ ~ q ) “ etc. etc. Man hätte damit auch schon die Wirkung aller nur möglichen Kombinationen von Klammern eingeführt. Und damit wäre es klar geworden, dass die eigentlichen allgemeinen Urzeichen nicht die „ p ∨ q “, „ ( ∃ x ). fx “, etc. sind, sondern die allgemeinste Form ihrer Kombinationen.</german>
      <ogden>When we have rightly introduced the logical signs, the sense of all their combinations has been already introduced with them: therefore not only “ p ∨ q ” but also “ ~ ( p ∨ ~ q ) ”, etc. etc. We should then already have introduced the effect of all possible combinations of brackets; and it would then have become clear that the proper general primitive signs are not “ p ∨ q ”, “ ( ∃ x ). fx ”, etc., but the most general form of their combinations.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>If we introduced logical signs properly, then we should also have introduced at the same time the sense of all combinations of them; i.e. not only ‘ p ∨ q ’ but ‘ ~ ( p ∨ ~ q ) ’ as well, etc. etc. We should also have introduced at the same time the effect of all possible combinations of brackets. And thus it would have been made clear that the real general primitive signs are not ‘ p ∨ q ’, ‘ ( ∃ x ). fx ’, etc. but the most general form of their combinations.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.461" depth="3">
      <german>Bedeutungsvoll ist die scheinbar unwichtige Tatsache, dass die logischen Scheinbeziehungen, wie ∨ und ⊃, der Klammern bedürfen – im Gegensatz zu den wirklichen Beziehungen.</german>
      <ogden>The apparently unimportant fact that the apparent relations like ∨ and ⊃ need brackets—unlike real relations—is of great importance.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Though it seems unimportant, it is in fact significant that the pseudo-relations of logic, such as ∨ and ⊃, need brackets—unlike real relations.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.4611" depth="4">
      <german>Die logischen Operationszeichen sind Interpunktionen.</german>
      <ogden>Logical operation signs are punctuations.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Signs for logical operations are punctuation-marks.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.47" depth="2">
      <german>Es ist klar, dass alles, was sich überhaupt von vornherein über die Form aller Sätze sagen lässt, sich auf einmal sagen lassen muss.</german>
      <ogden>It is clear that everything which can be said beforehand about the form of all propositions at all can be said on one occasion .</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>It is clear that whatever we can say in advance about the form of all propositions, we must be able to say all at once .</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.471" depth="3">
      <german>Die allgemeine Satzform ist das Wesen des Satzes.</german>
      <ogden>The general form of proposition is the essence of proposition.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The general propositional form is the essence of a proposition.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.4711" depth="4">
      <german>Das Wesen des Satzes angeben, heißt, das Wesen aller Beschreibung angeben, also das Wesen der Welt.</german>
      <ogden>To give the essence of proposition means to give the essence of all description, therefore the essence of the world.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>To give the essence of a proposition means to give the essence of all description, and thus the essence of the world.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.472" depth="3">
      <german>Die Beschreibung der allgemeinsten Satzform ist die Beschreibung des einen und einzigen allgemeinen Urzeichens der Logik.</german>
      <ogden>The description of the most general propositional form is the description of the one and only general primitive sign in logic.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The description of the most general propositional form is the description of the one and only general primitive sign in logic.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.473" depth="3">
      <german>Die Logik muss für sich selber sorgen.</german>
      <ogden>Logic must take care of itself.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Logic must look after itself.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.4731" depth="4">
      <german>Das Einleuchten, von dem Russell so viel sprach, kann nur dadurch in der Logik entbehrlich werden, dass die Sprache selbst jeden logischen Fehler verhindert. – Dass die Logik a priori ist, besteht darin, dass nicht unlogisch gedacht werden kann .</german>
      <ogden>Self-evidence, of which Russell has said so much, can only be discarded in logic by language itself preventing every logical mistake. That logic is a priori consists in the fact that we cannot think illogically.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Self-evidence, which Russell talked about so much, can become dispensable in logic, only because language itself prevents every logical mistake.—What makes logic a priori is the impossibility of illogical thought.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.4732" depth="4">
      <german>Wir können einem Zeichen nicht den unrechten Sinn geben.</german>
      <ogden>We cannot give a sign the wrong sense.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>We cannot give a sign the wrong sense.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.47321" depth="5">
      <german>Occams Devise ist natürlich keine willkürliche, oder durch ihren praktischen Erfolg gerechtfertigte Regel: Sie besagt, dass unnötige Zeicheneinheiten nichts bedeuten.</german>
      <ogden>Occam’s razor is, of course, not an arbitrary rule nor one justified by its practical success. It simply says that unnecessary elements in a symbolism mean nothing.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Occam’s maxim is, of course, not an arbitrary rule, nor one that is justified by its success in practice: its point is that unnecessary units in a sign-language mean nothing.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.4733" depth="4">
      <german>Frege sagt: Jeder rechtmäßig gebildete Satz muss einen Sinn haben; und ich sage: Jeder mögliche Satz ist rechtmäßig gebildet, und wenn er keinen Sinn hat, so kann das nur daran liegen, dass wir einigen seiner Bestandteile keine Bedeutung gegeben haben.</german>
      <ogden>Frege says: Every legitimately constructed proposition must have a sense; and I say: Every possible proposition is legitimately constructed, and if it has no sense this can only be because we have given no meaning to some of its constituent parts.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Frege says that any legitimately constructed proposition must have a sense. And I say that any possible proposition is legitimately constructed, and, if it has no sense, that can only be because we have failed to give a meaning to some of its constituents.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.474" depth="3">
      <german>Die Anzahl der nötigen Grundoperationen hängt nur von unserer Notation ab.</german>
      <ogden>The number of necessary fundamental operations depends only on our notation.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The number of fundamental operations that are necessary depends solely on our notation.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.475" depth="3">
      <german>Es kommt nur darauf an, ein Zeichensystem von einer bestimmten Anzahl von Dimensionen – von einer bestimmten mathematischen Mannigfaltigkeit – zu bilden.</german>
      <ogden>It is only a question of constructing a system of signs of a definite number of dimensions—of a definite mathematical multiplicity.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>All that is required is that we should construct a system of signs with a particular number of dimensions—with a particular mathematical multiplicity.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.476" depth="3">
      <german>Es ist klar, dass es sich hier nicht um eine Anzahl von Grundbegriffen handelt, die bezeichnet werden müssen, sondern um den Ausdruck einer Regel.</german>
      <ogden>It is clear that we are not concerned here with a number of primitive ideas which must be signified but with the expression of a rule.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>It is clear that this is not a question of a number of primitive ideas that have to be signified, but rather of the expression of a rule.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.5" depth="1">
      <german>Jede Wahrheitsfunktion ist ein Resultat der successiven Anwendung der Operation (−−−−− W ) ( ξ , . . . . .) auf Elementarsätze.</german>
      <ogden>Every truth-function is a result of the successive application of the operation (−−−−− T ) ( ξ , . . . . .) to elementary propositions.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Every truth-function is a result of successive applications to elementary propositions of the operation ‘ (−−−−− T ) ( ξ , . . . . .) ’.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.501" depth="3">
      <german>Einen Klammerausdruck, dessen Glieder Sätze sind, deute ich – wenn die Reihenfolge der Glieder in der Klammer gleichgültig ist – durch ein Zeichen von der Form „ ( ξ ) “ an. „ ξ “ ist eine Variable, deren Werte die Glieder des Klammerausdruckes sind; und der Strich über der Variablen deutet an, dass sie ihre sämtlichen Werte in der Klammer vertritt.</german>
      <ogden>An expression in brackets whose terms are propositions I indicate—if the order of the terms in the bracket is indifferent—by a sign of the form “ ( ξ ) ”. “ ξ ” is a variable whose values are the terms of the expression in brackets, and the line over the variable indicates that it stands for all its values in the bracket.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>When a bracketed expression has propositions as its terms—and the order of the terms inside the brackets is indifferent—then I indicate it by a sign of the form ‘ ( ξ ) ’. ‘ ξ ’ is a variable whose values are terms of the bracketed expression and the bar over the variable indicates that it is the representative of all its values in the brackets.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.502" depth="3">
      <german>Ich schreibe also statt „ (−−−−− W ) ( ξ , . . . . .) “ „ N ( ξ ) “.</german>
      <ogden>Therefore I write instead of “ (−−−−− T ) ( ξ , . . . . .) ”, “ N ( ξ ) ”.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>So instead of ‘ (−−−−− T ) ( ξ , . . . . .) ’, I write ‘ N ( ξ ) ’.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.503" depth="3">
      <german>Da sich offenbar leicht ausdrücken lässt, wie mit dieser Operation Sätze gebildet werden können und wie Sätze mit ihr nicht zu bilden sind, so muss dies auch einen exakten Ausdruck finden können.</german>
      <ogden>As it is obviously easy to express how propositions can be constructed by means of this operation and how propositions are not to be constructed by means of it, this must be capable of exact expression.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>It is obvious that we can easily express how propositions may be constructed with this operation, and how they may not be constructed with it; so it must be possible to find an exact expression for this.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.51" depth="2">
      <german>Hat ξ nur einen Wert, so ist N ( ξ ) = ~ p (nicht p ), hat es zwei Werte, so ist N ( ξ ) = ~ p . ~ q (weder p noch q ).</german>
      <ogden>If ξ has only one value, then N ( ξ ) = ~ p (not p ), if it has two values then N ( ξ ) = ~ p . ~ q (neither p nor q ).</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>If ξ has only one value, then N ( ξ ) = ~ p (not p ); if it has two values, then N ( ξ ) = ~ p . ~ q (neither p nor q ).</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.511" depth="3">
      <german>Wie kann die allumfassende, weltspiegelnde Logik so spezielle Haken und Manipulationen gebrauchen? Nur, indem sich alle diese zu einem unendlich feinen Netzwerk, zu dem großen Spiegel, verknüpfen.</german>
      <ogden>How can the all-embracing logic which mirrors the world use such special catches and manipulations? Only because all these are connected into an infinitely fine network, to the great mirror.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>How can logic—all-embracing logic, which mirrors the world—use such peculiar crotchets and contrivances? Only because they are all connected with one another in an infinitely fine network, the great mirror.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.512" depth="3">
      <german>„ ~ p “ ist wahr, wenn „ p “ falsch ist. Also in dem wahren Satz „ ~ p “ ist „ p “ ein falscher Satz. Wie kann ihn nun der Strich „~“ mit der Wirklichkeit zum Stimmen bringen?</german>
      <ogden>“ ~ p ” is true if “ p ” is false. Therefore in the true proposition “ ~ p ” “ p ” is a false proposition. How then can the stroke “~” bring it into agreement with reality?</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>‘ ~ p ’ is true if ‘ p ’ is false. Therefore, in the proposition ‘ ~ p ’, when it is true, ‘ p ’ is a false proposition. How then can the stroke ‘~’ make it agree with reality?</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.513" depth="3">
      <german>Man könnte sagen: Das Gemeinsame aller Symbole, die sowohl p als q bejahen, ist der Satz „ p . q “. Das Gemeinsame aller Symbole, die entweder p oder q bejahen, ist der Satz „ p ∨ q “.</german>
      <ogden>We could say: What is common to all symbols, which assert both p and q , is the proposition “ p . q ”. What is common to all symbols, which asserts either p or q , is the proposition “ p ∨ q ”.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>We might say that what is common to all symbols that affirm both p and q is the proposition ‘ p . q ’; and that what is common to all symbols that affirm either p or q is the proposition ‘ p ∨ q ’.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.514" depth="3">
      <german>Ist eine Notation festgelegt, so gibt es in ihr eine Regel, nach der alle p verneinenden Sätze gebildet werden, eine Regel, nach der alle p bejahenden Sätze gebildet werden, eine Regel, nach der alle p oder q bejahenden Sätze gebildet werden, u. s. f. Diese Regeln sind den Symbolen äquivalent und in ihnen spiegelt sich ihr Sinn wieder.</german>
      <ogden>If a notation is fixed, there is in it a rule according to which all the propositions denying p are constructed, a rule according to which all the propositions asserting p are constructed, a rule according to which all the propositions asserting p or q are constructed, and so on. These rules are equivalent to the symbols and in them their sense is mirrored.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Once a notation has been established, there will be in it a rule governing the construction of all propositions that negate p , a rule governing the construction of all propositions that affirm p , and a rule governing the construction of all propositions that affirm p or q ; and so on. These rules are equivalent to the symbols; and in them their sense is mirrored.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.515" depth="3">
      <german>Es muss sich an unseren Symbolen zeigen, dass das, was durch „∨“, „.“, etc. miteinander verbunden ist, Sätze sein müssen.</german>
      <ogden>It must be recognized in our symbols that what is connected by “∨”, “.”, etc., must be propositions.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>It must be manifest in our symbols that it can only be propositions that are combined with one another by ‘∨’, ‘.’, etc.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.5151" depth="4">
      <german>Muss das Zeichen des negativen Satzes mit dem Zeichen des positiven gebildet werden? Warum sollte man den negativen Satz nicht durch eine negative Tatsache ausdrücken können. (Etwa: Wenn „ a “ nicht in einer bestimmten Beziehung zu „ b “ steht, könnte das ausdrücken, dass aRb nicht der Fall ist.)</german>
      <ogden>Must the sign of the negative proposition be constructed by means of the sign of the positive? Why should one not be able to express the negative proposition by means of a negative fact? (Like: if “ a ” does not stand in a certain relation to “ b ”, it could express that aRb is not the case.)</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Must the sign of a negative proposition be constructed with that of the positive proposition? Why should it not be possible to express a negative proposition by means of a negative fact? (E.g. suppose that ‘ a ’ does not stand in a certain relation to ‘ b ’; then this might be used to say that aRb was not the case.)</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.52" depth="2">
      <german>Sind die Werte von ξ sämtliche Werte einer Funktion fx für alle Werte von x , so wird N ( ξ ) = ~ ( ∃ x ). fx .</german>
      <ogden>If the values of ξ are the total values of a function fx for all values of x , then N ( ξ ) = ~ ( ∃ x ). fx .</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>If ξ has as its values all the values of a function fx for all values of x , then N ( ξ ) = ~ ( ∃ x ). fx .</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.521" depth="3">
      <german>Ich trenne den Begriff Alle von der Wahrheitsfunktion.</german>
      <ogden>I separate the concept all from the truth-function.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>I dissociate the concept all from truth-functions.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.522" depth="3">
      <german>Das Eigentümliche der Allgemeinheitsbezeichnung ist erstens, dass sie auf ein logisches Urbild hinweist, und zweitens, dass sie Konstante hervorhebt.</german>
      <ogden>That which is peculiar to the “symbolism of generality” is firstly, that it refers to a logical prototype, and secondly, that it makes constants prominent.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>What is peculiar to the generality-sign is first, that it indicates a logical prototype, and secondly, that it gives prominence to constants.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.523" depth="3">
      <german>Die Allgemeinheitsbezeichnung tritt als Argument auf.</german>
      <ogden>The generality symbol occurs as an argument.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The generality-sign occurs as an argument.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.524" depth="3">
      <german>Wenn die Gegenstände gegeben sind, so sind uns damit auch schon alle Gegenstände gegeben.</german>
      <ogden>If the objects are given, therewith are all objects also given.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>If objects are given, then at the same time we are given all objects.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.525" depth="3">
      <german>Es ist unrichtig, den Satz „ ( ∃ x ). fx “ – wie Russell dies tut – in Worten durch „ fx ist möglich “ wiederzugeben.</german>
      <ogden>It is not correct to render the proposition “ ( ∃ x ). fx ”—as Russell does—in the words “ fx is possible ”.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>It is incorrect to render the proposition ‘ ( ∃ x ). fx ’ in the words, ‘ fx is possible ’ as Russell does.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.526" depth="3">
      <german>Man kann die Welt vollständig durch vollkommen verallgemeinerte Sätze beschreiben, das heißt also, ohne irgendeinen Namen von vornherein einem bestimmten Gegenstand zuzuordnen.</german>
      <ogden>One can describe the world completely by completely generalized propositions, i.e. without from the outset co-ordinating any name with a definite object.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>We can describe the world completely by means of fully generalized propositions, i.e. without first correlating any name with a particular object.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.5261" depth="4">
      <german>Ein vollkommen verallgemeinerter Satz ist, wie jeder andere Satz, zusammengesetzt. (Dies zeigt sich daran, dass wir in „ ( ∃ x , φ ). φx “ „ φ “ und „ x “ getrennt erwähnen müssen. Beide stehen unabhängig in bezeichnenden Beziehungen zur Welt, wie im unverallgemeinerten Satz.)</german>
      <ogden>A completely generalized proposition is like every other proposition composite. (This is shown by the fact that in “ ( ∃ x , φ ). φx ” we must mention “ φ ” and “ x ” separately. Both stand independently in signifying relations to the world as in the ungeneralized proposition.)</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>A fully generalized proposition, like every other proposition, is composite. (This is shown by the fact that in ‘ ( ∃ x , φ ). φx ’ we have to mention ‘ φ ’ and ‘ x ’ separately. They both, independently, stand in signifying relations to the world, just as is the case in ungeneralized propositions.)</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.5262" depth="4">
      <german>Es verändert ja die Wahr- oder Falschheit jedes Satzes etwas am allgemeinen Bau der Welt. Und der Spielraum, welcher ihrem Bau durch die Gesamtheit der Elementarsätze gelassen wird, ist eben derjenige, welchen die ganz allgemeinen Sätze begrenzen.</german>
      <ogden>The truth or falsehood of every proposition alters something in the general structure of the world. And the range which is allowed to its structure by the totality of elementary propositions is exactly that which the completely general propositions delimit.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The truth or falsity of every proposition does make some alteration in the general construction of the world. And the range that the totality of elementary propositions leaves open for its construction is exactly the same as that which is delimited by entirely general propositions.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.53" depth="2">
      <german>Gleichheit des Gegenstandes drücke ich durch Gleichheit des Zeichens aus, und nicht mit Hilfe eines Gleichheitszeichens. Verschiedenheit der Gegenstände durch Verschiedenheit der Zeichen.</german>
      <ogden>Identity of the object I express by identity of the sign and not by means of a sign of identity. Difference of the objects by difference of the signs.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Identity of object I express by identity of sign, and not by using a sign for identity. Difference of objects I express by difference of signs.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.5301" depth="4">
      <german>Dass die Identität keine Relation zwischen Gegenständen ist, leuchtet ein. Dies wird sehr klar, wenn man z. B. den Satz „ ( x ): fx . ⊃ . x = a “ betrachtet. Was dieser Satz sagt, ist einfach, dass nur a der Funktion f genügt, und nicht, dass nur solche Dinge der Funktion f genügen, welche eine gewisse Beziehung zu a haben.</german>
      <ogden>That identity is not a relation between objects is obvious. This becomes very clear if, for example, one considers the proposition “ ( x ): fx . ⊃ . x = a ”. What this proposition says is simply that only a satisfies the function f , and not that only such things satisfy the function f which have a certain relation to a .</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>It is self-evident that identity is not a relation between objects. This becomes very clear if one considers, for example, the proposition ‘ ( x ): fx . ⊃ . x = a ’. What this proposition says is simply that only a satisfies the function f , and not that only things that have a certain relation to a satisfy the function f .</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.5302" depth="4">
      <german>Russells Definition von „=“ genügt nicht; weil man nach ihr nicht sagen kann, dass zwei Gegenstände alle Eigenschaften gemeinsam haben. (Selbst wenn dieser Satz nie richtig ist, hat er doch Sinn .)</german>
      <ogden>Russell’s definition of “=” won’t do; because according to it one cannot say that two objects have all their properties in common. (Even if this proposition is never true, it is nevertheless significant .)</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Russell’s definition of ‘=’ is inadequate, because according to it we cannot say that two objects have all their properties in common. (Even if this proposition is never correct, it still has sense .)</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.5303" depth="4">
      <german>Beiläufig gesprochen: Von zwei Dingen zu sagen, sie seien identisch, ist ein Unsinn, und von Einem zu sagen, es sei identisch mit sich selbst, sagt gar nichts.</german>
      <ogden>Roughly speaking: to say of two things that they are identical is nonsense, and to say of one thing that it is identical with itself is to say nothing.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Roughly speaking, to say of two things that they are identical is nonsense, and to say of one thing that it is identical with itself is to say nothing at all.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.531" depth="3">
      <german>Ich schreibe also nicht „ f ( a , b ) . a = b “, sondern „ f ( a , a ) “ (oder „ f ( b , b ) “). Und nicht „ f ( a , b ) . ~ a = b “, sondern „ f ( a , b ) “.</german>
      <ogden>I write therefore not “ f ( a , b ) . a = b ” but “ f ( a , a ) ” (or “ f ( b , b ) ”). And not “ f ( a , b ) . ~ a = b ”, but “ f ( a , b ) ”.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Thus I do not write ‘ f ( a , b ) . a = b ’, but ‘ f ( a , a ) ’ (or ‘ f ( b , b ) ’); and not ‘ f ( a , b ) . ~ a = b ’, but ‘ f ( a , b ) ’.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.532" depth="3">
      <german>Und analog: Nicht „ ( ∃ x , y ). f ( x , y ) . x = y “, sondern „ ( ∃ x ). f ( x , x ) “; und nicht „ ( ∃ x , y ). f ( x , y ) . ~ x = y “, sondern „ ( ∃ x , y ). f ( x , y ) “.</german>
      <ogden>And analogously: not “ ( ∃ x , y ). f ( x , y ) . x = y ”, but “ ( ∃ x ). f ( x , x ) ”; and not “ ( ∃ x , y ). f ( x , y ) . ~ x = y ”, but “ ( ∃ x , y ). f ( x , y ) ”.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>And analogously I do not write ‘ ( ∃ x , y ). f ( x , y ) . x = y ’, but ‘ ( ∃ x ). f ( x , x ) ’; and not ‘ ( ∃ x , y ). f ( x , y ) . ~ x = y ’, but ‘ ( ∃ x , y ). f ( x , y ) ’.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.5321" depth="4">
      <german>Statt „ ( x ): fx ⊃ x = a “ schreiben wir also z. B. „ ( ∃ x ). fx . ⊃ . fa : ~ ( ∃ x , y ). fx . fy “.</german>
      <ogden>Instead of “ ( x ): fx ⊃ x = a ” we therefore write e.g. “ ( ∃ x ). fx . ⊃ . fa : ~ ( ∃ x , y ). fx . fy ”.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Thus, for example, instead of ‘ ( x ): fx ⊃ x = a ’ we write ‘ ( ∃ x ). fx . ⊃ . fa : ~ ( ∃ x , y ). fx . fy ’.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.533" depth="3">
      <german>Das Gleichheitszeichen ist also kein wesentlicher Bestandteil der Begriffsschrift.</german>
      <ogden>The identity sign is therefore not an essential constituent of logical notation.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The identity-sign, therefore, is not an essential constituent of conceptual notation.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.534" depth="3">
      <german>Und nun sehen wir, dass Scheinsätze wie: „ a = a “, „ a = b . b = c . ⊃ a = c “, „ ( x ). x = x “, „ ( ∃ x ). x = a “, etc. sich in einer richtigen Begriffsschrift gar nicht hinschreiben lassen.</german>
      <ogden>And we see that the apparent propositions like: “ a = a ”, “ a = b . b = c . ⊃ a = c ”, “ ( x ). x = x ”. “ ( ∃ x ). x = a ”, etc. cannot be written in a correct logical notation at all.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>And now we see that in a correct conceptual notation pseudo-propositions like ‘ a = a ’, ‘ a = b . b = c . ⊃ a = c ’, ‘ ( x ). x = x ’, ‘ ( ∃ x ). x = a ’, etc. cannot even be written down.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.535" depth="3">
      <german>Damit erledigen sich auch alle Probleme, die an solche Scheinsätze geknüpft waren.</german>
      <ogden>So all problems disappear which are connected with such pseudo-propositions.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>This also disposes of all the problems that were connected with such pseudo-propositions.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.5351" depth="4">
      <german>Es gibt gewisse Fälle, wo man in Versuchung gerät, Ausdrücke von der Form „ a = a “ oder „ p ⊃ p “ u. dgl. zu benützen. Und zwar geschieht dies, wenn man von dem Urbild: Satz, Ding, etc. reden möchte. So hat Russell in den „Principles of Mathematics“ den Unsinn „ p ist ein Satz“ in Symbolen durch „ p ⊃ p “ wiedergegeben und als Hypothese vor gewisse Sätze gestellt, damit deren Argumentstellen nur von Sätzen besetzt werden könnten.</german>
      <ogden>There are certain cases in which one is tempted to use expressions of the form “ a = a ” or “ p ⊃ p ”. As, for instance, when one would speak of the archetype Proposition, Thing, etc. So Russell in the Principles of Mathematics has rendered the nonsense “ p is a proposition” in symbols by “ p ⊃ p ” and has put it as hypothesis before certain propositions to show that their places for arguments could only be occupied by propositions.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>There are certain cases in which one is tempted to use expressions of the form ‘ a = a ’ or ‘ p ⊃ p ’ and the like. In fact, this happens when one wants to talk about prototypes, e.g. about proposition, thing, etc. Thus in Russell’s Principles of Mathematics ‘ p is a proposition’—which is nonsense—was given the symbolic rendering ‘ p ⊃ p ’ and placed as an hypothesis in front of certain propositions in order to exclude from their argument-places everything but propositions.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.5352" depth="4">
      <german>Ebenso wollte man „Es gibt keine Dinge “ ausdrücken durch „ ~ ( ∃ x ). x = x “. Aber selbst wenn dies ein Satz wäre – wäre er nicht auch wahr, wenn es zwar „Dinge gäbe“, aber diese nicht mit sich selbst identisch wären?</german>
      <ogden>Similarly it was proposed to express “There are no things” by “ ~ ( ∃ x ). x = x ”. But even if this were a proposition—would it not be true if indeed “There were things”, but these were not identical with themselves?</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>In the same way people have wanted to express, ‘There are no things ’, by writing ‘ ~ ( ∃ x ). x = x ’. But even if this were a proposition, would it not be equally true if in fact ‘there were things’ but they were not identical with themselves?</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.54" depth="2">
      <german>In der allgemeinen Satzform kommt der Satz im Satze nur als Basis der Wahrheitsoperationen vor.</german>
      <ogden>In the general propositional form, propositions occur in a proposition only as bases of the truth-operations.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>In the general propositional form propositions occur in other propositions only as bases of truth-operations.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.541" depth="3">
      <german>Auf den ersten Blick scheint es, als könne ein Satz in einem anderen auch auf andere Weise vorkommen.</german>
      <ogden>At first sight it appears as if there were also a different way in which one proposition could occur in another.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>At first sight it looks as if it were also possible for one proposition to occur in another in a different way.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.542" depth="3">
      <german>Es ist aber klar, dass „A glaubt, dass p “, „A denkt p “, „A sagt p “ von der Form „‚ p ‘ sagt p “ sind: Und hier handelt es sich nicht um eine Zuordnung von einer Tatsache und einem Gegenstand, sondern um die Zuordnung von Tatsachen durch Zuordnung ihrer Gegenstände.</german>
      <ogden>But it is clear that “A believes that p ”, “A thinks p ”, “A says p ”, are of the form “‘ p ’ says p ”: and here we have no co-ordination of a fact and an object, but a co-ordination of facts by means of a co-ordination of their objects.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>It is clear, however, that ‘ A believes that p ’, ‘ A has the thought p ’, and ‘ A says p ’ are of the form ‘“ p ” says p ’: and this does not involve a correlation of a fact with an object, but rather the correlation of facts by means of the correlation of their objects.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.5421" depth="4">
      <german>Dies zeigt auch, dass die Seele – das Subjekt etc. – wie sie in der heutigen oberflächlichen Psychologie aufgefasst wird, ein Unding ist.</german>
      <ogden>This shows that there is no such thing as the soul—the subject, etc.—as it is conceived in superficial psychology.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>This shows too that there is no such thing as the soul—the subject, etc.—as it is conceived in the superficial psychology of the present day.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.5422" depth="4">
      <german>Die richtige Erklärung der Form des Satzes „A urteilt p “ muss zeigen, dass es unmöglich ist, einen Unsinn zu urteilen. (Russells Theorie genügt dieser Bedingung nicht.)</german>
      <ogden>The correct explanation of the form of the proposition “A judges p ” must show that it is impossible to judge a nonsense. (Russell’s theory does not satisfy this condition.)</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The correct explanation of the form of the proposition, ‘ A makes the judgement p ’, must show that it is impossible for a judgement to be a piece of nonsense. (Russell’s theory does not satisfy this requirement.)</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.5423" depth="4">
      <german>Einen Komplex wahrnehmen heißt wahrnehmen, dass sich seine Bestandteile so und so zu einander verhalten.</german>
      <ogden>To perceive a complex means to perceive that its constituents are combined in such and such a way.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>To perceive a complex means to perceive that its constituents are related to one another in such and such a way.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.55" depth="2">
      <german>Wir müssen nun die Frage nach allen möglichen Formen der Elementarsätze a priori beantworten.</german>
      <ogden>We must now answer a priori the question as to all possible forms of the elementary propositions.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>We now have to answer a priori the question about all the possible forms of elementary propositions.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.551" depth="3">
      <german>Unser Grundsatz ist, dass jede Frage, die sich überhaupt durch die Logik entscheiden lässt, sich ohne weiteres entscheiden lassen muss.</german>
      <ogden>Our fundamental principle is that every question which can be decided at all by logic can be decided off-hand.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Our fundamental principle is that whenever a question can be decided by logic at all it must be possible to decide it without more ado.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.552" depth="3">
      <german>Die „Erfahrung“, die wir zum Verstehen der Logik brauchen, ist nicht die, dass sich etwas so und so verhält, sondern, dass etwas ist : aber das ist eben keine Erfahrung.</german>
      <ogden>The “experience” which we need to understand logic is not that such and such is the case, but that something is ; but that is no experience.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The ‘experience’ that we need in order to understand logic is not that something or other is the state of things, but that something is : that, however, is not an experience.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.5521" depth="4">
      <german>Und wenn dies nicht so wäre, wie könnten wir die Logik anwenden? Man könnte sagen: Wenn es eine Logik gäbe, auch wenn es keine Welt gäbe, wie könnte es dann eine Logik geben, da es eine Welt gibt.</german>
      <ogden>And if this were not the case, how could we apply logic? We could say: if there were a logic, even if there were no world, how then could there be a logic, since there is a world?</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>And if this were not so, how could we apply logic? We might put it in this way: if there would be a logic even if there were no world, how then could there be a logic given that there is a world?</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.553" depth="3">
      <german>Russell sagte, es gäbe einfache Relationen zwischen verschiedenen Anzahlen von Dingen (Individuals). Aber zwischen welchen Anzahlen? Und wie soll sich das entscheiden? – Durch die Erfahrung?</german>
      <ogden>Russell said that there were simple relations between different numbers of things (individuals). But between what numbers? And how should this be decided—by experience?</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Russell said that there were simple relations between different numbers of things (individuals). But between what numbers? And how is this supposed to be decided?—By experience?</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.554" depth="3">
      <german>Die Angabe jeder speziellen Form wäre vollkommen willkürlich.</german>
      <ogden>The enumeration of any special forms would be entirely arbitrary.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>It would be completely arbitrary to give any specific form.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.5541" depth="4">
      <german>Es soll sich a priori angeben lassen, ob ich z. B. in die Lage kommen kann, etwas mit dem Zeichen einer 27-stelligen Relation bezeichnen zu müssen.</german>
      <ogden>How could we decide a priori whether, for example, I can get into a situation in which I need to symbolize with a sign of a 27-termed relation?</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>It is supposed to be possible to answer a priori the question whether I can get into a position in which I need the sign for a 27-termed relation in order to signify something.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.5542" depth="4">
      <german>Dürfen wir denn aber überhaupt so fragen? Können wir eine Zeichenform aufstellen und nicht wissen, ob ihr etwas entsprechen könne?</german>
      <ogden>May we then ask this at all? Can we set out a sign form and not know whether anything can correspond to it?</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>But is it really legitimate even to ask such a question? Can we set up a form of sign without knowing whether anything can correspond to it?</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.555" depth="3">
      <german>Es ist klar, wir haben vom Elementarsatz einen Begriff, abgesehen von seiner besonderen logischen Form.</german>
      <ogden>It is clear that we have a concept of the elementary proposition apart from its special logical form.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Clearly we have some concept of elementary propositions quite apart from their particular logical forms.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.556" depth="3">
      <german>Eine Hierarchie der Formen der Elementarsätze kann es nicht geben. Nur was wir selbst konstruieren, können wir voraussehen.</german>
      <ogden>There cannot be a hierarchy of the forms of the elementary propositions. Only that which we ourselves construct can we foresee.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>There cannot be a hierarchy of the forms of elementary propositions. We can foresee only what we ourselves construct.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.5561" depth="4">
      <german>Die empirische Realität ist begrenzt durch die Gesamtheit der Gegenstände. Die Grenze zeigt sich wieder in der Gesamtheit der Elementarsätze.</german>
      <ogden>Empirical reality is limited by the totality of objects. The boundary appears again in the totality of elementary propositions.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Empirical reality is limited by the totality of objects. The limit also makes itself manifest in the totality of elementary propositions.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.5562" depth="4">
      <german>Wissen wir aus rein logischen Gründen, dass es Elementarsätze geben muss, dann muss es jeder wissen, der die Sätze in ihrer unanalysierten Form versteht.</german>
      <ogden>If we know on purely logical grounds, that there must be elementary propositions, then this must be known by everyone who understands propositions in their unanalysed form.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>If we know on purely logical grounds that there must be elementary propositions, then everyone who understands propositions in their unanalyzed form must know it.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.5563" depth="4">
      <german>Alle Sätze unserer Umgangssprache sind tatsächlich, so wie sie sind, logisch vollkommen geordnet. – Jenes Einfachste, was wir hier angeben sollen, ist nicht ein Gleichnis der Wahrheit, sondern die volle Wahrheit selbst.</german>
      <ogden>All propositions of our colloquial language are actually, just as they are, logically completely in order. That simple thing which we ought to give here is not a model of the truth but the complete truth itself.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>In fact, all the propositions of our everyday language, just as they stand, are in perfect logical order.—That utterly simple thing, which we have to formulate here, is not a likeness of the truth, but the truth itself in its entirety.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.557" depth="3">
      <german>Die Anwendung der Logik entscheidet darüber, welche Elementarsätze es gibt.</german>
      <ogden>The application of logic decides what elementary propositions there are.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The application of logic decides what elementary propositions there are.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.5571" depth="4">
      <german>Wenn ich die Elementarsätze nicht a priori angeben kann, dann muss es zu offenbarem Unsinn führen, sie angeben zu wollen.</german>
      <ogden>If I cannot give elementary propositions a priori then it must lead to obvious nonsense to try to give them.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>If I cannot say a priori what elementary propositions there are, then the attempt to do so must lead to obvious nonsense.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.6" depth="1">
      <german>Die Grenzen meiner Sprache bedeuten die Grenzen meiner Welt.</german>
      <ogden>The limits of my language mean the limits of my world.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The limits of my language mean the limits of my world.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.61" depth="2">
      <german>Die Logik erfüllt die Welt; die Grenzen der Welt sind auch ihre Grenzen.</german>
      <ogden>Logic fills the world: the limits of the world are also its limits.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Logic pervades the world: the limits of the world are also its limits.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.62" depth="2">
      <german>Diese Bemerkung gibt den Schlüssel zur Entscheidung der Frage, inwieweit der Solipsismus eine Wahrheit ist.</german>
      <ogden>This remark provides a key to the question, to what extent solipsism is a truth.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>This remark provides the key to the problem, how much truth there is in solipsism.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.621" depth="3">
      <german>Die Welt und das Leben sind Eins.</german>
      <ogden>The world and life are one.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The world and life are one.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.63" depth="2">
      <german>Ich bin meine Welt. (Der Mikrokosmos.)</german>
      <ogden>I am my world. (The microcosm.)</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>I am my world. (The microcosm.)</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.631" depth="3">
      <german>Das denkende, vorstellende, Subjekt gibt es nicht.</german>
      <ogden>The thinking, presenting subject; there is no such thing.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>There is no such thing as the subject that thinks or entertains ideas.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.632" depth="3">
      <german>Das Subjekt gehört nicht zur Welt, sondern es ist eine Grenze der Welt.</german>
      <ogden>The subject does not belong to the world but it is a limit of the world.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The subject does not belong to the world: rather, it is a limit of the world.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.633" depth="3">
      <german>Wo in der Welt ist ein metaphysisches Subjekt zu merken?</german>
      <ogden>Where in the world is a metaphysical subject to be noted?</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Where in the world is a metaphysical subject to be found?</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.6331" depth="4">
      <german>Das Gesichtsfeld hat nämlich nicht etwa eine solche Form:</german>
      <ogden>For the field of sight has not a form like this:</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>For the form of the visual field is surely not like this</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.634" depth="3">
      <german>Das hängt damit zusammen, dass kein Teil unserer Erfahrung auch a priori ist.</german>
      <ogden>This is connected with the fact that no part of our experience is also a priori.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>This is connected with the fact that no part of our experience is at the same time a priori .</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.64" depth="2">
      <german>Hier sieht man, dass der Solipsismus, streng durchgeführt, mit dem reinen Realismus zusammenfällt. Das Ich des Solipsismus schrumpft zum ausdehnungslosen Punkt zusammen, und es bleibt die ihm koordinierte Realität.</german>
      <ogden>Here we see that solipsism strictly carried out coincides with pure realism. The I in solipsism shrinks to an extensionless point and there remains the reality co-ordinated with it.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Here it can be seen that solipsism, when its implications are followed out strictly, coincides with pure realism. The self of solipsism shrinks to a point without extension, and there remains the reality co-ordinated with it.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="5.641" depth="3">
      <german>Es gibt also wirklich einen Sinn, in welchem in der Philosophie nichtpsychologisch vom Ich die Rede sein kann.</german>
      <ogden>There is therefore really a sense in which in philosophy we can talk of a non-psychological I.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Thus there really is a sense in which philosophy can talk about the self in a non-psychological way.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
  </proposition>
  <proposition id="6" depth="0">
    <german>Die allgemeine Form der Wahrheitsfunktion ist: [ p , ξ , N ( ξ )] .</german>
    <ogden>The general form of truth-function is: [ p , ξ , N ( ξ )] .</ogden>
    <pears_mcguinness>The general form of a truth-function is [ p , ξ , N ( ξ )] .</pears_mcguinness>
    <proposition id="6.001" depth="3">
      <german>Dies sagt nichts anderes, als dass jeder Satz ein Resultat der successiven Anwendung der Operation N ’ ( ξ ) auf die Elementarsätze ist.</german>
      <ogden>This says nothing else than that every proposition is the result of successive applications of the operation N ’ ( ξ ) to the elementary propositions.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>What this says is just that every proposition is a result of successive applications to elementary propositions of the operation N ( ξ ) .</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.002" depth="3">
      <german>Ist die allgemeine Form gegeben, wie ein Satz gebaut ist, so ist damit auch schon die allgemeine Form davon gegeben, wie aus einem Satz durch eine Operation ein anderer erzeugt werden kann.</german>
      <ogden>If we are given the general form of the way in which a proposition is constructed, then thereby we are also given the general form of the way in which by an operation out of one proposition another can be created.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>If we are given the general form according to which propositions are constructed, then with it we are also given the general form according to which one proposition can be generated out of another by means of an operation.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.01" depth="2">
      <german>Die allgemeine Form der Operation Ω’ ( η ) ist also: [ ξ , N ( ξ )]’ ( η ) ( = [ η , ξ , N ( ξ )]) .</german>
      <ogden>The general form of the operation Ω’ ( η ) is therefore: [ ξ , N ( ξ )]’ ( η ) ( = [ η , ξ , N ( ξ )]) .</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Therefore the general form of an operation Ω’ ( η ) is [ ξ , N ( ξ )]’ ( η ) ( = [ η , ξ , N ( ξ )]) .</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.02" depth="2">
      <german>Und so kommen wir zu den Zahlen: Ich definiere</german>
      <ogden>And thus we come to numbers: I define</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>And this is how we arrive at numbers. I give the following definitions</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.021" depth="3">
      <german>Die Zahl ist der Exponent einer Operation.</german>
      <ogden>A number is the exponent of an operation.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>A number is the exponent of an operation.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.022" depth="3">
      <german>Der Zahlbegriff ist nichts anderes als das Gemeinsame aller Zahlen, die allgemeine Form der Zahl.</german>
      <ogden>The concept number is nothing else than that which is common to all numbers, the general form of a number.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The concept of number is simply what is common to all numbers, the general form of a number.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.03" depth="2">
      <german>Die allgemeine Form der ganzen Zahl ist: [0, ξ , ξ + 1] .</german>
      <ogden>The general form of the cardinal number is: [0, ξ , ξ + 1] .</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The general form of an integer is [0, ξ , ξ + 1] .</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.031" depth="3">
      <german>Die Theorie der Klassen ist in der Mathematik ganz überflüssig.</german>
      <ogden>The theory of classes is altogether superfluous in mathematics.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The theory of classes is completely superfluous in mathematics.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.1" depth="1">
      <german>Die Sätze der Logik sind Tautologien.</german>
      <ogden>The propositions of logic are tautologies.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The propositions of logic are tautologies.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.11" depth="2">
      <german>Die Sätze der Logik sagen also Nichts. (Sie sind die analytischen Sätze.)</german>
      <ogden>The propositions of logic therefore say nothing. (They are the analytical propositions.)</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Therefore the propositions of logic say nothing. (They are the analytic propositions.)</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.111" depth="3">
      <german>Theorien, die einen Satz der Logik gehaltvoll erscheinen lassen, sind immer falsch. Man könnte z. B. glauben, dass die Worte „wahr“ und „falsch“ zwei Eigenschaften unter anderen Eigenschaften bezeichnen, und da erschiene es als eine merkwürdige Tatsache, dass jeder Satz eine dieser Eigenschaften besitzt. Das scheint nun nichts weniger als selbstverständlich zu sein, ebensowenig selbstverständlich, wie etwa der Satz, „alle Rosen sind entweder gelb oder rot“ klänge, auch wenn er wahr wäre. Ja, jener Satz bekommt nun ganz den Charakter eines naturwissenschaftlichen Satzes, und dies ist das sichere Anzeichen dafür, dass er falsch aufgefasst wurde.</german>
      <ogden>Theories which make a proposition of logic appear substantial are always false. One could e.g. believe that the words “true” and “false” signify two properties among other properties, and then it would appear as a remarkable fact that every proposition possesses one of these properties. This now by no means appears self-evident, no more so than the proposition “All roses are either yellow or red” would seem even if it were true. Indeed our proposition now gets quite the character of a proposition of natural science and this is a certain symptom of its being falsely understood.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>All theories that make a proposition of logic appear to have content are false. One might think, for example, that the words ‘true’ and ‘false’ signified two properties among other properties, and then it would seem to be a remarkable fact that every proposition possessed one of these properties. On this theory it seems to be anything but obvious, just as, for instance, the proposition, ‘All roses are either yellow or red’, would not sound obvious even if it were true. Indeed, the logical proposition acquires all the characteristics of a proposition of natural science and this is the sure sign that it has been construed wrongly.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.112" depth="3">
      <german>Die richtige Erklärung der logischen Sätze muss ihnen eine einzigartige Stellung unter allen Sätzen geben.</german>
      <ogden>The correct explanation of logical propositions must give them a peculiar position among all propositions.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The correct explanation of the propositions of logic must assign to them a unique status among all propositions.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.113" depth="3">
      <german>Es ist das besondere Merkmal der logischen Sätze, dass man am Symbol allein erkennen kann, dass sie wahr sind, und diese Tatsache schließt die ganze Philosophie der Logik in sich. Und so ist es auch eine der wichtigsten Tatsachen, dass sich die Wahrheit oder Falschheit der nichtlogischen Sätze nicht am Satz allein erkennen lässt.</german>
      <ogden>It is the characteristic mark of logical propositions that one can perceive in the symbol alone that they are true; and this fact contains in itself the whole philosophy of logic. And so also it is one of the most important facts that the truth or falsehood of non-logical propositions can not be recognized from the propositions alone.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>It is the peculiar mark of logical propositions that one can recognize that they are true from the symbol alone, and this fact contains in itself the whole philosophy of logic. And so too it is a very important fact that the truth or falsity of non-logical propositions cannot be recognized from the propositions alone.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.12" depth="2">
      <german>Dass die Sätze der Logik Tautologien sind, das zeigt die formalen – logischen – Eigenschaften der Sprache, der Welt.</german>
      <ogden>The fact that the propositions of logic are tautologies shows the formal—logical—properties of language, of the world.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The fact that the propositions of logic are tautologies shows the formal—logical—properties of language and the world.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.1201" depth="4">
      <german>Dass z. B. die Sätze „ p “ und „ ~ p “ in der Verbindung „ ~ ( p . ~ p ) “ eine Tautologie ergeben, zeigt, dass sie einander widersprechen. Dass die Sätze „ p ⊃ q “, „ p “ und „ q “ in der Form „ ( p ⊃ q ) . ( p ) : ⊃ : ( q ) “ miteinander verbunden eine Tautologie ergeben, zeigt, dass q aus p und p ⊃ q folgt. Dass „ ( x ). fx : ⊃ : fa “ eine Tautologie ist, dass fa aus ( x ). fx folgt. etc. etc.</german>
      <ogden>That e.g. the propositions “ p ” and “ ~ p ” in the connexion “ ~ ( p . ~ p ) ” give a tautology shows that they contradict one another. That the propositions “ p ⊃ q ”, “ p ” and “ q ” connected together in the form “ ( p ⊃ q ) . ( p ) : ⊃ : ( q ) ” give a tautology shows that q follows from p and p ⊃ q . That “ ( x ). fx : ⊃ : fa ” is a tautology shows that fa follows from ( x ). fx , etc. etc.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>For example, the fact that the propositions ‘ p ’ and ‘ ~ p ’ in the combination ‘ ~ ( p . ~ p ) ’ yield a tautology shows that they contradict one another. The fact that the propositions ‘ p ⊃ q ’, ‘ p ’, and ‘ q ’, combined with one another in the form ‘ ( p ⊃ q ) . ( p ) : ⊃ : ( q ) ’, yield a tautology shows that q follows from p and p ⊃ q . The fact that ‘ ( x ). fx : ⊃ : fa ’ is a tautology shows that fa follows from ( x ). fx . Etc. etc.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.1202" depth="4">
      <german>Es ist klar, dass man zu demselben Zweck statt der Tautologien auch die Kontradiktionen verwenden könnte.</german>
      <ogden>It is clear that we could have used for this purpose contradictions instead of tautologies.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>It is clear that one could achieve the same purpose by using contradictions instead of tautologies.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.1203" depth="4">
      <german>Um eine Tautologie als solche zu erkennen, kann man sich, in den Fällen, in welchen in der Tautologie keine Allgemeinheitsbezeichnung vorkommt, folgender anschaulichen Methode bedienen: Ich schreibe statt „ p “, „ q “, „ r “ etc. „ W p F “, „ W q F “, „ W r F “ etc. Die Wahrheitskombinationen drücke ich durch Klammern aus, z. B.:</german>
      <ogden>In order to recognize a tautology as such, we can, in cases in which no sign of generality occurs in the tautology, make use of the following intuitive method: I write instead of “ p ”, “ q ”, “ r ”, etc., “ T p F ”, “ T q F ”, “ T r F ”, etc. The truth-combinations I express by brackets, e.g. :</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>In order to recognize an expression as a tautology, in cases where no generality-sign occurs in it, one can employ the following intuitive method: instead of ‘ p ’, ‘ q ’, ‘ r ’, etc. I write ‘ T p F ’, ‘ T q F ’, ‘ T r F ’, etc. Truth-combinations I express by means of brackets, e.g.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.121" depth="3">
      <german>Die Sätze der Logik demonstrieren die logischen Eigenschaften der Sätze, indem sie sie zu nichtssagenden Sätzen verbinden.</german>
      <ogden>The propositions of logic demonstrate the logical properties of propositions, by combining them into propositions which say nothing.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The propositions of logic demonstrate the logical properties of propositions by combining them so as to form propositions that say nothing.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.122" depth="3">
      <german>Daraus ergibt sich, dass wir auch ohne die logischen Sätze auskommen können, da wir ja in einer entsprechenden Notation die formalen Eigenschaften der Sätze durch das bloße Ansehen dieser Sätze erkennen können.</german>
      <ogden>Whence it follows that we can get on without logical propositions, for we can recognize in an adequate notation the formal properties of the propositions by mere inspection.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>It follows from this that we can actually do without logical propositions; for in a suitable notation we can in fact recognize the formal properties of propositions by mere inspection of the propositions themselves.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.1221" depth="4">
      <german>Ergeben z. B. zwei Sätze „ p “ und „ q “ in der Verbindung „ p ⊃ q “ eine Tautologie, so ist klar, dass q aus p folgt.</german>
      <ogden>If for example two propositions “ p ” and “ q ” give a tautology in the connexion “ p ⊃ q ”, then it is clear that q follows from p .</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>If, for example, two propositions ‘ p ’ and ‘ q ’ in the combination ‘ p ⊃ q ’ yield a tautology, then it is clear that q follows from p .</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.1222" depth="4">
      <german>Dies wirft ein Licht auf die Frage, warum die logischen Sätze nicht durch die Erfahrung bestätigt werden können, ebenso wenig, wie sie durch die Erfahrung widerlegt werden können. Nicht nur muss ein Satz der Logik durch keine mögliche Erfahrung widerlegt werden können, sondern er darf auch nicht durch eine solche bestätigt werden können.</german>
      <ogden>This throws light on the question why logical propositions can no more be empirically confirmed than they can be empirically refuted. Not only must a proposition of logic be incapable of being contradicted by any possible experience, but it must also be incapable of being confirmed by any such.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>This throws some light on the question why logical propositions cannot be confirmed by experience any more than they can be refuted by it. Not only must a proposition of logic be irrefutable by any possible experience, but it must also be unconfirmable by any possible experience.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.1223" depth="4">
      <german>Nun wird klar, warum man oft fühlte, als wären die „logischen Wahrheiten“ von uns zu „ fordern “: Wir können sie nämlich insofern fordern, als wir eine genügende Notation fordern können.</german>
      <ogden>It now becomes clear why we often feel as though “logical truths” must be “ postulated ” by us. We can in fact postulate them in so far as we can postulate an adequate notation.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Now it becomes clear why people have often felt as if it were for us to ‘ postulate ’ the ‘truths of logic’. The reason is that we can postulate them in so far as we can postulate an adequate notation.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.1224" depth="4">
      <german>Es wird jetzt auch klar, warum die Logik die Lehre von den Formen und vom Schließen genannt wurde.</german>
      <ogden>It also becomes clear why logic has been called the theory of forms and of inference.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>It also becomes clear now why logic was called the theory of forms and of inference.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.123" depth="3">
      <german>Es ist klar: Die logischen Gesetze dürfen nicht selbst wieder logischen Gesetzen unterstehen.</german>
      <ogden>It is clear that the laws of logic cannot themselves obey further logical laws.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Clearly the laws of logic cannot in their turn be subject to laws of logic.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.1231" depth="4">
      <german>Das Anzeichen des logischen Satzes ist nicht die Allgemeingültigkeit.</german>
      <ogden>The mark of logical propositions is not their general validity.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The mark of a logical proposition is not general validity.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.1232" depth="4">
      <german>Die logische Allgemeingültigkeit könnte man wesentlich nennen, im Gegensatz zu jener zufälligen, etwa des Satzes: „alle Menschen sind sterblich“. Sätze wie Russells „Axiom of reducibility“ sind nicht logische Sätze, und dies erklärt unser Gefühl: Dass sie, wenn wahr, so doch nur durch einen günstigen Zufall wahr sein könnten.</german>
      <ogden>Logical general validity, we could call essential as opposed to accidental general validity, e.g. of the proposition “all men are mortal”. Propositions like Russell’s “axiom of reducibility” are not logical propositions, and this explains our feeling that, if true, they can only be true by a happy chance.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The general validity of logic might be called essential, in contrast with the accidental general validity of such propositions as ‘All men are mortal’. Propositions like Russell’s ‘axiom of reducibility’ are not logical propositions, and this explains our feeling that, even if they were true, their truth could only be the result of a fortunate accident.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.1233" depth="4">
      <german>Es lässt sich eine Welt denken, in der das Axiom of reducibility nicht gilt. Es ist aber klar, dass die Logik nichts mit der Frage zu schaffen hat, ob unsere Welt wirklich so ist oder nicht.</german>
      <ogden>We can imagine a world in which the axiom of reducibility is not valid. But it is clear that logic has nothing to do with the question whether our world is really of this kind or not.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>It is possible to imagine a world in which the axiom of reducibility is not valid. It is clear, however, that logic has nothing to do with the question whether our world really is like that or not.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.124" depth="3">
      <german>Die logischen Sätze beschreiben das Gerüst der Welt, oder vielmehr, sie stellen es dar. Sie „handeln“ von nichts. Sie setzen voraus, dass Namen Bedeutung, und Elementarsätze Sinn haben: Und dies ist ihre Verbindung mit der Welt. Es ist klar, dass es etwas über die Welt anzeigen muss, dass gewisse Verbindungen von Symbolen – welche wesentlich einen bestimmten Charakter haben – Tautologien sind. Hierin liegt das Entscheidende. Wir sagten, manches an den Symbolen, die wir gebrauchen, wäre willkürlich, manches nicht. In der Logik drückt nur dieses aus: Das heißt aber, in der Logik drücken nicht wir mit Hilfe der Zeichen aus, was wir wollen, sondern in der Logik sagt die Natur der naturnotwendigen Zeichen selbst aus: Wenn wir die logische Syntax irgendeiner Zeichensprache kennen, dann sind bereits alle Sätze der Logik gegeben.</german>
      <ogden>The logical propositions describe the scaffolding of the world, or rather they present it. They “treat” of nothing. They presuppose that names have meaning, and that elementary propositions have sense. And this is their connexion with the world. It is clear that it must show something about the world that certain combinations of symbols—which essentially have a definite character—are tautologies. Herein lies the decisive point. We said that in the symbols which we use something is arbitrary, something not. In logic only this expresses: but this means that in logic it is not we who express, by means of signs, what we want, but in logic the nature of the essentially necessary signs itself asserts. That is to say, if we know the logical syntax of any sign language, then all the propositions of logic are already given.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The propositions of logic describe the scaffolding of the world, or rather they represent it. They have no ‘subject-matter’. They presuppose that names have meaning and elementary propositions sense; and that is their connexion with the world. It is clear that something about the world must be indicated by the fact that certain combinations of symbols—whose essence involves the possession of a determinate character—are tautologies. This contains the decisive point. We have said that some things are arbitrary in the symbols that we use and that some things are not. In logic it is only the latter that express: but that means that logic is not a field in which we express what we wish with the help of signs, but rather one in which the nature of the natural and inevitable signs speaks for itself. If we know the logical syntax of any sign-language, then we have already been given all the propositions of logic.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.125" depth="3">
      <german>Es ist möglich, und zwar auch nach der alten Auffassung der Logik, von vornherein eine Beschreibung aller „wahren“ logischen Sätze zu geben.</german>
      <ogden>It is possible, also with the old conception of logic, to give at the outset a description of all “true” logical propositions.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>It is possible—indeed possible even according to the old conception of logic—to give in advance a description of all ‘true’ logical propositions.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.1251" depth="4">
      <german>Darum kann es in der Logik auch nie Überraschungen geben.</german>
      <ogden>Hence there can never be surprises in logic.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Hence there can never be surprises in logic.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.126" depth="3">
      <german>Ob ein Satz der Logik angehört, kann man berechnen, indem man die logischen Eigenschaften des Symbols berechnet.</german>
      <ogden>Whether a proposition belongs to logic can be calculated by calculating the logical properties of the symbol .</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>One can calculate whether a proposition belongs to logic, by calculating the logical properties of the symbol .</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.1261" depth="4">
      <german>In der Logik sind Prozess und Resultat äquivalent. (Darum keine Überraschung.)</german>
      <ogden>In logic process and result are equivalent. (Therefore no surprises.)</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>In logic process and result are equivalent. (Hence the absence of surprise.)</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.1262" depth="4">
      <german>Der Beweis in der Logik ist nur ein mechanisches Hilfsmittel zum leichteren Erkennen der Tautologie, wo sie kompliziert ist.</german>
      <ogden>Proof in logic is only a mechanical expedient to facilitate the recognition of tautology, where it is complicated.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Proof in logic is merely a mechanical expedient to facilitate the recognition of tautologies in complicated cases.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.1263" depth="4">
      <german>Es wäre ja auch zu merkwürdig, wenn man einen sinnvollen Satz logisch aus anderen beweisen könnte, und einen logischen Satz auch . Es ist von vornherein klar, dass der logische Beweis eines sinnvollen Satzes und der Beweis in der Logik zwei ganz verschiedene Dinge sein müssen.</german>
      <ogden>It would be too remarkable, if one could prove a significant proposition logically from another, and a logical proposition also . It is clear from the beginning that the logical proof of a significant proposition and the proof in logic must be two quite different things.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Indeed, it would be altogether too remarkable if a proposition that had sense could be proved logically from others, and so too could a logical proposition. It is clear from the start that a logical proof of a proposition that has sense and a proof in logic must be two entirely different things.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.1264" depth="4">
      <german>Der sinnvolle Satz sagt etwas aus, und sein Beweis zeigt, dass es so ist; in der Logik ist jeder Satz die Form eines Beweises.</german>
      <ogden>The significant proposition asserts something, and its proof shows that it is so; in logic every proposition is the form of a proof.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>A proposition that has sense states something, which is shown by its proof to be so. In logic every proposition is the form of a proof.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.1265" depth="4">
      <german>Immer kann man die Logik so auffassen, dass jeder Satz sein eigener Beweis ist.</german>
      <ogden>Logic can always be conceived to be such that every proposition is its own proof.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>It is always possible to construe logic in such a way that every proposition is its own proof.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.127" depth="3">
      <german>Alle Sätze der Logik sind gleichberechtigt, es gibt unter ihnen nicht wesentlich Grundgesetze und abgeleitete Sätze.</german>
      <ogden>All propositions of logic are of equal rank; there are not some which are essentially primitive and others deduced from there.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>All the propositions of logic are of equal status: it is not the case that some of them are essentially derived propositions.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.1271" depth="4">
      <german>Es ist klar, dass die Anzahl der „logischen Grundgesetze“ willkürlich ist, denn man könnte die Logik ja aus Einem Grundgesetz ableiten, indem man einfach z. B. aus Freges Grundgesetzen das logische Produkt bildet. (Frege würde vielleicht sagen, dass dieses Grundgesetz nun nicht mehr unmittelbar einleuchte. Aber es ist merkwürdig, dass ein so exakter Denker wie Frege sich auf den Grad des Einleuchtens als Kriterium des logischen Satzes berufen hat.)</german>
      <ogden>It is clear that the number of “primitive propositions of logic” is arbitrary, for we could deduce logic from one primitive proposition by simply forming, for example, the logical produce of Frege’s primitive propositions. (Frege would perhaps say that this would no longer be immediately self-evident. But it is remarkable that so exact a thinker as Frege should have appealed to the degree of self-evidence as the criterion of a logical proposition.)</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>It is clear that the number of the ‘primitive propositions of logic’ is arbitrary, since one could derive logic from a single primitive proposition, e.g. by simply constructing the logical product of Frege’s primitive propositions. (Frege would perhaps say that we should then no longer have an immediately self-evident primitive proposition. But it is remarkable that a thinker as rigorous as Frege appealed to the degree of self-evidence as the criterion of a logical proposition.)</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.13" depth="2">
      <german>Die Logik ist keine Lehre, sondern ein Spiegelbild der Welt.</german>
      <ogden>Logic is not a theory but a reflexion of the world.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Logic is not a body of doctrine, but a mirror-image of the world.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.2" depth="1">
      <german>Die Mathematik ist eine logische Methode.</german>
      <ogden>Mathematics is a logical method.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Mathematics is a logical method.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.21" depth="2">
      <german>Der Satz der Mathematik drückt keinen Gedanken aus.</german>
      <ogden>Mathematical propositions express no thoughts.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>A proposition of mathematics does not express a thought.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.211" depth="3">
      <german>Im Leben ist es ja nie der mathematische Satz, den wir brauchen, sondern wir benützen den mathematischen Satz nur , um aus Sätzen, welche nicht der Mathematik angehören, auf andere zu schließen, welche gleichfalls nicht der Mathematik angehören.</german>
      <ogden>In life it is never a mathematical proposition which we need, but we use mathematical propositions only in order to infer from propositions which do not belong to mathematics to others which equally do not belong to mathematics.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Indeed in real life a mathematical proposition is never what we want. Rather, we make use of mathematical propositions only in inferences from propositions that do not belong to mathematics to others that likewise do not belong to mathematics.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.22" depth="2">
      <german>Die Logik der Welt, die die Sätze der Logik in den Tautologien zeigen, zeigt die Mathematik in den Gleichungen.</german>
      <ogden>The logic of the world which the propositions of logic show in tautologies, mathematics shows in equations.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The logic of the world, which is shown in tautologies by the propositions of logic, is shown in equations by mathematics.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.23" depth="2">
      <german>Wenn zwei Ausdrücke durch das Gleichheitszeichen verbunden werden, so heißt das, sie sind durch einander ersetzbar. Ob dies aber der Fall ist, muss sich an den beiden Ausdrücken selbst zeigen.</german>
      <ogden>If two expressions are connected by the sign of equality, this means that they can be substituted for one another. But whether this is the case must show itself in the two expressions themselves.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>If two expressions are combined by means of the sign of equality, that means that they can be substituted for one another. But it must be manifest in the two expressions themselves whether this is the case or not.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.231" depth="3">
      <german>Es ist eine Eigenschaft der Bejahung, dass man sie als doppelte Verneinung auffassen kann.</german>
      <ogden>It is a property of affirmation that it can be conceived as double denial.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>It is a property of affirmation that it can be construed as double negation.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.232" depth="3">
      <german>Frege sagt, die beiden Ausdrücke haben dieselbe Bedeutung, aber verschiedenen Sinn.</german>
      <ogden>Frege says that these expressions have the same meaning but different senses.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Frege says that the two expressions have the same meaning but different senses.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.2321" depth="4">
      <german>Und, dass die Sätze der Mathematik bewiesen werden können, heißt ja nichts anderes, als dass ihre Richtigkeit einzusehen ist, ohne dass das, was sie ausdrücken, selbst mit den Tatsachen auf seine Richtigkeit hin verglichen werden muss.</german>
      <ogden>And, that the propositions of mathematics can be proved means nothing else than that their correctness can be seen without our having to compare what they express with the facts as regards correctness.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>And the possibility of proving the propositions of mathematics means simply that their correctness can be perceived without its being necessary that what they express should itself be compared with the facts in order to determine its correctness.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.2322" depth="4">
      <german>Die Identität der Bedeutung zweier Ausdrücke lässt sich nicht behaupten . Denn, um etwas von ihrer Bedeutung behaupten zu können, muss ich ihre Bedeutung kennen: und indem ich ihre Bedeutung kenne, weiß ich, ob sie dasselbe oder verschiedenes bedeuten.</german>
      <ogden>The identity of the meaning of two expressions cannot be asserted . For in order to be able to assert anything about their meaning, I must know their meaning, and if I know their meaning, I know whether they mean the same or something different.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>It is impossible to assert the identity of meaning of two expressions. For in order to be able to assert anything about their meaning, I must know their meaning, and I cannot know their meaning without knowing whether what they mean is the same or different.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.2323" depth="4">
      <german>Die Gleichung kennzeichnet nur den Standpunkt, von welchem ich die beiden Ausdrücke betrachte, nämlich vom Standpunkte ihrer Bedeutungsgleichheit.</german>
      <ogden>The equation characterizes only the standpoint from which I consider the two expressions, that is to say the standpoint of their equality of meaning.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>An equation merely marks the point of view from which I consider the two expressions: it marks their equivalence in meaning.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.233" depth="3">
      <german>Die Frage, ob man zur Lösung der mathematischen Probleme die Anschauung brauche, muss dahin beantwortet werden, dass eben die Sprache hier die nötige Anschauung liefert.</german>
      <ogden>To the question whether we need intuition for the solution of mathematical problems it must be answered that language itself here supplies the necessary intuition.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The question whether intuition is needed for the solution of mathematical problems must be given the answer that in this case language itself provides the necessary intuition.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.2331" depth="4">
      <german>Der Vorgang des Rechnens vermittelt eben diese Anschauung.</german>
      <ogden>The process of calculation brings about just this intuition.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The process of calculating serves to bring about that intuition.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.234" depth="3">
      <german>Die Mathematik ist eine Methode der Logik.</german>
      <ogden>Mathematics is a method of logic.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Mathematics is a method of logic.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.2341" depth="4">
      <german>Das Wesentliche der mathematischen Methode ist es, mit Gleichungen zu arbeiten. Auf dieser Methode beruht es nämlich, dass jeder Satz der Mathematik sich von selbst verstehen muss.</german>
      <ogden>The essential of mathematical method is working with equations. On this method depends the fact that every proposition of mathematics must be self-evident.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>It is the essential characteristic of mathematical method that it employs equations. For it is because of this method that every proposition of mathematics must go without saying.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.24" depth="2">
      <german>Die Methode der Mathematik, zu ihren Gleichungen zu kommen, ist die Substitutionsmethode.</german>
      <ogden>The method by which mathematics arrives at its equations is the method of substitution.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The method by which mathematics arrives at its equations is the method of substitution.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.241" depth="3">
      <german>So lautet der Beweis des Satzes 2 × 2 = 4 :</german>
      <ogden>Thus the proof of the proposition 2 × 2 = 4 runs:</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Thus the proof of the proposition 2 × 2 = 4 runs as follows:</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.3" depth="1">
      <german>Die Erforschung der Logik bedeutet die Erforschung aller Gesetzmäßigkeit . Und außerhalb der Logik ist alles Zufall.</german>
      <ogden>Logical research means the investigation of all regularity . And outside logic all is accident.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The exploration of logic means the exploration of everything that is subject to law . And outside logic everything is accidental.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.31" depth="2">
      <german>Das sogenannte Gesetz der Induktion kann jedenfalls kein logisches Gesetz sein, denn es ist offenbar ein sinnvoller Satz. – Und darum kann es auch kein Gesetz a priori sein.</german>
      <ogden>The so-called law of induction cannot in any case be a logical law, for it is obviously a significant proposition.—And therefore it cannot be a law a priori either.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The so-called law of induction cannot possibly be a law of logic, since it is obviously a proposition with sense.—Nor, therefore, can it be an a priori law.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.32" depth="2">
      <german>Das Kausalitätsgesetz ist kein Gesetz, sondern die Form eines Gesetzes.</german>
      <ogden>The law of causality is not a law but the form of a law. †</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The law of causality is not a law but the form of a law.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.321" depth="3">
      <german>„Kausalitätsgesetz“, das ist ein Gattungsname. Und wie es in der Mechanik, sagen wir, Minimum-Gesetze gibt – etwa der kleinsten Wirkung – so gibt es in der Physik Kausalitätsgesetze, Gesetze von der Kausalitätsform.</german>
      <ogden>“Law of Causality” is a class name. And as in mechanics there are, for instance, minimum-laws, such as that of least actions, so in physics there are causal laws, laws of the causality form.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>‘Law of causality’—that is a general name. And just as in mechanics, for example, there are ‘minimum-principles’, such as the law of least action, so too in physics there are causal laws, laws of the causal form.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.3211" depth="4">
      <german>Man hat ja auch davon eine Ahnung gehabt, dass es ein „Gesetz der kleinsten Wirkung“ geben müsse, ehe man genau wusste, wie es lautete. (Hier, wie immer, stellt sich das a priori Gewisse als etwas rein Logisches heraus.)</german>
      <ogden>Men had indeed an idea that there must be a “law of least action”, before they knew exactly how it ran. (Here, as always, the a priori certain proves to be something purely logical.)</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Indeed people even surmised that there must be a ‘law of least action’ before they knew exactly how it went. (Here, as always, what is certain a priori proves to be something purely logical.)</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.33" depth="2">
      <german>Wir glauben nicht a priori an ein Erhaltungsgesetz, sondern wir wissen a priori die Möglichkeit einer logischen Form.</german>
      <ogden>We do not believe a priori in a law of conservation, but we know a priori the possibility of a logical form.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>We do not have an a priori belief in a law of conservation, but rather a priori knowledge of the possibility of a logical form.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.34" depth="2">
      <german>Alle jene Sätze, wie der Satz vom Grunde, von der Kontinuität in der Natur, vom kleinsten Aufwande in der Natur etc. etc., alle diese sind Einsichten a priori über die mögliche Formgebung der Sätze der Wissenschaft.</german>
      <ogden>All propositions, such as the law of causation, the law of continuity in nature, the law of least expenditure in nature, etc. etc., all these are a priori intuitions of possible forms of the propositions of science.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>All such propositions, including the principle of sufficient reason, the laws of continuity in nature and of least effort in nature, etc. etc.—all these are a priori insights about the forms in which the propositions of science can be cast.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.341" depth="3">
      <german>Die Newtonsche Mechanik z. B. bringt die Weltbeschreibung auf eine einheitliche Form. Denken wir uns eine weiße Fläche, auf der unregelmäßige schwarze Flecken wären. Wir sagen nun: Was für ein Bild immer hierdurch entsteht, immer kann ich seiner Beschreibung beliebig nahe kommen, indem ich die Fläche mit einem entsprechend feinen quadratischen Netzwerk bedecke und nun von jedem Quadrat sage, dass es weiß oder schwarz ist. Ich werde auf diese Weise die Beschreibung der Fläche auf eine einheitliche Form gebracht haben. Diese Form ist beliebig, denn ich hätte mit dem gleichen Erfolge ein Netz aus dreieckigen oder sechseckigen Maschen verwenden können. Es kann sein, dass die Beschreibung mit Hilfe eines Dreiecks-Netzes einfacher geworden wäre; das heißt, dass wir die Fläche mit einem gröberen Dreiecks-Netz genauer beschreiben könnten als mit einem feineren quadratischen (oder umgekehrt) usw. Den verschiedenen Netzen entsprechen verschiedene Systeme der Weltbeschreibung. Die Mechanik bestimmt eine Form der Weltbeschreibung, indem sie sagt: Alle Sätze der Weltbeschreibung müssen aus einer Anzahl gegebener Sätze – den mechanischen Axiomen – auf eine gegebene Art und Weise erhalten werden. Hierdurch liefert sie die Bausteine zum Bau des wissenschaftlichen Gebäudes und sagt: Welches Gebäude immer du aufführen willst, jedes musst du irgendwie mit diesen und nur diesen Bausteinen zusammenbringen.</german>
      <ogden>Newtonian mechanics, for example, brings the description of the universe to a unified form. Let us imagine a white surface with irregular black spots. We now say: Whatever kind of picture these make I can always get as near as I like to its description, if I cover the surface with a sufficiently fine square network and now say of every square that it is white or black. In this way I shall have brought the description of the surface to a unified form. This form is arbitrary, because I could have applied with equal success a net with a triangular or hexagonal mesh. It can happen that the description would have been simpler with the aid of a triangular mesh; that is to say we might have described the surface more accurately with a triangular, and coarser, than with the finer square mesh, or vice versa, and so on. To the different networks correspond different systems of describing the world. Mechanics determine a form of description by saying: All propositions in the description of the world must be obtained in a given way from a number of given propositions—the mechanical axioms. It thus provides the bricks for building the edifice of science, and says: Whatever building thou wouldst erect, thou shalt construct it in some manner with these bricks and these alone.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Newtonian mechanics, for example, imposes a unified form on the description of the world. Let us imagine a white surface with irregular black spots on it. We then say that whatever kind of picture these make, I can always approximate as closely as I wish to the description of it by covering the surface with a sufficiently fine square mesh, and then saying of every square whether it is black or white. In this way I shall have imposed a unified form on the description of the surface. The form is optional, since I could have achieved the same result by using a net with a triangular or hexagonal mesh. Possibly the use of a triangular mesh would have made the description simpler: that is to say, it might be that we could describe the surface more accurately with a coarse triangular mesh than with a fine square mesh (or conversely), and so on. The different nets correspond to different systems for describing the world. Mechanics determines one form of description of the world by saying that all propositions used in the description of the world must be obtained in a given way from a given set of propositions—the axioms of mechanics. It thus supplies the bricks for building the edifice of science, and it says, ‘Any building that you want to erect, whatever it may be, must somehow be constructed with these bricks, and with these alone.’</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.342" depth="3">
      <german>Und nun sehen wir die gegenseitige Stellung von Logik und Mechanik. (Man könnte das Netz auch aus verschiedenartigen Figuren etwa aus Dreiecken und Sechsecken bestehen lassen.) Dass sich ein Bild, wie das vorhin erwähnte, durch ein Netz von gegebener Form beschreiben lässt, sagt über das Bild nichts aus. (Denn dies gilt für jedes Bild dieser Art.) Das aber charakterisiert das Bild, dass es sich durch ein bestimmtes Netz von bestimmter Feinheit vollständig beschreiben lässt.</german>
      <ogden>And now we see the relative position of logic and mechanics. (We could construct the network out of figures of different kinds, as out of triangles and hexagons together.) That a picture like that instanced above can be described by a network of a given form asserts nothing about the picture. (For this holds of every picture of this kind.) But this does characterize the picture, the fact, namely, that it can be completely described by a definite net of definite fineness.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>And now we can see the relative position of logic and mechanics. (The net might also consist of more than one kind of mesh: e.g. we could use both triangles and hexagons.) The possibility of describing a picture like the one mentioned above with a net of a given form tells us nothing about the picture. (For that is true of all such pictures.) But what does characterize the picture is that it can be described completely by a particular net with a particular size of mesh.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.343" depth="3">
      <german>Die Mechanik ist ein Versuch, alle wahren Sätze, die wir zur Weltbeschreibung brauchen, nach Einem Plane zu konstruieren.</german>
      <ogden>Mechanics is an attempt to construct according to a single plan all true propositions which we need for the description of the world.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Mechanics is an attempt to construct according to a single plan all the true propositions that we need for the description of the world.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.3431" depth="4">
      <german>Durch den ganzen logischen Apparat hindurch sprechen die physikalischen Gesetze doch von den Gegenständen der Welt.</german>
      <ogden>Through their whole logical apparatus the physical laws still speak of the objects of the world.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The laws of physics, with all their logical apparatus, still speak, however indirectly, about the objects of the world.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.3432" depth="4">
      <german>Wir dürfen nicht vergessen, dass die Weltbeschreibung durch die Mechanik immer die ganz allgemeine ist. Es ist in ihr z. B. nie von bestimmten materiellen Punkten die Rede, sondern immer nur von irgend welchen .</german>
      <ogden>We must not forget that the description of the world by mechanics is always quite general. There is, for example, never any mention of particular material points in it, but always only of some points or other .</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>We ought not to forget that any description of the world by means of mechanics will be of the completely general kind. For example, it will never mention particular point-masses: it will only talk about any point-masses whatsoever .</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.35" depth="2">
      <german>Obwohl die Flecke in unserem Bild geometrische Figuren sind, so kann doch selbstverständlich die Geometrie gar nichts über ihre tatsächliche Form und Lage sagen. Das Netz aber ist rein geometrisch, alle seine Eigenschaften können a priori angegeben werden.</german>
      <ogden>Although the spots in our picture are geometrical figures, geometry can obviously say nothing about their actual form and position. But the network is purely geometrical, and all its properties can be given a priori.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Although the spots in our picture are geometrical figures, nevertheless geometry can obviously say nothing at all about their actual form and position. The network, however, is purely geometrical; all its properties can be given a priori .</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.36" depth="2">
      <german>Wenn es ein Kausalitätsgesetz gäbe, so könnte es lauten: „Es gibt Naturgesetze“.</german>
      <ogden>If there were a law of causality, it might run: “There are natural laws”.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>If there were a law of causality, it might be put in the following way: There are laws of nature.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.361" depth="3">
      <german>In der Ausdrucksweise Hertz’s  könnte man sagen: Nur gesetzmäßige Zusammenhänge sind denkbar .</german>
      <ogden>In the terminology of Hertz we might say: Only uniform connections are thinkable .</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>One might say, using Hertz’s terminology, that only connexions that are subject to law are thinkable .</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.3611" depth="4">
      <german>Wir können keinen Vorgang mit dem „Ablauf der Zeit“ vergleichen – diesen gibt es nicht –, sondern nur mit einem anderen Vorgang (etwa mit dem Gang des Chronometers).</german>
      <ogden>We cannot compare any process with the “passage of time”—there is no such thing—but only with another process (say, with the movement of the chronometer).</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>We cannot compare a process with ‘the passage of time’—there is no such thing—but only with another process (such as the working of a chronometer).</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.36111" depth="5">
      <german>Das Kant’sche Problem von der rechten und linken Hand, die man nicht zur Deckung bringen kann, besteht schon in der Ebene, ja im eindimensionalen Raum, wo die beiden kongruenten Figuren a und b auch nicht zur Deckung gebracht werden können, ohne aus diesem Raum</german>
      <ogden>The Kantian problem of the right and left hand which cannot be made to cover one another already exists in the plane, and even in one-dimensional space; where the two congruent figures a and b cannot be made to cover one another without</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Kant’s problem about the right hand and the left hand, which cannot be made to coincide, exists even in two dimensions. Indeed, it exists in one-dimensional space</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.362" depth="3">
      <german>Was sich beschreiben lässt, das kann auch geschehen, und was das Kausalitätsgesetz ausschließen soll, das lässt sich auch nicht beschreiben.</german>
      <ogden>What can be described can happen too, and what is excluded by the law of causality cannot be described.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>What can be described can happen too: and what the law of causality is meant to exclude cannot even be described.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.363" depth="3">
      <german>Der Vorgang der Induktion besteht darin, dass wir das einfachste Gesetz annehmen, das mit unseren Erfahrungen in Einklang zu bringen ist.</german>
      <ogden>The process of induction is the process of assuming the simplest law that can be made to harmonize with our experience.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The procedure of induction consists in accepting as true the simplest law that can be reconciled with our experiences.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.3631" depth="4">
      <german>Dieser Vorgang hat aber keine logische, sondern nur eine psychologische Begründung.</german>
      <ogden>This process, however, has no logical foundation but only a psychological one.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>This procedure, however, has no logical justification but only a psychological one.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.36311" depth="5">
      <german>Dass die Sonne morgen aufgehen wird, ist eine Hypothese; und das heißt: wir wissen nicht, ob sie aufgehen wird.</german>
      <ogden>That the sun will rise to-morrow, is an hypothesis; and that means that we do not know whether it will rise.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>It is an hypothesis that the sun will rise tomorrow: and this means that we do not know whether it will rise.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.37" depth="2">
      <german>Einen Zwang, nach dem Eines geschehen müsste, weil etwas anderes geschehen ist, gibt es nicht. Es gibt nur eine logische Notwendigkeit.</german>
      <ogden>A necessity for one thing to happen because another has happened does not exist. There is only logical necessity.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>There is no compulsion making one thing happen because another has happened. The only necessity that exists is logical necessity</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.371" depth="3">
      <german>Der ganzen modernen Weltanschauung liegt die Täuschung zugrunde, dass die sogenannten Naturgesetze die Erklärungen der Naturerscheinungen seien.</german>
      <ogden>At the basis of the whole modern view of the world lies the illusion that the so-called laws of nature are the explanations of natural phenomena.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The whole modern conception of the world is founded on the illusion that the so-called laws of nature are the explanations of natural phenomena.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.372" depth="3">
      <german>So bleiben sie bei den Naturgesetzen als bei etwas Unantastbarem stehen, wie die Älteren bei Gott und dem Schicksal.</german>
      <ogden>So people stop short at natural laws as something unassailable, as did the ancients at God and Fate.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Thus people today stop at the laws of nature, treating them as something inviolable, just as God and Fate were treated in past ages.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.373" depth="3">
      <german>Die Welt ist unabhängig von meinem Willen.</german>
      <ogden>The world is independent of my will.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The world is independent of my will.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.374" depth="3">
      <german>Auch wenn alles, was wir wünschen, geschähe, so wäre dies doch nur, sozusagen, eine Gnade des Schicksals, denn es ist kein logischer Zusammenhang zwischen Willen und Welt, der dies verbürgte, und den angenommenen physikalischen Zusammenhang könnten wir doch nicht selbst wieder wollen.</german>
      <ogden>Even if everything we wished were to happen, this would only be, so to speak, a favour of fate, for there is no logical connexion between will and world, which would guarantee this, and the assumed physical connexion itself we could not again will.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Even if all that we wish for were to happen, still this would only be a favour granted by fate, so to speak: for there is no logical connexion between the will and the world, which would guarantee it, and the supposed physical connexion itself is surely not something that we could will.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.375" depth="3">
      <german>Wie es nur eine logische Notwendigkeit gibt, so gibt es auch nur eine logische Unmöglichkeit.</german>
      <ogden>As there is only a logical necessity, so there is only a logical impossibility.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Just as the only necessity that exists is logical necessity, so too the only impossibility that exists is logical impossibility.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.3751" depth="4">
      <german>Dass z. B. zwei Farben zugleich an einem Ort des Gesichtsfeldes sind, ist unmöglich, und zwar logisch unmöglich, denn es ist durch die logische Struktur der Farbe ausgeschlossen.</german>
      <ogden>For two colours, e.g. to be at one place in the visual field, is impossible, logically impossible, for it is excluded by the logical structure of colour.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>For example, the simultaneous presence of two colours at the same place in the visual field is impossible, in fact logically impossible, since it is ruled out by the logical structure of colour.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.4" depth="1">
      <german>Alle Sätze sind gleichwertig.</german>
      <ogden>All propositions are of equal value.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>All propositions are of equal value.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.41" depth="2">
      <german>Der Sinn der Welt muss außerhalb ihrer liegen. In der Welt ist alles, wie es ist, und geschieht alles, wie es geschieht; es gibt in ihr keinen Wert – und wenn es ihn gäbe, so hätte er keinen Wert.</german>
      <ogden>The sense of the world must lie outside the world. In the world everything is as it is and happens as it does happen. In it there is no value—and if there were, it would be of no value.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The sense of the world must lie outside the world. In the world everything is as it is, and everything happens as it does happen: in it no value exists—and if it did exist, it would have no value.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.42" depth="2">
      <german>Darum kann es auch keine Sätze der Ethik geben.</german>
      <ogden>Hence also there can be no ethical propositions.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>So too it is impossible for there to be propositions of ethics.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.421" depth="3">
      <german>Es ist klar, dass sich die Ethik nicht aussprechen lässt.</german>
      <ogden>It is clear that ethics cannot be expressed.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>It is clear that ethics cannot be put into words.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.422" depth="3">
      <german>Der erste Gedanke bei der Aufstellung eines ethischen Gesetzes von der Form „du sollst . . . .“ ist: Und was dann, wenn ich es nicht tue? Es ist aber klar, dass die Ethik nichts mit Strafe und Lohn im gewöhnlichen Sinne zu tun hat. Also muss diese Frage nach den Folgen einer Handlung belanglos sein. – Zum Mindesten dürfen diese Folgen nicht Ereignisse sein. Denn etwas muss doch an jener Fragestellung richtig sein. Es muss zwar eine Art von ethischem Lohn und ethischer Strafe geben, aber diese müssen in der Handlung selbst liegen.</german>
      <ogden>The first thought in setting up an ethical law of the form “thou shalt …” is: And what if I do not do it? But it is clear that ethics has nothing to do with punishment and reward in the ordinary sense. This question as to the consequences of an action must therefore be irrelevant. At least these consequences will not be events. For there must be something right in that formulation of the question. There must be some sort of ethical reward and ethical punishment, but this must lie in the action itself.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>When an ethical law of the form, ‘Thou shalt …’ is laid down, one’s first thought is, ‘And what if I do not do it?’ It is clear, however, that ethics has nothing to do with punishment and reward in the usual sense of the terms. So our question about the consequences of an action must be unimportant.—At least those consequences should not be events. For there must be something right about the question we posed. There must indeed be some kind of ethical reward and ethical punishment, but they must reside in the action itself.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.423" depth="3">
      <german>Vom Willen als dem Träger des Ethischen kann nicht gesprochen werden.</german>
      <ogden>Of the will as the subject of the ethical we cannot speak.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>It is impossible to speak about the will in so far as it is the subject of ethical attributes.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.43" depth="2">
      <german>Wenn das gute oder böse Wollen die Welt ändert, so kann es nur die Grenzen der Welt ändern, nicht die Tatsachen; nicht das, was durch die Sprache ausgedrückt werden kann.</german>
      <ogden>If good or bad willing changes the world, it can only change the limits of the world, not the facts; not the things that can be expressed in language.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>If the good or bad exercise of the will does alter the world, it can alter only the limits of the world, not the facts—not what can be expressed by means of language.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.431" depth="3">
      <german>Wie auch beim Tod die Welt sich nicht ändert, sondern aufhört.</german>
      <ogden>As in death, too, the world does not change, but ceases.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>So too at death the world does not alter, but comes to an end.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.4311" depth="4">
      <german>Der Tod ist kein Ereignis des Lebens. Den Tod erlebt man nicht.</german>
      <ogden>Death is not an event of life. Death is not lived through.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Death is not an event in life: we do not live to experience death.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.4312" depth="4">
      <german>Die zeitliche Unsterblichkeit der Seele des Menschen, das heißt also ihr ewiges Fortleben auch nach dem Tode, ist nicht nur auf keine Weise verbürgt, sondern vor allem leistet diese Annahme gar nicht das, was man immer mit ihr erreichen wollte. Wird denn dadurch ein Rätsel gelöst, dass ich ewig fortlebe? Ist denn dieses ewige Leben dann nicht ebenso rätselhaft wie das gegenwärtige? Die Lösung des Rätsels des Lebens in Raum und Zeit liegt außerhalb von Raum und Zeit.</german>
      <ogden>The temporal immortality of the human soul, that is to say, its eternal survival also after death, is not only in no way guaranteed, but this assumption in the first place will not do for us what we always tried to make it do. Is a riddle solved by the fact that I survive for ever? Is this eternal life not as enigmatic as our present one? The solution of the riddle of life in space and time lies outside space and time.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Not only is there no guarantee of the temporal immortality of the human soul, that is to say of its eternal survival after death; but, in any case, this assumption completely fails to accomplish the purpose for which it has always been intended. Or is some riddle solved by my surviving for ever? Is not this eternal life itself as much of a riddle as our present life? The solution of the riddle of life in space and time lies outside space and time.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.432" depth="3">
      <german>Wie die Welt ist, ist für das Höhere vollkommen gleichgültig. Gott offenbart sich nicht in der Welt.</german>
      <ogden>How the world is, is completely indifferent for what is higher. God does not reveal himself in the world.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>How things are in the world is a matter of complete indifference for what is higher. God does not reveal himself in the world.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.4321" depth="4">
      <german>Die Tatsachen gehören alle nur zur Aufgabe, nicht zur Lösung.</german>
      <ogden>The facts all belong only to the task and not to its performance.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The facts all contribute only to setting the problem, not to its solution.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.44" depth="2">
      <german>Nicht wie die Welt ist, ist das Mystische, sondern dass sie ist.</german>
      <ogden>Not how the world is, is the mystical, but that it is.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>It is not how things are in the world that is mystical, but that it exists.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.45" depth="2">
      <german>Die Anschauung der Welt sub specie aeterni ist ihre Anschauung als – begrenztes – Ganzes.</german>
      <ogden>The contemplation of the world sub specie aeterni is its contemplation as a limited whole.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>To view the world sub specie aeterni is to view it as a whole—a limited whole.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.5" depth="1">
      <german>Zu einer Antwort, die man nicht aussprechen kann, kann man auch die Frage nicht aussprechen.</german>
      <ogden>For an answer which cannot be expressed the question too cannot be expressed.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>When the answer cannot be put into words, neither can the question be put into words.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.51" depth="2">
      <german>Skeptizismus ist nicht unwiderleglich, sondern offenbar unsinnig, wenn er bezweifeln will, wo nicht gefragt werden kann.</german>
      <ogden>Scepticism is not irrefutable, but palpably senseless, if it would doubt where a question cannot be asked.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>Scepticism is not irrefutable, but obviously nonsensical, when it tries to raise doubts where no questions can be asked.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.52" depth="2">
      <german>Wir fühlen, daß selbst, wenn alle möglichen wissenschaftlichen Fragen beantwortet sind, unsere Lebensprobleme noch gar nicht berührt sind. Freilich bleibt dann eben keine Frage mehr; und eben dies ist die Antwort.</german>
      <ogden>We feel that even if all possible scientific questions be answered, the problems of life have still not been touched at all. Of course there is then no question left, and just this is the answer.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>We feel that even when all possible scientific questions have been answered, the problems of life remain completely untouched. Of course there are then no questions left, and this itself is the answer.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.521" depth="3">
      <german>Die Lösung des Problems des Lebens merkt man am Verschwinden dieses Problems.</german>
      <ogden>The solution of the problem of life is seen in the vanishing of this problem.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The solution of the problem of life is seen in the vanishing of the problem.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.522" depth="3">
      <german>Es gibt allerdings Unaussprechliches. Dies zeigt sich, es ist das Mystische.</german>
      <ogden>There is indeed the inexpressible. This shows itself; it is the mystical.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>There are, indeed, things that cannot be put into words. They make themselves manifest . They are what is mystical.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.53" depth="2">
      <german>Die richtige Methode der Philosophie wäre eigentlich die: Nichts zu sagen, als was sich sagen lässt, also Sätze der Naturwissenschaft – also etwas, was mit Philosophie nichts zu tun hat – , und dann immer, wenn ein anderer etwas Metaphysisches sagen wollte, ihm nachzuweisen, dass er gewissen Zeichen in seinen Sätzen keine Bedeutung gegeben hat. Diese Methode wäre für den anderen unbefriedigend – er hätte nicht das Gefühl, dass wir ihn Philosophie lehrten – aber sie wäre die einzig streng richtige.</german>
      <ogden>The right method of philosophy would be this: To say nothing except what can be said, i.e. the propositions of natural science, i.e. something that has nothing to do with philosophy: and then always, when someone else wished to say something metaphysical, to demonstrate to him that he had given no meaning to certain signs in his propositions. This method would be unsatisfying to the other—he would not have the feeling that we were teaching him philosophy—but it would be the only strictly correct method.</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>The correct method in philosophy would really be the following: to say nothing except what can be said, i.e. propositions of natural science—i.e. something that has nothing to do with philosophy—and then, whenever someone else wanted to say something metaphysical, to demonstrate to him that he had failed to give a meaning to certain signs in his propositions. Although it would not be satisfying to the other person—he would not have the feeling that we were teaching him philosophy— this method would be the only strictly correct one.</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
    <proposition id="6.54" depth="2">
      <german>Meine Sätze erläutern dadurch, dass sie der, welcher mich versteht, am Ende als unsinnig erkennt, wenn er durch sie – auf ihnen – über sie hinausgestiegen ist. (Er muss sozusagen die Leiter wegwerfen, nachdem er auf ihr hinaufgestiegen ist.)</german>
      <ogden>My propositions are elucidatory in this way: he who understands me finally recognizes them as senseless, when he has climbed out through them, on them, over them. (He must so to speak throw away the ladder, after he has climbed up on it.)</ogden>
      <pears_mcguinness>My propositions serve as elucidations in the following way: anyone who understands me eventually recognizes them as nonsensical, when he has used them—as steps—to climb up beyond them. (He must, so to speak, throw away the ladder after he has climbed up it.)</pears_mcguinness>
    </proposition>
  </proposition>
  <proposition id="7" depth="0">
    <german>Wovon man nicht sprechen kann, darüber muss man schweigen.</german>
    <ogden>Whereof one cannot speak, thereof one must be silent.</ogden>
    <pears_mcguinness>What we cannot speak about we must pass over in silence.</pears_mcguinness>
  </proposition>
</tractatus>